<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" lang="en-GB"><head><title>???</title><meta content="Hamilton" name="author"/><meta content="2015-09-28T21:15:00Z" name="dcterms.created"/><meta content="2015-09-28T21:15:00Z" name="dcterms.modified"/><meta content="United Christian Broadcasters Australia Ltd" name="dcterms.publisher"/><meta content="XMLmind Word To XML Professional Edition 1.0.0-beta04" name="generator"/></head><body>
<p>Fri 21 August 2015</p>
<p>‘…God’s Spirit, who is in you, is greater than the devil, who is in the world.’ 1 John 4:4 NCV</p>
<p>It’s Dangerous to Go Alone (3)</p>
<p>John was writing to a church that was hard pressed, with heavy persecution on all sides. They were afraid, tired, and may have been starting to feel like perhaps all this just wasn’t worth it. How could they keep going back to God when all they seemed to do was fail, and get attacked by outsiders?<br></br>The answer, of course, is Jesus. The last few days’ readings have been full of challenges, and so today’s verse should ground us nicely: the one ‘who is in the world’, whose goal it is to harm us, has already been defeated. When Jesus stretched out His nail–pierced hands on the cross, He ‘stripped the rulers and authorities of their power and made a public spectacle of them.’ (Colossians 2:15 GWT) Satan wants us to be separated from God, but to do that, He’d have to get through Jesus first. Nothing can separate us from Him.<br></br>This all adds up to something very, very important: God has ‘given you authority over all the power of the enemy.’ (Luke 10:19 NLT) Whatever it is you’re facing, you can declare your authority over it through Jesus—something Satan would rather you didn’t know. So take a moment to think about the challenges you’re up against today and tomorrow. Don’t let anxiety or worry come between you and Jesus; take hold of the authority He gives you and, with His help, learn to overcome those challenges. </p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 16–18, Mark 7:24–37, Ps 119:113–120, Prov 22:1–3</p></body><body>
<p>Sat 22 August 2015</p>
<p>‘By faith Noah…built an ark to save his family...’ Hebrews 11:7 NIV</p>
<p>Get To Noah Your Bible Better</p>
<p>Ok, let’s talk Noah. Anyone picturing pretty Sunday school drawings of rainbows, and old toy sets with missing giraffes? The story of Noah has been retold so many times most of us know it off by heart, but have a read of Genesis 6–9 for a recap. Go on, we’ll wait right here. We reckon there’s something to take away from this that often gets missed: Noah was probably seen as a bit of a nutter. <br></br>Imagine seeing a guy creating a massive boat, on land, inviting a bunch of wild animals to climb aboard and then getting in there himself with his wife and kids. Strange, right? But Noah’s focus wasn’t on what everyone else was thinking, his focus was on what God was doing. We’re told in Genesis 6:9 NIV that he ‘…walked faithfully with God.’ He was willing to listen and follow God’s instructions every step of the way, because he was trusting that God would protect him. In Genesis 7:16 it says: ‘Then the Lord shut him in.’ So, what about us? How can we follow God’s instructions and live knowing that He’s protecting us? What would give us the confidence to live like Noah? Or the ability to trust in God in a way that would be utterly strange if He didn’t exist? Surely He could at least give us some sort of manual that outlines the pitfalls of life and gives us instructions about how to live for Him… Oh, yeah. He did. The Bible. Basic Instructions Before Leaving Earth. So close your door and spend an hour praying, studying the Bible, worshipping… dedicate just 60 minutes today to meeting with God in private.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 19–21, Mark 8:1–13, Ps 119:121–128, Prov 22:4–7</p></body><body>
<p>Sun 23 August 2015</p>
<p>‘…Don’t say, “Come back tomorrow, and then I’ll help you.”’ Proverbs 3:28 NLT</p>
<p>The Dog Ate My Kingdom Work… </p>
<p>Proverbs is a good ‘go–to’ book in the Bible, isn’t it? Full of all that wisdom plus verses short enough for handy encouragement texts (seriously, this is not being sarcastic—choose one and text a friend). But every now and again, we read a Proverb that makes us do that ‘oops’ noise, and suddenly we’re feeling just a little bit uncomfortable. That, friends, is conviction. When we spot something that God tells us to do or not do, and our minds instantly flick to a particular situation, person or thing that’s going on in our lives? Today’s verse can make that happen, can’t it? In full, it says: ‘Do not withhold good from those to whom it is due, when it is in your power to act. Do not say to your neighbour, “Come back tomorrow and I’ll give it to you” when you already have it with you.’ (Proverbs 3:28 NIV) Being a Christian is tough, we want to help people but it can take so much time, money and energy. Have a look at Luke 9:57–62 to see how Jesus reacted to people’s excuses. Oop. So, here’s a gutsy thought, what if we stopped making excuses and started seizing those opportunities to build God’s Kingdom? For as much of today as possible, do everything reasonable that you’re asked to, right away. And while you’re at it, do the same for the stuff you’re not even directly asked to do. If your gran asks you to call her, drop what you’re doing and pick up your phone. If someone in your house uses the last of the milk, go get some right away. You get the idea.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 17:8–16, 2 Cor 1:3–7</p></body><body>
<p>Mon 24 August 2015</p>
<p>‘God places the lonely in families...’ Psalm 68:6 NLT</p>
<p>Family: Retro vs. Real</p>
<p>White picket fence, cute little porch, dinner table laughs and not an argument in sight. Ahh, family. And that’s the end of today’s reading. Bye... <br></br>Oh? That’s not how it goes? Yeah. Family life can be tough. In fact, every family is different. Maybe you actually *do* have a picket fence, but perhaps your reality is far from picket–fence perfection. Whatever your experience of family, your choice to become a Christian is the choice to adopt, and be adopted into, another Family. <br></br>In John 1:12 we’re described as ‘children of God.’ Now this definitely still isn’t a 1950s advert family with little Jimmy and his Dad playing catch in the back yard. There will still be times when you’re frustrated, upset and disappointed by other Christians. But the concept of family does reflect some of the ways God calls us to act. We’re expected to honour and respect others (have a look at 1 Timothy 5:1–2), and we need to look out for one another (Galatians 6:10). Being a part of God’s family is always going to be a challenge, but when we work together to see lives changed we learn to reflect the heart of God. Think about someone who’s made a difference in your life over the past few years. Maybe someone who isn’t even a huge part of your life any more. Figure out the best way to get in touch with them, and thank them for whatever–it–is they’ve done, or given to you. Ask them if there’s anything you can do to show your appreciation, and give back to them. </p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 22–24, Mark 8:14–26, Ps 119:129–136, Prov 22:8–10</p></body><body>
<p>Tue 25 August 2015</p>
<p>‘For I can do everything through Christ, who gives me strength.’ Philippians 4:13 NLT</p>
<p>Bubble–wrap socks</p>
<p>A stubbed toe as you go to the bathroom, an empty milk carton as you get breakfast and, by lunchtime you realise you’ve been in a foul mood all morning. Sometimes, the little things that go wrong can make us massively grumpy. That’s without even getting onto the more serious stuff that goes wrong. So how on earth did Paul manage to say that he ‘…learned the secret of living in every situation…’ (Philippians 4:12 NLT)? Had he created a bubble wrap sock that protected his toes from ever getting stubbed? Or maybe he’d taken to hiding the milk to ensure there was enough left for his bowl of maple pecan crispies? <br></br>Doubt it; we reckon it’s probably more to do with the spiritual choices he was making. He was choosing to spend time praising God, even when things were looking pretty bleak. He believed in a God who was greater than his circumstances and more powerful than his emotions. So… the secret? Take a look at Philippians 4:4… Yep. Rejoicing. That doesn’t necessarily mean you have to click your heels together like you’re in a stage show (though, if that’s your thing, go you). The original Greek for rejoicing, ‘chairo’, is often translated as meaning ‘to experience God’s grace’, or be ‘conscious of His favour’. Let’s stay conscious of that grace today and be like Paul; let’s go out there, rejoicing. So: sing. Seriously. Sing the most cheerful worship song you can think of, out of doors, today. Even better, grab some friends and have a little worship session somewhere open. Remember, the key is to share your ‘chairo’ with the world, so joyful head bob dances get extra points.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 25–28, Mark 8:27–38, Ps 119:137–144, Prov 22:11–13</p></body><body>
<p>Wed 26 August 2015</p>
<p>‘…God, who began the good work within you, will continue…until it is finally finished...’ Philippians 1:6 NLT</p>
<p>Renovate Good Times, C’mon (1)</p>
<p>Ever watch those TV shows where they try to decorate a house before the owners arrive back? They’re always the same, you get the stressful middle bit, the overly emotional ending, and at least two garish ‘feature walls’. And sometimes our lives are the same too (minus the feature walls): that bit in the middle where everyone stresses out, followed by the emotional fallout. <br></br>When we’re so keen to see ourselves change (to quit that habit, to be more Christ–like, to pursue what’s holy—all good things) we can forget that it’s only possible with God’s Spirit. We try it alone, we stress and pressure ourselves to improve, which can send us crashing into all sorts of negative places. Just like the makeover shows, though, God wants to renovate you. Take a look at what’s on offer in Philippians 1:9–11 NIV: ‘…depth of insight’, ‘pure and blameless’, ‘filled with the fruit of righteousness’? Sounds kind of huge. But God’s a renovation pro. The Holy Spirit is the only one that can renovate and refresh you, and make you more like the Christian you desire to be. When we allow God’s Spirit to work on the stuff that we can’t, we begin to see change. When you’re done pondering over the things that might need renovating in your own heart, find something to renovate for someone else. Clean up something that you don’t use—an old phone, a games console, some decent clothes that aren’t your style now—and give it to someone who really will use it. Think big, and get creative. </p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 29–31, Mark 9:1–13, Ps 119:145–160, Prov 22:14–16</p></body><body>
<p>Thu 27 August 2015</p>
<p>‘…God is working in you, giving you the desire and the power to do what pleases Him.’ Philippians 2:13 NLT</p>
<p>Renovate Good Times, C’mon (2)</p>
<p>Yesterday we looked at change from God. Today we’re looking at desires from God: the kind of desires that are for God’s masterplan for creation. In Philippians 2:13 NIV it says God works in us ‘…in order to fulfil His good purpose.’ You see, inviting Jesus into our lives opens us up to being ambassadors, to being the ones in this world to translate God’s will into action. <br></br>The more we seek God, the more we desire Him and His purpose. His desires become ours, and they’re achieved through the individuality and unique talents He’s given to us. In John 15:5 NIV, Jesus said: ‘I am the vine; you are the branches. If you remain in Me and I in you, you will bear much fruit; apart from Me you can do nothing.’ Our desires must stem from our desire for God. When we seek God, whether it’s through His Word, time spent in worship or in prayer, we learn to listen to God’s heart. In Psalm 37:4 NIV it says, ‘Take delight in the Lord, and He will give you the desires of your heart.’ When our heartbeat gets in step with God’s, amazing, powerful stuff happens, and the world learns what Christians are *really* about. Think and pray about a problem in your local community or the wider world that you’d like to help alleviate. Plan a practical action today to do something about that issue. Then do it!</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 32–34, Mark 9:14–29, Ps 119:161–168, Prov 22:17–19</p></body><body>
<p>Fri 28 August 2015</p>
<p>‘I press on toward the goal to win the prize for which God has called me...’ Philippians 3:14 NIV</p>
<p>Nope. No. No can do.</p>
<p>Hold onto your pyjamas, we’re about take a step back here. Believe it or not, people deciding to live generously are actually allowed to say the word ‘no’. Wow. Great, we can get out of stacking the chairs at church now? Not exactly, let’s have a look at when it’s appropriate. We’ve been looking at God–filled change and desire over the past few days, and now it’s time to think about how those things can get crowded out sometimes. <br></br>Often we find ourselves in the Christian habit of saying ‘yes’ to just about everything we get asked to do, especially when it’s at church. Let’s get one thing straight, making ourselves available to serve isn’t a bad thing: in fact, the Bible says God honours anyone that serves Jesus. (John 12:26) But when we start to say ‘yes’ to too many things, we’re in danger of giving a half–hearted effort, and our God–filled desires often begin to get cut short. We end up confused about our priorities, and it’s our own time with God that usually suffers the most. <br></br>If we really do want to ‘press on’ towards godliness (Philippians 3:14 style), we have to make sure that we’re not going to burn out. Reaching forwards takes energy, and effort. Let’s use our Spirit–led desires to discern (1) what we need to say ‘yes’ to, (2) what we need to put on a back burner or even (3) turn down completely. And if you’ve found it hard to know what you should say ‘no’ to, then ask God for the gift of discernment so that you know what He does and doesn’t want you to take on. </p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 35–36, 2 Jn, Mark 9:30–37, Ps 119:169–176, Prov 22:20–23</p></body><body>
<p>Sat 29 August 2015</p>
<p>‘…It was my closest friend, the one I trusted most.’ Psalm 55:13 CEV </p>
<p>Close–Range Pain (1)</p>
<p>Close–range shots hurt most (ever been paintballing?) And it’s the same with emotional stuff. We get wounded if something close to our hearts, or someone we trust, turns out to be not quite how we thought. Betrayal, man. It stings (King David felt it—read the whole of today’s Psalm). Even if you’re not the type to admit to feeling ‘wounded’ when stuff you counted on goes wrong, it still affects you, leaving you feeling generally miffed with the world, or losing sleep. Betrayal, and other messy life–stuff, throws us out of balance. And, truth is, not dealing with it properly affects our relationship with God. This might feel like a tough idea, but not taking time to work through those it separates us from the fullness of God’s grace. Matthew 6:14–15 brings that home.<br></br>Also, not dealing with hurt can lead us into a new sense of not–quite–full–trust towards God. The likelihood is, you’re not yelling at the sky, raging at God. Perhaps something just feels slightly… off. We’re not saying that it’s a conscious act, but the stuff that sits on our heart changes its landscape. And there’s only one thing that fixes it. Honesty. With God. And yourself. It’s ok to be hurt. It’s not un–Christian. It’s not petty. It’s human. And, guess what? You’re one of those. <br></br>We need to learn to hand over the deep stuff to the Holy Spirit. Go for a 30 minute prayer walk today, and assess whether anything is sitting, undealt with, in your mind. Talk to God about it, 100% honestly. Keep nothing back. Invite Him to heal you.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 3 Jn, Jude, Mark 9:38–50, Ps 84, Prov 22:24–26</p></body><body>
<p>Sun 30 August 2015</p>
<p>‘God…will hear me and humble them.’ Psalm 55:19 NLT</p>
<p>Close–Range Pain (2)</p>
<p>Ok, hopefully you went for a prayer walk yesterday. And hopefully you’ve identified some of the stuff that’s been pressing on your mind and heart, and are now working through with God. <br></br>And the next step after that? Well, maybe there isn’t one. It could be that once you’ve acknowledged what’s going on inside of you, and taken it to God, you’re done. Often, all we need to ‘get over something’ is to actually face up to the thing itself. Maybe, then, you can just keep praying it through, and you’ll be A–OK. If, however you feel like you need an extra step forwards to feel completely ‘over it’, then we have an idea or two. (We’re going to interrupt ourselves here to tell you to spend five minutes praying it through again. Come back and carry on reading from here when you’re done, though.) <br></br>(1) Talk to the person or people or organisation involved. Do it rationally, calmly, and with as much grace as you (and Jesus through you) can muster, but *do* talk about the fact that you’re hurt. <br></br>(2) If, after doing that, you’re still hurt, talk to someone else—a trusted, older friend. Sometimes, if the hurt goes deep, we need that outside perspective. <br></br>It can be really powerful to keep looking out to others, even if you’re going through hurt. Pay for someone’s cup of coffee today. If you find yourself in a coffee shop, ask the person next in the queue what they want, and pay for it. If you don’t have the cash to do that, strike up a conversation with them instead. Or spend a minute praying for them.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 11:1–9, Phil 2:1–11</p></body><body>
<p>Mon 31 August 2015</p>
<p>‘Abram believed the Lord, and the Lord counted him as righteous because of his faith.’ Genesis 15:6 NLT</p>
<p>Give It Some Heart</p>
<p>We got a bit nerdy and looked up ‘wholeheartedness’ in the Oxford English Dictionary (other dictionaries are available…but this one makes us sound more cleverer). ‘Wholeheartedness’ is all about sincerity and commitment. You could describe Abraham that way. Sincere. Committed. Yep, he was so God–fearing he was willing to sacrifice his only son (have a read of Genesis 22:1–19 for a reminder). That’s sincere faith, right there. And when you look at how God responded to this kind of faith it’s a good reminder of how we should be willing to live. In Genesis 22:17 NLT God says through an angel that He will ‘…certainly bless’ Abraham. Genesis 22:18 goes on: God says ‘…through your descendants all the nations of the earth will be blessed—all because you have obeyed Me.’ <br></br>Wow. When we’re willing to put in extra effort for God, He certainly notices it. When we learn to live out our faith with heart, He blesses whatever work we’re doing for Him. Now that doesn’t mean that playing in the worship group has a direct correlation to the dollars in your bank balance. But it does mean that, when you give it absolutely everything you’ve got, living with a generous heart, you’ll begin to see God at work and learn to recognise His blessings. So, how can we sacrifice? Well, have a wardrobe clearout. Among the too–small t–shirts and last year’s jeans, give away something that you like. If Abraham could prepare to sacrifice his son, you can sacrifice that jumper. Give the clothes to someone who might be struggling to get new ones or, if you don’t know anyone who is, take them to a charity shop.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Josh 1–4, Mark 10:1–12, Ps 103:1–12, Prov 22:27–29</p></body><body>
<p>Tue 1 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…It is more blessed to give than to receive.’ Acts 20:35 NIV</p>
<p>Why Is It Better To Give?</p>
<p>Maybe it would have been easier if Jesus had just said: ‘Receiving things is great! Giving things, mmm yeah, that’s nice too, once in a while...’ Doesn’t Jesus realise how hard it is to give sometimes? We get that He gave Himself for us, and so Christians should be willing to give too. However, people can be really ungrateful and it just ends up being so much hard work. <br></br>What if Jesus wasn’t only telling us to ‘give’ for the benefit of others (those we’re giving stuff to) but for our own benefit too? God designed us in His image (Genesis 1:26), and the image of God is one of someone who gives. Say what now? Let’s dig into another version of today’s verse to expand on what Jesus is getting at. The CEV edition says: ‘More blessings come from giving than from receiving.’ As we said yesterday, it doesn’t mean we’ll get insta–rich. It means we will be blessed by giving because in giving we will become more Christ–like. We will find contentment because we’ll be acting more like Jesus. And that’s really something amazing. When, through giving, we find that deep contentment, we’re less likely to crave getting ‘stuff’ from other people in the first place. Think about the last thing that God gave to you: a particular exciting task or job, or good experience, even just your last meal. Can you find a way to mirror God’s act of giving, and replicate it for someone else? That might be a task that requires thought and creativity, but it’ll be worth it.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Josh 5:1–8:29, Mark 10:13–22, Ps 103:13–22, Prov 23:1–3</p></body><body>
<p>Wed 2 September </p>
<p>‘…It is more blessed to give than to receive.’ Acts 20:35 NKJ</p>
<p>Giving Takes Guts</p>
<p>Whether you find stepping up in front of people easy or you’d rather remain anonymous, giving takes guts. It takes initiative. Taking initiative is all about looking a situation up and down, and grabbing the opportunity within it—picking up the mess after the party is over, chatting to the newbie at church. It took initiative for the Good Samaritan to do what two others had failed to do. Read Luke 10:25–37 and see what sets him apart from the do–gooders… go on, we’ll wait here. <br></br>You see, we don’t know whether that Samaritan was an outgoing guy, or whether he was shy, worried about what people would think and say. We don’t know if he found stepping out like that really simple or super difficult. Either way, he did it. Whatever he might have felt, he responded immediately. Jesus describes the Samaritan as a ‘neighbour to the man.’ (Luke 10:36 NIV) How amazing would it be for Christians (especially those who’d rather not make a big deal about it) to be known as people who are neighbours to everyone in every situation, jumping in with compassion when others don’t? For those of us who wouldn’t class ourselves as outgoing types, there may be an extra leap needed towards acts of generosity. But that leap, even when it’s difficult, is 100% worth it. That’s what Jesus is getting at when He says, ‘Go and do likewise.’ (Luke 10:37 NIV) Off you go, then.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Josh 8:30–10:43, Mark 10:23–34, Ps 111, Prov 23:4–6</p></body><body>
<p>Thu 3 September </p>
<p>‘But Jesus often withdrew to lonely places and prayed.’ Luke 5:16 NIV</p>
<p>Prayer is Major</p>
<p>Someone asked American pastor Tim Keller, ‘What’s one piece of advice you would tell your younger self, or something you wished you knew then that you know now about the Lord?’ Tim tweeted back: ‘I would tell him that prayer is way more important than he thinks.’ <br></br>Prayer is major. Though it can be tough to find time to properly sit and chat with God, and we can stress ourselves even more by feeling guilty when we compare our prayer habits to our prays–every–second friend. (Yeah, stop that! Prayer is your personal business, and comparisons help no–one). Sooo, what to do when it feels like we’re just too busy, when we literally don’t have a spare minute? <br></br>In Mark 1:35 NIV, it says: ‘Very early in the morning, while it was still dark, Jesus got up, left the house and went off to a solitary place, where He prayed.’ Getting up early is grim, especially when it’s still dark out. But Jesus did it. Why? Because He was making time to pray in the middle of a busy stretch. We might have to get up early to ensure we get that one on one time with God. But if Jesus thought it was important to make time for it, maybe we should too. <br></br>So, inconvenience yourself. Set two alarms on your phone today/tomorrow: the first for a pre–sunrise prayer time. Ask God to direct you towards selfless acts during the day. Use the second alarm to remind you to go out of your way to give your time and energy to anyone within range. (How much easier is it to inconvenience yourself for other people when you’ve inconvenienced yourself for God first?)</p>
<p>SoulFood: Josh 11–13, Mark 10:35–52, Ps 142, Prov 23:7–9 </p></body><body>
<p>Fri 4 September 2015</p>
<p>‘I want men everywhere to lift up holy hands in prayer.’ 1 Timothy 2:8 NIV</p>
<p>Praying Together</p>
<p>When Paul was training Timothy up in ministry, he kept going back over and over this one point: prayer. Have a read of 1 Timothy 2:1–10. Paul was keen to hammer home to Timothy the need for prayer, particularly in Church—that is, with others, banded together. When we bring everything before God in prayer, we’re including Him in our adventures, our trials and our future. When we do that as a group we’re on to something powerful. Something that fixes us together and fixes us into God’s plans. Without including God in our adventures, trials and future, we end up being a church of people, not a Church of God. <br></br>Prayer reminds us that we’re not able to do this stuff alone; that the Holy Spirit is desperately needed. When you think of prayer, is it a quick end of the day job or a rushed word before a meal? Or is it a shoulder–to–shoulder cry of the Church, longing to get closer to God and get Him out there into the world? <br></br>In Isaiah 56:7 NIV, the Lord’s house is described as a ‘…house of prayer for all nations.’ Prayer changes things, across the whole world. It’s also one of the things that unites the Church, globally. So, let’s get serious about praying for the Church, and as the Church, today. Text two different people from your church, your workplace or your neighbourhood and ask if there’s anything in their lives right now they’d like you to pray for.  </p>
<p>SoulFood: Josh 14–15, Mark 11:1–11, Ps 20, Prov 23:10–12</p></body><body>
<p>Sat 5 September 2015</p>
<p>‘The prayer of a righteous person is powerful and effective.’ James 5:16 NIV</p>
<p>Prayer: Relationship, Not Help–Desk.</p>
<p>Are all prayers worth the same? God’s fair, right? So that should mean that He takes the distracted half–grace I said before dinner as seriously as that person praying and fasting for 24 hours, right? Hmmm, maybe not. <br></br>Why did Jesus teach His disciples that certain ministry was only possible with prayer and fasting? (Mark 9:29, Matthew 17:21) Why does James 5:16 talk about the prayer of a ‘righteous person’, instead of saying that ‘all prayer is powerful and effective’? <br></br>Here’s a challenging thought. Maybe prayer isn’t heaven’s help desk. (‘Take a ticket and wait there please; your problem is number 689,345,834,957 in the queue…’) Maybe, just maybe, prayer is part of that Christianity thing we keep insisting is a relationship. In fact, we’d argue, it’s the lifeblood of it. <br></br>If being a Christian is having a relationship with God—supported by good habits of ‘true religion’ (James 1:27) that we build into it—then, when it comes to facing a problem, only firing off the odd panic–prayer is like talking to your parents only when you want money. Look up 1 Thessalonians 5:17. <br></br>And get this as a kicker: prayer isn’t really about you. It’s about Him. In fact, not only are we meant to be in a constant prayerlationship with God, but that prayer should be the sort that re–points ourselves, from ourselves, toward Him. That’s the sort of prayer that moves mountains. Mull over James 5:13–18, then think of someone who leads something—a church, a politician, a manager. Stick their name on your wall, and pray for them each day this week. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Josh 16:1–19:23, Mark 11:12–26, Ps 112, Prov 23:13–15</p></body><body>
<p>Sun 6 September 2015</p>
<p>‘The Word became flesh and dwelt among us...’ John 1:14 NKJ</p>
<p>Words Lived Out</p>
<p>Wouldn’t it be awesome to be able to read the Bible in the original Greek and Hebrew? Or to be a theology professor, and know all about what people have written about God throughout the whole of human history? <br></br>Yes but, that knowledge can be a fantastic tool to help you get closer to God, *if* that’s what you want it for. If you want it for any other reason, beware. Ecclesiastes 1:17 NLT tells the story of someone who ran after head–knowledge for its own sake: ‘So I set out to learn everything from wisdom to madness and folly. But I learned firsthand that pursuing all this is like chasing the wind.’ <br></br>A Christian isn’t someone who knows the Bible inside out. It’s someone who knows (and is getting to know) God personally. Romans 12:2 ESV says that we should ‘…be transformed by the renewal of your mind,’ so God’s not against you learning stuff, especially about Him. But He’s pretty intent on what we read making its way into how we think and what we do. <br></br>And God set us the example here: yes, Jesus. Jesus is, literally, the ‘Word’ of God made flesh. If God has something to say to Creation, Jesus is it. One to think about, there... God lived out some pretty amazing theology in the life, death and resurrection of Jesus. So turn off the technology today—tv, tablet, computer, phone—and spend time instead reading one of the Gospels to get to know Jesus, the Word, better. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Dan 6:1–24, Acts 12:1–19 </p></body><body>
<p>Mon 7 September 2015</p>
<p>‘Turn my eyes from looking at worthless things; and give me life in your ways.’ Psalm 119:37 ESV</p>
<p>Devoted</p>
<p>‘Devote’ is a strong word. It comes from ‘de’ = down and ‘votum’ = vow. So to be ‘devoted’ to something means to be dedicated to it by a vow. Powerful stuff. Devotionals (like this one) are hopefully a good pointer to help you spend time with Jesus every day, and learn more of who He is while you’re at it.<br></br>Devotionals aren’t daily horoscopes, though. Sometimes we get so caught up in getting our fix of encouragement that we miss the point. Being devoted is an act done for someone else. The point is that we’ve discovered something wonderful—a life with God—and we want to stay with it. Five of the ten New Testament uses of the word ‘proskartereo’ for devoted are about prayer (Acts 1:14, Acts 2:42, Acts 6:4, Romans 12:12, Colossians 4:2). Being devoted requires action. Think about it—when you discover something great, you keep coming back to it. Devotion makes patterns in our lives out of our love for God, returning His first place in our lives, thanking Him for His generosity to us. <br></br>Remember, God asked Abraham to choose who he was more ‘devoted’ to—his son or God—to make sure he kept the right focus. (God *did* let Abraham keep Isaac too, but the reminder was a *big* challenge to Abraham, and is to us, too). We need to keep looking to Him, not our To–Be–Blessed–By list. What’s the best thing you’ve ever discovered? A coffee shop or restaurant? A book/film/music? Give it to someone, or take someone there, to share that thing you love. Just enjoy it with your guest. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Josh 19:24–21:45, Mark 11:27–33, Ps 27, Prov 23:16–18</p></body><body>
<p>Tue 8 September 2015</p>
<p>‘Show me Your ways, O Lord, teach me Your paths.’ Psalm 25:4 NIV</p>
<p>Tunnel Vision</p>
<p>Today, we want to know what your plans for the future are. C’mon now, out with it. Show us your colour–coded, itemised, prioritised ten–year plan! <br></br>Oh, you don’t have one? Well… yeah. Neither do we. But don’t sweat; it can feel daunting when the future looks hazy, but God works in different ways to us. Here’s some good news—even though He might not show you where you’ll be in the long–term, if you ask Him to, God will guide your steps as you take them. <br></br>‘I will bring the blind by a way they did not know; I will lead them in paths they have not known. I will make darkness light before them, and crooked places straight. These things I will do for them, and not forsake them.’ (Isaiah 42:16 NKJ) Before you go down a path, consult God first: He might not show you your final destination, but He wants you to know that He has a purpose and direction for you, right now, today. Even if it’s a path you ‘have not known’, it’ll be worth it. <br></br>Mark 3:34 NKJ says: ‘…When they were alone, He explained all things to His disciples.’ There’s some serious merit in creating (even schedule–forcing) yourself into alone–time with God. Jesus made it a priority with His disciples, and used it for some really valuable, direction–bringing time. Let’s get in on it, too. Know someone with a particular life–plan or dream? Put a refreshing spin on the dreaded question and ask: ‘What can I do today to help you make that dream a reality?’ Then, with due attention to the message on August 28, yep, you guessed it… help out, if you can. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Josh 22–24, Mark 12:1–12, Ps 78:1–8, Prov 23:19–21</p></body><body>
<p>Wed 9 September 2015</p>
<p>‘Search me, O God, and know my heart…’ Psalm 139:23 NIV</p>
<p>My Lighthouse, My Lighthouuuse</p>
<p>God’s attention searches around like a beam, seeking those whose hearts are fully committed to Him (2 Chronicles 16:9) to strengthen them. His light should spill out through us to others. But, more often than not, we have to ask Him to search us, try us and clean us before we can transmit His light well. His cleansing enables us to: <br></br>(1) Be vulnerable with Him. David prayed, ‘Search me, O God, and know my heart; test me and know my anxious thoughts. See if there is any offensive way in me and lead me in the way everlasting.’ (Psalm 139:23–24 NIV) Let’s face it, we all have habits we need to break, and that’s hard. But when we’re vulnerable (simply open and honest) with God, He can mould us into the person we want to be. God never meant for you to deal with these alone. <br></br>(2) Commit every day to God. What does that mean? Well, the writer of Proverbs said, ‘Trust in the Lord with all your heart and lean not on your own understanding; in all your ways acknowledge Him, and He will make your paths straight.’ (Proverbs 3:5–6 ESV) Asking God to shine a light on your life will make your life clearer as well as cleaner. Trust that He knows what’s going on when you don’t; look out for His presence in everything. Every single day (every moment, even) we have to deal with some pretty daunting stuff. But when you go into your day asking God to search your heart, you and your life start to light up. And you’ll be pointing people to Him. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Col 1–2, Mark 12:13–27, Ps 78:9–16, Prov 23:22–25 </p></body><body>
<p>Thu 10 September 2015</p>
<p>‘This is real love—not that we loved God, but that He loved us...’ 1 John 4:10 NLT</p>
<p>Get Thirsty</p>
<p>We’ve all had those relationships where it feels like we’re the only one contributing—like those grabber machines where you put around $300 in, and never get that 3cm tall Minion out. <br></br>If you’ve been there (in the one–way–relationship, not the arcade), you won’t need us to remind you of how it feels to put a whole lot of effort in, only to feel unwanted. Truth is, we can sometimes risk giving God that feeling. Maybe you’ve read a chunk of Bible, but praying about it to thank Him for it? Or looking to bless someone else because of it? Hmm. Sometimes, those relationship bits slip under our radar, and the whole giving back thing can be neglected. <br></br>Spending one–on–one time with God allows us to be in His presence which isn’t only about enjoying His love. It’s the root of all action that we look to do, too—the root of all ‘giving back’. The Psalmist said, ‘My soul thirsts for God, for the living God. When can I go and meet with God?’ (Psalm 42:2 NIV) The more our lives become a response to everything we find in Him, the more we need, and long, to spend time with Him. It becomes simultaneous. We spend time with God, which enables and inspires us to live out what we learn from Him, which naturally makes us long to go back to Him to learn more, which makes us live more like Him… You see where we’re going with that. So what can you thank Him for and live out today?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Col 3–4, Philemon, Mark 12:28–44, Ps 78:17–31, Prov 23:26–28 </p></body><body>
<p>Fri 11 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is freedom.’ 2 Corinthians 3:17 NIV</p>
<p>But Sometimes It’s Tough</p>
<p>Today, if you’re struggling, we’re talking to you especially. Struggling to see God at work in your life, even though you’ve done so in the past? Struggling with prayer, and reading your Bible, even though you *want* to? It happens. But it’s not as simple as turning in on yourself and thinking, ‘I’m not holy enough… I’m not praying hard enough…’ [fill in as appropriate]. Sometimes, we get tired: physically tired or emotionally tired. Have you had enough sleep recently? Have you been going through some draining times, for yourself or with your family or friends? These things are connected. <br></br>If you’ve heard the Gospel news that, amazingly, Jesus offers you healing and life in Him, and nothing in return to earn it, great. If you’ve said ‘yes’ to that, brilliant. If you’ve then slipped back into thinking that you’ve got to work to earn His attention, ah—something’s gone wrong. Giving Jesus control is a solution for your whole being. He brings joy, and purpose, to life. He will ‘refresh the weary and satisfy the faint.’ (Jeremiah 31:25 NIV) He can give us peace, rest for our minds and bodies, and healing (sometimes straight away, sometimes over time). Sometimes, even this can seem beyond us, though. If ‘running to Jesus’ seems too hard for you right now, try this: ask Him to come to you. To push through all that stuff that weighs you down. Wait for a while, and let Him come to you. We don’t have to work for God’s attention. Or people’s. Do something anonymously generous today. Clean something, donate money, whatever.<br></br>Just make sure no–one knows you did it. Masked outfits at the ready?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Neh 1–4, Mark 13:1–11, Ps 78:32–39, Prov 23:29–35</p></body><body>
<p>Sat 12 September 2015</p>
<p>‘Don’t worry about anything; instead, pray about everything.’ Philippians 4:6 NLT</p>
<p>What? A Feeling?</p>
<p>Ever told someone about a worry you had, and received a response like, ‘Yeah, well, worrying is normal’? That’s nearly true: worry is something many people do, so in that way it’s ‘normal’. But not for us. Christians get a new ‘normal’. And it’s not whistling, ‘Don’t worry, be happy,’ through your problems. Philippians 4 says we get to tell God about the things we’re stressed about, and instead of hearing back, ‘Oh, that’s just normal human behaviour,’ we hear back from Him, ‘I’ve got that for you. You don’t have to worry anymore.’ <br></br>That’s because Christians get to share in the peace Jesus had. His peace wasn’t a floaty idea or a nice feeling or a good vibe. No, His peace came from His relationship with His Father. Jesus knew for sure that His Father would give Him everything He needed, so He didn’t have to worry about not having what He needed, or being in the wrong place. What’s our way into that peace? Prayer. When we give every little situation and detail to God, He’ll give us peace that no one else can give. If we want to experience lives free of worry and filled with peace, we have to let go of whatever control we possess over a situation. (Let’s be honest, it’s really not that much anyway.) We need to say, ‘Here God. Here are my problems, my worries, my troubles. Help me through them. I’ll do what You say about them.’ <br></br>After you’ve given up your own worries, think about someone you know who always seems on the edge and pray for them so they’ll find God’s peace in every situation.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Neh 5–7, Mark 13:12–23, Ps 78:40–55, Prov 24:1–4</p></body><body>
<p>Sun 13 September 2015</p>
<p>‘Teach me to do Your will, for You are my God; may Your good Spirit lead me on level ground.’ Psalm 143:10 NIV</p>
<p>Get Level</p>
<p>When we invite God into the areas of ourselves that need some changing, He loves getting to work. And being real with Him is the way to start. But He’s a gentleman. He waits for us to invite Him in. He wants us to ask Him to change us, to lead us, and to do His will (like the writer of today’s Psalm did). All of that is God’s work to do, and our place is to ask for it. Sounds easy, huh? <br></br>Ummm, maybe not, exactly. Not when asking for that help means acknowledging those flaws first. Even when we know, deep down, that something’s not how it should be, it can be so hard to confess that out loud. We can get really good at acting like everything’s great, because that’s easier than being what we really are. But it’s not worth it. There’s nothing wrong in admitting to a weakness. Romans 7:14–25 charts Paul’s own admission of his weaknesses, and it includes some great acknowledgements of God’s grace as part of that. <br></br>So. Let’s not pretend to be doing great when we’re wrestling with that–thing–we–shouldn’t–do. It’s just… exhausting. And we don’t need to do it. Let’s be who we are, in front of God, and in front of the world. It’s when we admit that we need God’s good Spirit to ‘lead [us] on level ground’, that we can begin to find ourselves doing more and more of what God wants.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Kings 6:8–20, Eph 1:15–23 </p></body><body>
<p>Mon 14 September 2015</p>
<p>‘I take joy in doing Your will, my God, for Your instructions are written on my heart.’ Psalm 40:8 NLT</p>
<p>Tomato vs. Barbecue Sauce? </p>
<p>Sausage rolls: tomato or barbecue sauce? Superman or Batman? Comparisons. We’re making them all the time (and probably between bigger things than sauces and superheroes). Human–comparisons are especially dangerous—we’re *meant* to be different. What someone’s good at, you might not be. To put it in terms of our Christian walk, when you notice a friend’s prayer life/volunteering/worship leading, isn’t it tempting to wallow in a whole lot of ‘why am I not as awesomely Godly as that’ negativity. But, God gave each of us specific talents, abilities and passions. If we mould our lives around matching others, we’ll burn out. <br></br>As well as that, what brings someone else closer to God, might not work for you. Don’t let the great stuff in other people’s lives become damaging to your own. Others’ good habits aren’t there to weigh us down. If someone gets up at the crack of dawn to pray, you can be encouraged to pray more. But doing that at 5am isn’t what makes you a good Christian. So, getting to a point where you can say, ‘I take joy in doing Your will, my God’ won’t happen while we’re trying to tick the right boxes to have a ‘good’ faith. It happens when we live out faith in the way that God designed for us. If you find one time/way of praying difficult, go for what makes you more enthusiastic. When our God–given–preferences meet our with–Him time, it’s a win. Think of something that you really enjoy, that you’re passionate about, and turn it outwards. Do it in a way that’ll bless someone else (e.g. invite someone who seems kinda lonely to play basketball, if that’s what you love).</p>
<p>SoulFood: Num 29:1–6, Matt 24, Rev 11:15–19, 1 Cor 15:50–58 </p></body><body>
<p>Tue 15 September 2015</p>
<p>‘Through Him all things were made; without Him nothing was made that has been made.’ John 1:3 NIV</p>
<p>At The Centre</p>
<p>It can feel like everyone has expectations for you. Your parents want you to be successful. Your boyfriend/girlfriend wants you to pay more attention. Your tutor wants you to knock that essay out of the park. People’s expectations can weigh you down, and if you spend all your time trying to please people, you’ll never be free. If we’re constantly trying to fulfil other people’s expectations, as well as our own, we’ll end up crumbling because we didn’t accomplish all they wanted. Some make a list of priorities and number them from one to ten (or twenty, or a hundred), but that could stress us out even more because priorities can change within minutes. <br></br>Stop. Look at John 1:3 again. Everything was made through God: ‘…without Him nothing was made that has been made.’ In order to find a balance in our daily life, we’ve got to put God at the centre of everything we do. Our number one priority should be Him. And that priority wouldn’t change. Even if it sounds a bit cliché, it’s the truth. The only way to anchor ourselves in the face of a bazillion expectations is if our no.1 aim is to live for, and with, a Constant. That way, with God at the root and centre of everything we are, the pressure to decide which human expectations to carry becomes less and less important. <br></br>Identify someone who’s expected a lot of you. Even if it’s difficult, pay them back with generosity. Thank them for something you learned from them. </p>
<p> SoulFood: Neh 8–10, Mark 13:24–37, Ps 78:56–64, Prov 24:5–10 </p></body><body>
<p>Wed 16 September 2015</p>
<p>‘For you were once darkness, but now you are light in the Lord. Live as children of the light.’ Ephesians 5:8 NIV</p>
<p>Boundaries</p>
<p>Seeing God as some distant rule maker, and His book (that’d be the Bible) as weighty lists of restrictions, is a pretty common myth about Christianity. And Christians often respond to this myth with the popular line: ‘I’m not religious, I’ve got a relationship.’ <br></br>But digging a little deeper, there’s a middle way that makes most sense: if we are in that relationship with God, we’ll want to know how to live in a way that pleases Him. And if we trust His judgement, His warning that this world is dangerously wrong about some things is one we’ll want to hear: ‘Be very careful, then, how you live—not as unwise but as wise, making the most of every opportunity, because the days are evil.’ (Ephesians 5:15–16 NIV) <br></br>God seems pretty keen on us living a certain way. But what’s in it for Him? He doesn’t need a relationship with us, He *wants* it, out of love, so it makes sense that His preferences for us are because He has our interests at heart. Add into that that He knows absolutely everything that can be known and His opinions become very trustworthy indeed. When God says: ‘live wisely’, ‘do not gossip’, ‘get filled with My Spirit, rather than getting drunk’ (Ephesians 5:15–18), it’s probably because those are bits of how our world rolls that we should be wary of, to avoid hurting ourselves and others. ‘Do not conform to the pattern of this world, but be transformed by the renewing of your mind…’ (Romans 12:2 NIV) Doing things deliberately differently, for God, includes wanting to see His justice and fairness in our world.<br></br>Today, be conscious of acting wisely and fairly.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Neh 11–13, Mark 14:1–11, Ps 78:65–72, Prov 24:11–14</p></body><body>
<p>Thu 17 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…I have come that they may have life, and have it to the full.’ John 10:10 NIV</p>
<p>Acedia: Dry Bones Live</p>
<p>God led Ezekiel to a valley full of dry bones and He told Ezekiel to prophesy to the skeletons: ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord says: Look! I am going to put breath into you and make you live again!’ (Ezekiel 37:5 NLT) <br></br>Some days we need to hear that more than others. Those are the days when we just don’t care. When acedia takes over. What’s ‘acedia’? We’re glad you asked! In a nutshell, it means feeling sluggish, lifeless, not really interested in anything, including yourself. Left to fester, it can become life–threatening. <br></br>In today’s verse, Jesus explains the difference between His way of life and how the devil works on us: ‘The thief comes only to steal and kill and destroy. I came that they may have life and have it abundantly.’ (John 10:10 ESV) Jesus calling the devil ‘the thief’ is no casual insult, it’s a spot–on warning to us. <br></br>God created us, lovingly crafted us, to thrive. To grow into our own reflections of His creativity, full of life, joy and love. And when we fall flat, when we’re nothing more than dry bones in a tough–time valley, He can breathe into us (literally: ‘in–spire’ us), can restore our hope, can ‘open [our] graves of exile and cause [us] to rise again.’ (Ezekiel 37:12 NLT) Who can you inspire today? Find someone who you can send a message to, spend time with, or maybe even commit to mentoring, who you can inspire to do amazing things. You’ll not only be breathing life into someone’s day–to–day, but we reckon you’ll be inspired by doing it, too.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Mic 1–4, Mark 14:12–26, Ps 24, Prov 24:15–18</p></body><body>
<p>Fri 18 September 2015</p>
<p>‘If I speak in the tongues of men or of angels, but do not have love, I am only a resounding gong or a clanging cymbal.’ 1 Corinthians 13:1 NIV</p>
<p>Lovely.</p>
<p>1 Corinthians 13 is commonly known as the love chapter (Go read it. Yup. A *whole* chapter of the Bible. What are we thinking?) You might be surprised by what love truly is. Maybe, as you read the chapter, you wondered over things you’ve done from love or duty. 1 Corinthians 13:3 NIV says, ‘If I give all I possess to the poor and give my body to hardship that I may boast, but do not have love, I gain nothing.’ If you volunteer at a shelter for the homeless, pick up litter along the motorway or give away all your possessions, that’s great in one sense. But do it from grudging duty or to build a good reputation, and you won’t gain anything. God just isn’t impressed with good deeds done to get people’s praise. <br></br>Take a deeper look at the next two verses. They say love isn’t boastful, proud or self–seeking. When we do good things for the wrong reasons, we fall into these categories. Jesus said, ‘Your giving should be done in secret. Your Father can see what is done in secret, and He will reward you.’ (Matthew 6:3 NCV) In other words, keep an eye on Him when we’re doing that good stuff, not on our popularity ratings. What if, when you did good deeds, people saw God at work in their lives, and praised God for it, instead of praising you? Wouldn’t that, actually, be lovely?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Mic 5–7, Mark 14:27–42, Ps 19, Prov 24:19–22 </p></body><body>
<p>Sat 19 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…Spur one another on toward love and good deeds.’ Hebrews 10:24 NIV </p>
<p>Just Banter, Right?</p>
<p>There are an awful lot of people on this planet. You’ve probably noticed one or two of them. When we come into close contact with one another, the way we interact can leave us feeling good or bad about ourselves. We may think that the way we speak to each other isn’t a big deal but the Bible, uh... disagrees with us: ‘The tongue has the power of life and death.’ (Proverbs 18:21 NIV) Starting to question something you said to someone this week now? Life and death may sound a bit extreme, but words have an extreme impact—certain things that people say can stay with you for a long time. <br></br>Words are how we come into close contact with one another. God created other people because He said it wasn’t good for man to be alone (cue, Eve). But just being around each other isn’t enough. God calls us to be loving, and that involves thinking about how we speak to one another. Are we encouraging? Are we kind? You might think that it’s no big deal to casually rip your friends—just banter, right? Banter better. We’re better than that sort of joke that’s really a cheap mask for abuse. We should be helping our friends to be the best that they can be. Because being a human being is difficult enough without harsh words. <br></br>Time out. Today let’s pray through our messages—stuff we’ve sent and stuff we’ve received. Get out your phone, and ask God to show you specific messages or people to pray about. Then spend some time ‘receiving’ from Him what He might want to say to you.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Tim 1–4, Mark 14:43–52, Ps 3, Prov 24:23–25</p></body><body>
<p>Sun 20 September 2015</p>
<p>‘....If two of you agree here on earth concerning anything you ask, My Father in Heaven will do it for you.’ Matthew 18:19 NLT</p>
<p>Bring Them to Jesus</p>
<p>They came to Him in droves. In the crowd was a paralysed man, carried by four men. After trying to get through the masses and getting nowhere, the four men got crafty and figured that the building Jesus was in had a roof... which they promptly took apart. They lowered the paralytic’s bed down to Jesus. When Jesus saw their faith, He said to the paralytic, ‘I tell you, get up, take your mat and go home.’ (Mark 2:11 NIV) We learn from this man’s story that sometimes people can’t get to Jesus on their own. God often uses us to reach those who don’t know Him. <br></br>It took four people with faith to bring this guy to Jesus. You don’t have to do all the bringing by yourself. Jesus said, ‘If two of you agree here on earth concerning anything you ask, My Father in Heaven will do it for you.’ (Matthew 18:19 NLT) Prayer, together, is massively powerful. <br></br>The four men also refused to let the crowd stop them. Even though there was a huge barrier (y’know, a mob of people), they were determined to reach Jesus. And when another barrier (the top of someone’s house) was in their way, they didn’t let that stop them either. They didn’t give up. What an encouragement for us, for the people we love, and those we want to bring to God. <br></br>The man on the mat had a Hollywood style testimony. Most of us don’t, but lots of us have stories of God being faithful and generous to us. If you do, today, tell someone. If you don’t, ask someone you think does, and give them time to tell you.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Kings 3:4–28, James 1:2–8</p></body><body>
<p>Mon 21 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…the strength of those who wait with hope in the Lord will be renewed...’ Isaiah 40:31 GWT</p>
<p>Feel the Wait</p>
<p>So being alive is pretty tiring. In crazy old 2015 there seems to be no relief from all the responsibilities we have. What should we do when we’re exhausted? The prophet Isaiah tells us that God ‘…gives strength to those who grow tired and... weak. Even young people grow tired and become weary... Yet, the strength of those who wait with hope in the Lord will be renewed. They will soar on wings like eagles. They will run and won’t become weary.’ (Isaiah 40:29–31 GWT) <br></br>We weren’t made to work all of the time, we were designed for a specific pattern of work and rest—six days on, one day off. When we abuse that and overwork ourselves, life gets even more difficult. ‘Remember the Sabbath day by keeping it holy. Six days you shall labour and do all your work, but the seventh day is a Sabbath to the Lord your God.’ (Exodus 20:8–9 NIV) Even though this verse is part of Old Testament law it still has a lot of wisdom for us now. The six days on, one day off thing was made for us to rest. But, more than that—so that we could focus on God. God rested after He made the world—and in the Sabbath He invites us, every week, to join Him in that rest, focusing on the fact that He’s done everything for us. Plan a restful, God–filled Sabbath this week—spend a peaceful day with someone, neither of you doing work. See what you can prepare in advance, from rearranging work shifts to pre–packing a picnic and a book each; treat that someone to a recharge–day to remember.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Zech 1–4, Mark 14:53–65, Ps 39, Prov 24:26–28</p></body><body>
<p>Tue 22 September 2015</p>
<p><i>‘</i>I am leaving you with a gift—peace of mind...’ John 14:27 NLT</p>
<p>Holy Spirit: You Are Not Alone (1)</p>
<p>You can be doing great when, all of a sudden, something comes along and smacks you in the face. A bunch of those ‘somethings’ that let you down: friends, family, even your own body. We weren’t promised that becoming a Christian would guarantee a bubblegum–pink life, free from sadness and drama. Sometimes God doesn’t get rid of the ‘rubbish’. He gives us the peace we need to get through it (and learn from it), instead. <br></br>How, then? In Philippians 4:6–7 NLT Paul wrote, ‘Don’t worry about anything; instead, pray about everything. Tell God what you need, and thank Him for all He has done. Then you will experience God’s peace, which exceeds anything we can understand. His peace will guard your hearts and minds as you live in Christ Jesus.’ When you pray, the Holy Spirit—God’s gift to you sent in Jesus’ name—will give you peace right through the muck life throws at you. ‘...the Advocate, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in My name, will teach you all things and will remind you of everything I have said to you. Peace I leave with you; My peace I give you… Do not let your hearts be troubled and do not be afraid.’ (John 14:26–27 NIV) ‘Sent in Jesus’ name’ means it’s as if you have Jesus Himself doing the reassuring, the teaching, and the peace providing that His Spirit does. Brilliant.Send a message (phone, twitter, facebook, whatever) to someone who needs peace through a pile–of–rubbish, today. Pray about which Bible verse would help encourage them.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Zech 5–8, Mark 14:66–72, Ps 34, Prov 24:29–31</p></body><body>
<p>Wed 23 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…He will give you another Counsellor.’ John 14:16 AMP</p>
<p>Holy Spirit: You Are Not Alone (2)</p>
<p>You are not alone. Maybe you feel that you are already. Hopefully you’ve got an amazing family and friends who support you in all that you do. But even if you don’t, you are still... not alone! God might feel far away, up in Heaven somewhere drifting on a cloud, but that isn’t how things are. God is *with* us. The Holy Spirit is one of the best gifts the world has ever received. He’s not some weird ghosty guy who sort of knows God. And He’s not like a wifi network we connect to whenever we feel prayerful and Christian–y. The Holy Spirit is an equal Person in the Trinity, and He lives in everyone who believes that Jesus Christ is Lord of all. <br></br>Seriously, how exciting is that? Jesus staying with the disciples forever might have seemed amazing by itself, but His leaving started a new, better phase in God’s plan. When Jesus ascended into Heaven, the Holy Spirit came to God’s people, and not just for a little while—forever. The Holy Spirit does heaps of things: comforts, teaches, sometimes whispers to us, prays on our behalf, and sometimes even does miraculous things through us. When you don’t know what to do, you can ask and the Holy Spirit is available to guide you. He can speak to you: through the Scripture you’re reading, a persistent idea or through something a friend says. You’re not alone, unless you want to be. The Holy Spirit is a Person, right here and now, with you. <br></br>You’re not alone. Today, make an effort to reach out to someone who is. If some friends are hanging out soon, plan together to invite that person to join you. </p>
<p>SoulFood (Yom Kippur): Lev 16, Lev 23:26–32, Heb 9:1–14, Heb 13:11–16</p></body><body>
<p>Thu 24 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…The Holy Spirit—He will teach you everything...’ John 14:26 NLT </p>
<p>Holy Spirit: You Are Not Alone (3)</p>
<p>Jesus didn’t leave the disciples to fend for themselves. What’s even better is that the help they got from the Holy Spirit wasn’t just for them, it’s for us as well. The Holy Spirit has names by the dozen; ‘representative’ and ‘counsellor’ are just two of them. In the New International Reader’s Version, ‘counsellor’ is translated as ‘friend’. In the New King James Bible, it’s ‘helper’ and in the original King James, it was ‘comforter’. In the Amplified Bible, it’s ‘intercessor, advocate, strengthener, standby’. In the original Greek, the Holy Spirit is referred to as ‘parakletos’, a combination of two words: para, which means ‘alongside of’, and kletos, ‘one who’s designated to you’. <br></br>Getting the idea yet? The Holy Spirit has been assigned to you—to come alongside you. He’s the One who will stand by you. He is the presence of Jesus with and in you. The disciples definitely needed this encouragement to make through not only just the next few days but the rest of their lives. They would go on to see Jesus crucified, and in the end only one of them (John) went on to die a natural death, the rest were martyred. Jesus wanted them, and you, to know this: ‘You’ll never face the future without My help.’ Wherever the journey leads, He will be there by your side. <br></br>Just like the Holy Spirit’s been assigned to help you as you help others, get alongside someone today and help them to serve. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Zech 9–11, Mark 15:1–11, Ps 52, Prov 24:32–34 </p></body><body>
<p>Fri 25 September 2015</p>
<p>‘These little troubles are getting us ready...’ 2 Corinthians 4:17 CEV </p>
<p>Holy Spirit: You Are Not Alone (4)</p>
<p>If we had Jesus still walking around on earth, that would be fantastic. But imagine the queues. The crowds. The long waiting list to get any time with Him. By giving us His Holy Spirit, we all have access to time with Him—and more than ‘access’, we’re given a live presence of God within us. <br></br>Everything Jesus did for His disciples, the Holy Spirit does for you. Everything Jesus taught, the Holy Spirit teaches us. Jesus healed, the Holy Spirit heals us. Jesus comforted, the Holy Spirit comforts us. Boom. Jesus sends us out into the world with the Spirit with us. And as you go He ‘will teach you everything and remind you of everything I [Jesus] have told you.’ (John 14:26 NLT) That means that when we face changes in life, they’re not as uncomfortable as they would otherwise have been. In fact, God often moulds us through changes, so they’re not all bad. And with a changed us, He changes the world. In partnership with His present, powerful, Holy Spirit. And about those painful changes? You’re not alone there, either. God goes there with you, through them, and however they came about, God is using them for our good: ‘...our present troubles are small and won’t last very long. Yet they produce for us a glory that vastly outweighs them and will last forever!’ (2 Corinthians 4:17 NLT) <br></br>Leave the phone at home for a day (gulp, we know). As you go from place to place, whenever you absent–mindedly reach for it, strike up a conversation instead. If there’s no–one around, then how about with the Holy Spirit, who we’ve been talking about for 4 days now?...</p>
<p>SoulFood: Zech 12–14, Mark 15:12–20, Ps 54, Prov 25:1–3</p></body><body>
<p>Sat 26 September </p>
<p>‘As for you, you meant evil against me, but God meant it for good....’ Genesis 50:20 ESV</p>
<p>Joseph: Hit Your Knees When You Fall </p>
<p>Here’s Joseph’s story in less than 25 words: his brothers put him in a pit, his boss put him in a prison, and God put him on a throne. (A few millennia later, Andrew Lloyd Webber put some songs out). What can we learn from Joseph? <br></br>(1) Your dreams may not go to your plan. Joseph’s dreams (Genesis 37:5–10) were about his own power. God’s plans included Joseph being in power, but were first about saving a nation. God’s plans weren’t incompatible with Joseph’s, but they were different, and massively better. Rather than us just growing our own empires, God wants to grow His Kingdom, which is a win for everyone. Joseph’s dreams seemed to have collapsed, but he got up again, with God. <br></br>(2) Other people may knock you to your knees. But that’s a good place to land. If God is in control of your life (hint: He is), then even when people have ‘meant evil against’ you, ‘God has meant it for good’. When you can only see the evil, go straight to God with it. He can bring you through it, and put you into a stronger place than before, because of it.<br></br>(3) God does it all. Joseph took a few opportunities to arrange power for himself, but he fell flat (Genesis 40:23). God’s all for you being proactive in your plans, but He also wants to make sure we remember where success comes from, and stay close to Him. After all, isn’t Godless leadership a problem for humanity throughout our history? <br></br>Have a God–focused day. Bask, if you can, in who God is and what He’s done for you. </p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 1–3, Mark 15:21–32, Ps 13, Prov 25: 4–8 </p></body><body>
<p>Sun 27 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…They did not respond to correction...’ Jeremiah 2:30 NIV</p>
<p>Check Yo’self</p>
<p>‘If only I had checked myself.’ – Guy Who Wrecked Himself<br></br>Chances are you’re not perfect. Most people accept that, so why is it so hard when other people acknowledge the fact out loud? When someone mentions something that we could have handled better or somewhere we could improve, it’s easy to take it like an arrow to the knee. <br></br>Actually, we need people who’ll be honest with us. A lot of the time, we act before we actually use that brain God gave us. So when someone comes along and lets us know what we could be doing better, it really is a blessing, not a curse. Think about it this way, you wouldn’t (shouldn’t!) hand a document to your boss or a piece of coursework in without checking your spelling first, right? Sometimes, we need someone to ‘proof–read’ us. Sure, it depends on how they do it: there’s a difference between ‘You suck at this!’ and ‘Hey, that thing you did, that ain’t cool.’ Generally, however, we don’t get offended because of the way someone’s criticised us, but because they’ve dared to suggest we’re not perfect. Which shouldn’t be news to us. Solomon (superwise Bible bloke) said, ‘To learn, you must love discipline; it is stupid to hate correction.’ (Proverbs 12:1 NLT) We can help other people too, by correcting them, but make this always because we love them, not because we want to humiliate them. Talking of not humiliating people with our words, let’s change our vocab. When you speak about any other people today, drop the labels (stuff like ‘the poor’, or ‘underprivileged’—especially words like ‘idiot’). Find ways of describing people that give them the utmost dignity and respect.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Eph 5:21–33, Song of Songs 2:1–7, Ps 45, Prov 5:15–19</p></body><body>
<p>Mon 28 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…We are…the aroma of Christ...’ 2 Corinthians 2:15 NIV</p>
<p>Eau de Galilee </p>
<p>So you’ve probably heard that you should act like Jesus. Has anyone told you that you’re supposed to smell like him too? Before you rush to the shop and buy whatever will help you smell like a walking–tour preacher from a hot dusty country in the 1st century AD (try explaining that to the staff of the perfume section) let’s look at what the Bible means by ‘Aroma of Christ’. ‘We are…the aroma of Christ among those who are being saved, and those who are perishing. To one we are an aroma that brings death; to the other, an aroma that brings life…’ (2 Corinthians 2:15–16 NIV) <br></br>When the Roman army won in battle, they paraded their defeated foes through the streets in chains. And as part of the celebration they burned incense on a series of altars throughout the city. That way those who couldn’t see the procession knew the army had won, because they could smell the incense. The aroma was symbolic of their victory. Hmmm... what could this mean for us...? As followers of Christ we carry ‘the aroma of the knowledge of Him.’ (2 Corinthians 2:14 NIV) Your life should be so full of God’s presence that people around you sense it. After all, you are the most compelling evidence that Jesus is alive. You. God uses His people to make Himself known. The more time we spend with God, talking to Him, reading His Word, listening and worshipping Him, the more people are going to say, ‘There’s something different about you.’</p>
<p>SoulFood: Eph 5:21–33, Song of Songs 2:1–7, Ps 45, Prov 5:15–19</p></body><body>
<p>Tue 29 September 2015</p>
<p>‘Open my eyes, that I may see wondrous things from Your law.’ Psalm 119:18 NKJ</p>
<p>Brush Up!</p>
<p>How’s your attention span? (Hey, there, yoohoo!… Come away from that phone already...) We know, we know. It’s easy to be distracted. In fairness, given the amount of phone/internet related distractions we all live with, it isn’t too big a surprise. That’s why we’re starting today with a practical tip: cut out attention–grabbers during devotional time. You may have heard the classic challenge: ‘What if we spent as much time reading the Bible as we did on social media/watching TV?’ That may seem such a cliché that it’s not worth letting it test us—but try to. And even if that seems a bit much, we can all keep notifications and texts out of sight to honour Him. From there, we can invite Him into our other time: our Bible and prayer time with Him set us up for the rest of our lives, including the stuff we read online and send other people. <br></br>Practical tip #2: reading the Bible daily is good for you. Finding a good time within your day to do it is better. Are you a morning person? An evening person? When you’re most likely to take in what you’re reading, that’s the best time to get stuck in to Scripture. The best hint we can give you, though, is that there’ll always be something else, pressuring you or trying to distract you. But when we determine to focus on God, our relationship with Him will go better. Obvious, really. So, start with reading a chunk of Bible (like SoulFood), then, open a social media newsfeed and spend time praying for each person who appears there.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 4–6, Mark 15:33–47, Ps 91, Prov 25:9–12</p></body><body>
<p>Wed 30 September 2015</p>
<p>‘…Not of yourselves; it is the gift of God.’ Ephesians 2:8 NKJ</p>
<p>You Can’t Save yourself!</p>
<p>Lifeguards know more than how to stand next to the pool looking fit and bronzed, or how to spin their whistle around, or how to glare at anyone doing a dive bomb. They know how to save people from drowning! If a lifeguard is trying to save you, you need to stop kicking around trying to save yourself. When you’re struggling in deep water you tire easily and sink faster. You also drag others down with you. That’s why a lifeguard will tell you to stop struggling and trust him. It’s true with God too: He doesn’t need your help to save you! <br></br>The Bible says, ‘...God’s mercy is great, and He loved us very much. Though we were spiritually dead because of the things we did against God, He gave us new life with Christ… And He raised us up with Christ and gave us a seat with Him in the heavens…I mean that you have been saved by grace through believing. You did not save yourselves; it was a gift from God. It was not the result of your own efforts, so you cannot brag about it.’ (Ephesians 2:4–9 NCV) <br></br>When Nicodemus came to talk to Jesus about salvation he thought Jesus would give him a list of religious do’s and don’ts to follow. What this top religious leader failed to grasp is that God is not impressed with our good works; He loves us but in His eyes ‘…each of our good deeds is merely a filthy rag…’ (Isaiah 64:6 CEV) There’s a humbling thought! Paul writes: ‘…His grace…is a free gift…’ (Romans 3:24 NCV), and He’s offering it to you today. Will you accept it?</p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 7–9, Mark 16:1–8, Ps 68:1–18, Prov 25:13–16 </p></body><body>
<p>Thu 1 October </p>
<p>‘…I have found David…a man after My own heart...’ Acts 13:22 NKJV</p>
<p>The Path To The Throne (1)</p>
<p>There aren’t many people in the Bible God describes as ‘a man after my own heart’—in fact there’s just one: David! For that reason it’s probably worth taking a good long look at his life—so we’ll take the next few days to do that. We’ll see that David had a humble start but it didn’t stop him reaching dizzy heights. He began as a shepherd and ended up as a king! The chances of that happening were next to none. In those days shepherds were so low on the ladder they couldn’t even witness in a court of law; their word wasn’t considered reliable; yet by age thirty he was wearing the crown. <br></br>But the story’s not all success, during his forty years in leadership he experienced devastating failure. There are two lessons here: <br></br>(1) Don’t rush to judgment. It is not over until God says it’s over. David’s story is a warning to the self-righteous, a testimony to the justice of God that won’t allow us to escape our sin’s consequences, and to His love that will never let go of us. <br></br>(2) God can bring good out of it. He can take every experience you’ve been through, both positive and negative, and make it work for good, either your good or the good of others. When you chase God’s purposes in spite of your flaws, He makes ‘…all things work together for good…’ (Romans 8:28 NKJV) </p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 10–11, Mark 16:9–20, Ps 68:19–35, Prov 25:17–20 </p></body><body>
<p>Fri 2 October</p>
<p>‘...I have found David…a man after My own heart...’ Acts 13:22 NKJV</p>
<p>The Path To The Throne (2)</p>
<p>David was chosen to be king in his teens, but he only made it to the throne at age thirty. There are lessons here: <br></br>(1) God calls the person. In spite of being unappreciated by his family and overlooked by the prophet Samuel, God picked David. He also picked Deborah to lead the nation in a male–dominated society. Stop trying to figure God out, and stop comparing yourself to others! ‘Does not the potter have the right to make out of the same lump of clay some pottery for noble purposes and some for common use?’ (Romans 9:21 NIV) <br></br>(2) God decides the plan. ‘…He who has begun a good work in you will complete it…’ (Philippians 1:6 NKJ) Who began it? So who should your confidence be in? God! God’s plan for David involved years of ducking Saul’s spears, living in caves with misfits who redefine the word ‘dysfunctional’. God trains you in a small sphere so you can handle a bigger one. <br></br>(3) God knows the span of time required. Endurance means standing firm under pressure. The Bible says we inherit the promises through faith, endurance and patience. (Colossians 1:11–12) That means being like Joseph who refused to let go of his dream; it’s what helped him through all sorts of agro, including years of unjust imprisonment. But the day came when a whole Kingdom was handed to Joseph. So keep your eyes on the prize and don’t give up!</p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 12–14, John 1:1–13, Ps 60, Prov 25:21–22 </p></body><body>
<p>Sat 3 October</p>
<p>‘…I have found David…a man after My own heart…’ Acts 13:22 NKJV</p>
<p>The Path To The Throne (3)</p>
<p>Every one of David’s brothers was lined up to meet Samuel, the famous man of God, when he came to Bethlehem looking for the next king of Israel. But not David. That must have hurt. So how did he respond? By sneakily asking somebody to put his name down on the guest list? No! It’s clear from David’s words and songs that he knew that nobody could keep God’s blessing from him. After a while it dawned on Samuel that somebody was missing and he called for that person: ‘…as David stood there among his brothers, Samuel took the flask of oil he had brought and anointed David…’ (1 Samuel 16:13 NLT) If you remain faithful, God will lift you up in the midst of those who put you down. But be prepared for trouble! Like Joseph’s brothers, they’ll lay traps thinking, ‘…we’ll see what comes of his dreams.’ (Genesis 37:20 NIV) Why would those who are supposed to love you say such a thing? Usually jealousy or self-preservation—they like to keep you in your place—below them! Be ready for a dose of rejection, especially when there’s no evidence to prove your God-given dream. Check this out: even when David was ready to take on Goliath, his oldest brother called him arrogant and dissed him to his face. (1 Samuel 17:28) Why did God put these stories in the Bible? ‘These things happened to them as examples and were written down as warnings for us…’ (1 Corinthians 10:11 NIV)</p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 12–14, John 1:1–13, Ps 60, Prov 25:21–22 </p></body><body>
<p>Sun 4 October</p>
<p>‘…I have found David…a man after My own heart…’ Acts 13:22 NKJV</p>
<p>The Path To The Throne (4)</p>
<p>It’s true that some of God’s promises become reality quickly. It’s great when that happens. Get in! But others, like the one God gave to David telling him he’d be king, have to be fought for. A tribal family called the Jebusites controlled Jerusalem; they taunted David saying, ‘You will not get in here…’ (2 Samuel 5:6 NIV) They were pretty cocky because they knew Jerusalem was built on a virtually impregnable hill. The only way up into the city was through a secret water passage where they had to wade and climb through pitch–black darkness. ‘Nevertheless, David captured the fortress of Zion...’ (2 Samuel 5:7 NIV) Understand this: if He has to, God will bring you up through the gutter to get you to the throne! <br></br>Are you in a dark place today, hidden, out of view? Well, that doesn’t mean you’re not on your way to the top. You can be steadily making progress towards your goal ready to burst onto the scene at any moment. Those Jebusites got a shock when David’s men burst out as if from nowhere! So, when you’re up to your neck in problems and the enemy is saying, ‘You won’t make it,’ stand on God’s Word and remember David’s victory in Jerusalem. God can show you how to use the situation you are facing for your good and His glory. Today, having prayed for God’s direction, go forward as He sends you, knowing He is with you!</p>
<p>SoulFood: Jos 1:7–8, 2 Tim 3:14–17, Ps 119:1–16 </p></body><body>
<p>Mon 5 October</p>
<p>‘Do it with all your might...’ Ecclesiastes 9:10 NIV</p>
<p>Digging Deep</p>
<p>Sometimes life requires us to really dig in and put in an extra effort. To live for God in ways that we’ve never done before, and trust in Him for things we never thought would be possible. The ‘bigger’ parts of faith often seem like, say, a mission trip or a promotion to youth leader. But: some of the things that take ‘all your might’ may look different. They might not be so up front and obvious. Take a look at Galatians 5:22–23, the Fruits of the Spirit verses. They’re a big part of faith by anyone’s measure: becoming more like Jesus. And if you’re like us, you’ll know they don’t come easy. Putting His will first can take as much attention, energy and prayer as the biggest of mission trips, but it’s life–changing and so thoroughly worth it. <br></br>What do we mean? It takes a lot of effort to be gentle in that situation where you’d rather let anger boil over. Wrestling our human tendencies is tiring like that. It can take just as much effort to have the self–control to hold back on going too far on that date, almost like you’re fighting against your senses. To bring any action before God when we’re feeling weak can take all of our might. But it’s so important. When we act out of love (which is the best motive we can have, according to Corinthians 13:2), and ask God to bless our efforts, we’re not pointlessly exhausting ourselves in order to ‘be good’. We’re being changed by Him in a permanent, enriching way. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 1–3, John 1:29–42, Ps 63, Prov 25:26–28</p></body><body>
<p>Tue 6 October</p>
<p>‘…We can certainly do it.’ Numbers 13:30 NIV</p>
<p>Dodge the Dead End</p>
<p>Caleb had his head screwed on. He was in a team on a mission to check out the Promised Land, which didn’t go so well. Most of the spies were terrified—they returned with stories of a land ‘that devours its inhabitants’ (Numbers 13:32 NKJ), with people who made them look ‘like grasshoppers’ (Numbers 13:33 NKJ). Not a great starting point for Israel, who’d been waiting to get to the land promised to them. <br></br>In the face of bad news, Caleb had a different approach. He trusted God and remembered His faithfulness, and said: ‘We should go up and take possession of the land, for we can certainly do it.’ It takes courage to look beyond what looks like a dead end. Perhaps you’re trying to break a habit, or trying out some gifts you think God’s given you, for the first time. You’re on new ground, and even if you know you’re there with God, when you feel under threat from others (or yourself), it can be enough to make you want to stop trying. But when we take hold of Caleb’s strategy, we’re on to a winner: ‘Do not rebel against the Lord. And do not fear the people of the land, for they are bread for us.’ (Numbers 14:9 ESV) See, the very things that hold you back can be used as ‘bread’ to feed you and keep you going to where God is leading you. If you’ve started a good thing with God, don’t give up now. Think about something that’s held you back from living fully for God. Keep it in your head, then read Numbers 13:25–14:10. Now pray about what’s holding you back.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 4–6, John 1:43–51, Ps 92, Prov 26:1–3</p></body><body>
<p>Fri 7 October</p>
<p>‘In the same way, let your light shine before others...’ Matthew 5:16 NIV</p>
<p>Radiate</p>
<p>Right then. Today’s task is to locate a whole bunch of uranium, and make a lovely glowy pie. Then, when you’ve eaten the pie, you’ll probably be set to go and shine before others. <br></br>As fun as that sounds (not!), Jesus probably had something else in mind (phew! You can let out your sigh of relief now). While He tells us to shine ‘our light’, Jesus also says this: ‘I am the light of the world.’ (John 8:12 NIV) Hold up. If He’s light and we’re light, there’s a ‘Jesus living through us’ dynamic going on, that we should be living in. That also lets us know where the Source of our shining comes from—Him. God considers us His representatives on earth, and so the light that Jesus gives to others, the hope and freedom that He brings, needs to be something that we participate in, too. We need to live out His light. What parts of Jesus do you look at and really want to copy? (Of course, we want to be completely like Him as much as possible, but that builds from each small thing.) Maybe His kindness, or how He loved others, or even His patience. That’s the light. God wants us to go out and shine it, so others can glimpse what Jesus means to their lives. <br></br>Wait until it’s dark and turn the light on your phone on, then off again. See the difference it makes in the room around you. Think about this question: How can I make that sort of difference in someone’s life who I know?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 7–9, John 2:1–11, Ps 29, Prov 26:4–6</p></body><body>
<p>Thu 8 October</p>
<p>‘He made us, and we are His. We are His people, the sheep of His pasture.’ Psalm 100:3 NLT</p>
<p>Palm Down</p>
<p>Palm trees are pretty awesome. As much as they might remind us of nice, sunny places, we can learn a lot about ourselves and God from the local (or not so local) palm tree. They’re mentioned more than 30 times in the Bible, probably because there were a fair few of them around where most of its writers were working. They provide us with a pretty good example of the endurance God offers to us, too. <br></br>When there’s a huge storm and wind is blowing everywhere (goodbye, good hair day) most trees are at risk of snapping or breaking. Not the palm tree. They’re adapted to bend as if they’re competing in the ultimate limbo competition. Afterwards, the place where the bend is becomes stronger than it was before. God doesn’t give us a supernatural ability to win a limbo competition, but whenever we pray as we face a ‘storm’, God causes us to be ‘invigorated and strengthened with all power according to the might of His glory.’ (Colossians 1:11 AMP) So, not only does He give us the strength to get over whatever challenge is thrown our way, we’re made stronger by learning to be thankful and understanding that God is bigger (and makes us bendier) than any storm that can be thrown our way. A final thing: a palm’s roots can search hundreds of metres for water, making what it relies on for survival much deeper and bigger than what it actually is. Good idea, that. As we seek the living water of the Holy Spirit, He promises that we’ll find Him. ‘Ask and it will be given to you; seek and you will find; knock and the door will be opened to you.’ (Matthew 7:7 NIV)</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 10–12, John 2:12–25, Ps 131, Prov 26:7–9</p></body><body>
<p>Fri 9 October</p>
<p>‘…They will flourish in the courts of our God.’ Psalm 92:13 NIV</p>
<p>Court, In the Act</p>
<p>Little actions can tell a big story. Cutting in front of a driver who instantly goes ballistic, honking and swearing at you, tells you they weren’t exactly a rose–garden of peace beforehand. (It doesn’t say much for your driving, either…) Always being the first to be served food and never buying someone else’s coffee send signals to the people around us about what the rest of our character is like. And worse, they’re usually forming an opinion about God through our not–so–handsome character flaws too. Not good. <br></br>Today’s verse says: ‘The righteous flourish like the palm tree and grow like a cedar in Lebanon. They are planted in the house of the Lord; they flourish in the courts of our God.’ (Psalm 92:12–13 NIV) Our not–very–Godlike actions aren’t exactly the ‘flourishing’ that He meant. We looked at palm trees yesterday, what about these courts then? Well, a king’s courts were places important people gathered to talk business. They were near enough to the throne room for the king to call in for a word when he wanted. Just like that, God wants us to keep close. If we’re in His ‘courts’, if our business is His business, and we’re regularly popping in for a chat, then we’ll find ourselves flourishing, big time. (And as a lovely little cherry on the flourish–cake, those around us will see something of our King in us too, which is a very good thing). Look up Galatians 5:22–23. This verse gives a list of all the things we can expect to become more like as we draw closer ‘in His courts’. Write them down and stick them up somewhere.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 13–15, John 3:1–8, Ps 23, Prov 26:10–12</p></body><body>
<p>Sat 10 October</p>
<p>‘…unless a kernel of wheat falls to the ground and dies, it remains only a single seed. But if it dies, it produces many seeds..’ John 12:24 NIV</p>
<p>Faithplant</p>
<p>When you look at what the Bible encourages us to do—things like looking out for others, being patient, loving those who hurt us—nowhere will you find the promise that it will always be easy. Sometimes, there’s just hard work involved. <br></br>So why do it in the first place? Because as we do those things, we grow more and more into what God wants us to become—like Christ. And the more we become like Jesus was, the more God can use us. God gives us amazing promises about what He has in store for us (Jeremiah 29:11, anyone?), and working through us, the world can be completely transformed by His Kingdom. The best way He can do that for (and through) us is if we allow ourselves to become more like Jesus. It might sound daunting, and it might seem like you’ll lose yourself in the process; but the reverse is true. You’ll find that the more you let Jesus mould you, the more you’ll become ‘you’. Jesus’ picture of this is a grain of wheat. On its own, a grain isn’t that impressive. But plant it, and it multiplies. Becoming like Christ isn’t all your work, but give yourself to God as the grain, and you’ll see amazing things come from that. <br></br>Find a small seed. Place it in your hand, and think about how small it currently is. How small is your life right now? Think about how big and useful the seed will become. How can your life be as large and productive for God as the seed becomes?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 16–18, John 3:9–21, Ps 110, Prov 26:13–16</p></body><body>
<p>Sun 11 October</p>
<p>‘The instructions of the Lord are perfect, reviving the soul...’ Psalm 19:7 NLT</p>
<p>Bible FAQ</p>
<p>Truth is, there’s a lot of soul–changing goodness in your Bible. If you know this already, we have one piece of advice today—go for it. Crack it open. If you’re unsure of where to start, look down at SoulFood at the bottom of this reading. Use it every day and it’ll take you through the Bible in one year.<br></br>Alternatively, head to the Gospel of John. Or one of Paul’s letters. Whatever you fancy really; the point is, once you’ve started reading, we reckon that’s half of the battle there and then. Satan doesn’t want you to learn God’s truth, and keeping your Bible shut might just further his plans.<br></br>Now’s a good time to open your Bible (app) as we head into Psalm 19. Time for a David–inspired Bible FAQ: Feeling down? God’s Word will revive your soul (Psalm 19:7). It brings ‘joy to the heart’ (Psalm 19:8). And why should we follow what God says? We’ll benefit from it—His ways of living are ‘sweeter than honey’ (Psalm 19:10), and there’s ‘great reward for those who obey them’ (Psalm 19:11). <br></br>King David knew what he was talking about. He knew he needed God’s help to ‘Cleanse me from these hidden faults. Keep your servant from deliberate sins! Don’t let them control me. Then I will be free of guilt.’ (Psalm 19:12–13 NLT) There’s power in your Bible—God will use it to change us for good. Read the whole of today’s Psalm. Do you feel challenged?<br></br>Encouraged to read more Bible? Bring your thoughts to God, and pray about how you can take in more of God’s Word each day. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Joel 2:23–32, Acts 2:1–21</p></body><body>
<p>Mon 12 October</p>
<p>‘…We are…created…to do good works, which God prepared in advance...’ Ephesians 2:10 NIV</p>
<p>We Have Work To Do</p>
<p>The day before yesterday we looked at this idea of becoming more like Christ in our day–to–day lives. This might sound like a mammoth task; but we’re not asking you to get busy forming planets and putting the sun in place or performing miracles everywhere you look. God isn’t asking you either, but rather He made you to be just like Jesus. <br></br>Paul the apostle wrote about how God ‘created’ us for good works—and the best part? God planned this all before. ‘You knit me together in my mother’s womb.’ (Psalm 139:13 NIV) Before you were born, God knew you and wove you together so you’d be able to accomplish great things here on earth. He’s had a purpose for you all along. <br></br>How can we tell we are being the version that God created us to be? Galatians 5:22–23 is a good indicator. When God is working in and through us and we see things in our lives like love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, gentleness, faithfulness and self–control, we know we’re doing the ‘good works’ God created us to do. Also, remember: God believes in you. He created you to be this way. If you’re willing to become more like Him, He’ll never leave you or leave this work ‘unfinished’. That’s a promise. <br></br>As you look at that list of nine ‘fruits’ from Galatians 5:22–23, is there one you’d like to have more of? Pray about that specifically today.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 19–21, John 3:22–36, Ps 89:1–14, Prov 26:17–19 </p></body><body>
<p>Tue 13 October</p>
<p>‘...for you, O Lord, help and comfort me...’ Psalm 86:17 NLT</p>
<p>Church Health: Hindrances</p>
<p>Even though the Church is a reflection of God here on earth, we can still let each other down. Because we’re human. Now, if there’s serious negative stuff going on inside of a church, it’s important to seek help or (safely and gracefully) call out the wrongs. Definitely. But sometimes it’s the little things that make up our most of our irritations with the Church. Y’know, things like the quality of the coffee, *that* song (that the worship leader played yet again, sigh), or the preacher that never quite gets to the point. But… actually, let’s remember that we’re a part of those things. As a Christian, you’ve become a part of the Church. We’re made to be involved in the wider community of Christians, and if our preferences separate us from that, we’re missing something. <br></br>Paul wrote that the Church is the ‘body of Christ’ and that ‘each one of you is a part of it.’ (1 Corinthians 12:27 NIV) He also wrote that we all ‘fall short of the glory of God.’ (Romans 3:23 NIV) Together, those two verses tell us that, exactly like a body, the eternal Church, and each individual church, takes work and understanding to keep it healthy. All of us, then, should be working in some way to build churches that look more and more Christ–like.<br></br>So, let’s take it back to basics. Grab some Christian friends, get together to worship, chat through some Scripture and share a meal together. That is where the Church starts. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 22–24, John 4:1–12, Ps 89:15–37, Prov 26:20–22</p></body><body>
<p>Wed 14 October</p>
<p>‘... Do you want to get well?’ John 5:6 NIV</p>
<p>Church Health: Healing Hindrances</p>
<p>In John 5:1–15, a man was lying paralysed by a pool in Jerusalem, waiting for ‘an angel of the Lord [who] came down to the pool and stirred up the water. After the angel did this, the first person to go into the pool was healed from any sickness he had.’ (John 5:4 NCV) Great situation, right? Great place to wait, and a good amount of hope that he might get healed. But. He’d been waiting for 38 years! When Jesus met him, the man explained, ‘I have no one to put me into the pool when the water bubbles up. Someone else always gets there ahead of me.’ (John 5:7 NLT) So near, and yet so far. No friends helping him, and no help from the religious leaders (see John 5:9–10). The story went pretty well after that, though, meeting Jesus and all. The man was miraculously healed. <br></br>If you’ve been struggling in church, for whatever reason, you can still have hope. Even if it’s been years, if no friends have helped you, if even the leaders haven’t helped you, if you’ve been in the right place, but haven’t got any help, you can have hope. Jesus can meet you, even in that same church. If you can answer His question, ‘Would you like to get well?’ (John 5:6) and follow His direction, ‘Get up! Pick up your mat and walk!’ (John 5:8) with an obedient, faith–filled, step toward Him, you can be healed even where you’ve been sitting and waiting for years. <br></br>If you’re ready, tell Jesus that you want to be well.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 25–27, John 4:13–26, Ps 89:38–52, Prov 26:23–26</p></body><body>
<p>Thu 15 October</p>
<p>‘The measure you use... will be measured to you.’ Luke 6:38 NIV</p>
<p>Ridiculous Generosity</p>
<p>How much should I give? How much time? How much money? How much of my energy? Frankly, how much of my chocolate bar should I give him/her? How much of this pie, given that my lunch will be what’s left? <br></br>Instead of giving a complicated formula (‘two chocolate chunks for every time they helped you clean up last week…’), Jesus says, ‘Give to the one who asks you, and do not turn away from the one who wants to borrow from you.’ (Matthew 5:42 NIV) Gulp. <br></br>But how, Jesus? If I do that, then I’ll go broke overnight! We figure there’s only one way Jesus can ask us to be so generous: if He’s already got us covered. It’ll be hard for us to go hungry, if God’s our Heavenly Father. It’ll be hard for us to run out, if we have Him to ask for things. You probably don’t need us to remind you that the Gospel message, of God dying for you so that you can be forgiven, is ‘ridiculously generous’. God isn’t just generous, He goes beyond. And that seems to be His design for how we should be, too. With a world in need, God’s answer is to go beyond the call of duty, Himself. Now that He’s gifted us His Holy Spirit, He’s looking to us to carry on that good work. <br></br>What have you been given, recently, that you can pass on to bless someone else? Been bought a coffee? Buy one for someone who needs it. Taken for a meal? Give food to a foodbank. Reflect a gift you’ve *already* had by passing the blessing on.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 28–29, John 4:27–38, Ps 100, Prov 26:27–28 </p></body><body>
<p>Fri 16 October</p>
<p>‘You must have the same attitude that Christ Jesus had.’ Philippians 2:5 NLT</p>
<p>Unselfish? (1)</p>
<p>Have you ever planned an unselfish act, but held off on it until you had a place or time (or Facebook post) where people would see your work? Paul, in writing today’s verse, had a challenge for that kind of attitude. He told us to adopt Jesus’ style. The difference between His way and ours is this: in a world where most things are centred around making us look good, Jesus’ mind was set on shining the light on God. How, on earth, are we supposed to replicate that? <br></br>Well, in the original Greek Paul wrote, he said that we should to have the same ‘mind’ as Jesus—to literally think like He did. Hmm. Suppose our best bet is to ask Him, then. When we put down our own agendas, and turn to Him empty–handed, we’re open to help so many people. We’re surrounded with people everyday who could do with an others–focused helper who’ll put aside their own concerns and help them—and more than that, shine a light on God for them. The challenge is to put aside our mind that would naturally help only those who help us, and ask Jesus for His mind. Even daily. Willing to make that trade? Here’s a way to see how big a hindrance our own attitudes are: load up a backpack, chock–a–block with whatever you can find that’ll make it heavy. Spend half an hour going about whatever you’re doing with it on. Then, take it off. We’re much more free to help others when we aren’t carrying our own agendas.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 30–32, John 4:39–54, Ps 32, Prov 27:1–3 </p></body><body>
<p>Sat 17 October</p>
<p>‘Let no one seek his own, but each one the other’s well–being.’ 1 Corinthians 10:24 NKJ</p>
<p>Unselfish? (2)</p>
<p>What does unselfishness look like? At the end of the day, it’s your prayer life with God that’ll help you find the best steps for putting Him and others first. The best way for you depends on your personal circumstances. But for now, one or two ideas: <br></br>If you reckon you’re the leader type, it’s good to consider what your motive is: actually leading people? Or just impressing them? Teachers all have to be careful about this one—in the book of James, we find that being responsible for others’ learning means we’ll be under greater scrutiny (James 3:1, not for the faint of heart). Leading others can’t be done on a whim—you have to be willing to follow up what you say to people with actions that show them you really care. <br></br>Another thought. When we’re under someone’s authority, like a church leader, how humble are we about it? Sometimes the culture encourages us to be as critical as we can to those who teach us. Now, just being ‘under someone’s authority’ doesn’t mean you can’t criticise anything they do or say—Jesus Himself pointed out the corruption of the religious leaders of the time. But Hebrews 13:17 NIV adds that we should ‘submit to their authority.’ Why? ‘So that their work will be a joy, not a burden, for that would be of no benefit to you.’ Recognising that our leaders have responsibility can help us to take in what they’re teaching us, as well as help us best work out how to serve where we find ourselves. Take time to thank your church leaders today, for everything that they do for the church.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 33–35, John 5:1–15, Ps 87, Prov 27:4–6</p></body><body>
<p>Sun 18 October</p>
<p>‘...take an interest in others, too.’ Philippians 2:4 NLT</p>
<p>Unselfish? (3)</p>
<p>Philippians 2 is fun. Go read it. (Yeah, we know! Another whole Bible chapter.) Now, let’s look at this bit: ‘In your relationships… have the same mindset as Christ Jesus.’ (Philippians 2:5 NIV) Not a particularly easy one. <br></br>Jesus sees value in you, as He does with everyone. Enough to become human and die for us (take a moment to try to grasp the awesomeness of that one more time). And He wants us to see the same value in each other. He wants us to genuinely care about each other. Which can be easy if we’re talking about our family or our friends, but not so easy when we realise that means we have to love those people that we may not particularly like. Not just polite kindness, but genuine concern. <br></br>Paul wrote: ‘I hope...to send Timothy to you...I have no one else like him, who will show genuine concern for your welfare. For everyone looks out for their own interests, not those of Jesus Christ.’ (Philippians 2:19–22 NIV) Maybe you find it easy to feel for people, or maybe you take longer to form a bond with someone. By living for Jesus, we can’t help but love those that He does. One way to start might be to look out for places, opportunities and gifts that you realise other people might enjoy more than you—when you’re offered them, perhaps you can redirect them to others. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Isa 61:1–9, Luke 4:16–30 </p></body><body>
<p>Mon 19 October</p>
<p>‘...no man cared for my soul.’ Psalm 142:4 KJV</p>
<p>Unselfish? (4)</p>
<p>Think about a person who loves you. It feels pretty great to really know that they care about you, doesn’t it? (And, if you can’t think of anyone that you really really believe loves you, give them and yourself some credit; trust us, you’re more loveable than you think). <br></br>You might already know that God’s love goes beyond that. Psalm 118 thanks God for loving the Psalmist as no one else does. God’s love is enough, true; He will always love you beyond any love you can imagine. And maybe you know that, or maybe you’re still trying to accept that, but either way it’s not easy to grasp just *how much* He cares. God’s love is hard to believe sometimes. No one can care for you on the same scale as God does, but it’s still really nice to feel like they care. To feel liked. <br></br>If you know how it feels to feel completely alone, and you also know how it feels to be loved—how would you want to make others feel? And sure, we can never love anyone as much as God does, but He still calls us to love them. It’s simple really: let’s show them that love. Let’s show people that somebody cares. Not everybody in your life knows how much God loves them, and not everybody will be able to accept that, so start by showing them that *you* love them. (And if you can’t accept how much God loves you yet, start by praying that He will reveal it to you.) Now, send a ‘how r u?’ text to someone you wouldn’t normally. Show them that someone is thinking about them and caring.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 36–38, John 5:16–30, Ps 41, Prov 27:7–9</p></body><body>
<p>Tue 20 October</p>
<p>‘…I am not seeking my own good but the good of many…’ 1 Corinthians 10:33 NIV</p>
<p>Unselfish? (5)</p>
<p>In the last leg of this series, we’re faced with a challenging verse. Paul knew that in order to put God on display to as many people as possible, he couldn’t be the centre of attention. In 1 Corinthians 10:31 NIV, he says, ‘...whether you eat or drink or whatever you do, do it all for the glory of God.’ <br></br>Eating and drinking? How can we do that for God’s glory? It’s not really Godly guidance about which knife and fork you use for what course. This is about keeping the main thing the main thing, keeping the focus on God. We’re told to ‘not cause anyone to stumble’ (1 Corinthians 10:32 NIV) by how we act, even if we’re not doing anything wrong. <br></br>Paul uses the example of food sacrificed to other ‘gods’. The Jews, who were the root of the Church, were forbidden to eat that food, but Jesus had declared all foods clean (Mark 7:19). So, if Paul was popping round for dinner with a Jewish friend, he could rant about the lack of bacon. Or he could focus on telling his friend that Jesus is Lord, and that there’s great news for him because of that. <br></br>It can take patience, and a determination to love (or ‘grace’) to ignore our personal gripes when we see small things we disagree with, but Paul wanted to prevent unnecessary disagreements. Paul wanted to have God–filled conversations to help welcome everyone he possibly could into God’s Kingdom. We can do the same.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ex 39–40, John 5:31–47, Ps 15, Prov 27:10–12 </p></body><body>
<p>Wed 21 October</p>
<p>‘...we can certainly do it.’ Numbers 13:30 NIV</p>
<p>Rewrite the Script</p>
<p>We’re going back to Caleb, the spies, and the Promised Land (October 6 was when we last checked in on them, if you need the reminder). Caleb has the guts to defy the people of Israel, and their spies, who’ve declared that reaching the Promised Land isn’t going to be a walk in the park—even though God had told them it was theirs for the taking. In the face of their loud pessimism, Caleb has to do some serious rewording. <br></br>‘They’re stronger,’ ‘we’re like grasshoppers,’ ‘we’re not able’... became ‘Let us go up at once and occupy it,’ and ‘We can certainly do it.’ See what he did? He didn’t even say ‘let’s go fight them’—he said, ‘Let’s walk in.’ It’s that easy. A life–filled faith beats back lifeless words. Caleb knew that God had told them they could do it, so He kept on talking the way God talked. Words can be a boost to your faith when you’re down, or when you’re thinking, ‘I’m not what other people think I am,’ or ‘I haven’t got what it takes, really.’ Talk about yourself the way God talks about you: His words for you are: beloved, chosen, with a ‘spirit of power, love and a strong mind.’ (2 Timothy 1:7 NIV) Rewrite the script, in your thoughts, in the voice you use to talk to yourself, in conversations with others: get rewording, and see what it does to your faith. Today, take on giant #1: the voice you use to talk to yourself. Keep a tally of the most common words you use. See if they are mostly criticising or talking yourself down. If so—go up at once and occupy your thoughts, yeah? </p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 1–3, John 6:1–15, Ps 5, Prov 27:13–16</p></body><body>
<p>Thu 22 October</p>
<p>‘He comforts us every time we have trouble...’ 2 Corinthians 1:4 NCV</p>
<p>Keep Your Hands Open (1)</p>
<p>Potential bubble–burst coming up: following God isn’t always easy. And becoming a Christian isn’t signing up for a life of leisure. Who knew? But honestly, that’s fairly easy to grasp, right? We can probably all identify with ‘not easy’. When we decide to live for Jesus, we’re deciding to live for Someone other than ourselves, which definitely means we’ll be out of our comfort zones from time to time. Why do we do it? Because, put simply, gratitude. Yet He’s given us more than we could ever give to Him. <br></br>Following God isn’t always easy, but He doesn’t leave us in the lurch. When He asks something of us, it’s not a no–contact–mission with a self–destructing–manila–envelope type of deal. He’s there doing it with us, comforting us and supporting us. More than that though, 2 Corinthians 1:4 NCV says that God ‘comforts us every time we have trouble...’ *Every* time. Not just in the big things. That’s pretty nice to know, every time we have trouble with work, relationships, health—anything. <br></br>And let’s be 100% honest, it is a thing to know. It’s not always a thing to feel. We may not always feel God’s comfort around us like a fuzzy blanket, but we can make the choice to know, to recognise that He’s already in every troubling situation that we can face. <br></br>So, start asking God into the small things. Jot down anything that worries you today. We mean *anything* that makes you worry—even if it feels tiny in the grand scheme. Don’t dwell on each thing, but pray a simple prayer for peace—just a few words—over each one. Keep your hands open, God wants to help in all of those things.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 4–7, John 6:16–24, Ps 126, Prov 27:17–19</p></body><body>
<p>Fri 23 October</p>
<p>‘As one whom his mother comforts, so will I comfort you...’ Isaiah 66:13 NKJ</p>
<p>Keep Your Hands Open (2)</p>
<p>There are some things we just can’t do on our own (ever tried playing boardgames against yourself?) And sometimes we just need someone to help, to comfort us. So, at the expense of sounding cheesy (and repetitive), there’s really no other way to say this: God loves you, and He wants to be that help for you. When we’re at that stage where nothing we’re doing is working, we can get angry and think: ‘God mustn’t care about our problems, because we’re trying to fix them but it’s not happening—right?’ Wrong. We need to take a step back, stop trying to control things, and ask God how to handle it.<br></br>But then maybe you have asked for help. Awesome. But you’re not done. Sometimes, it’s continuing to ask for God’s help that gets us through those times when we’re not sure He’s there. As laborious as it feels, we need to be active in seeking God’s comfort and help. We need to actually pray, to read our Bible, to worship. Those things may be the last things you feel like doing, but (typically) that’s when we need to do it the most. God’s given us triple comfort: the Bible as comfort, other Christians as comfort and the Holy Spirit as comfort (John 14:16). Need a prayer of comfort right now? Get in touch with prayforme.com.au. There are so many ways God’s offering comfort. Just pick one, and keep your hands open.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 8–11, John 6:25–34, Ps 85, Prov 27:20–22 </p></body><body>
<p>Sat 24 October</p>
<p>‘They shall bear fruit in old age...’ Psalm 92:14 NKJ</p>
<p>All Up From Here</p>
<p>Some people are more freaked out by the idea of old age than the idea of death. Even when getting old is a long way off, lots of us associate old age with growing lonelier and less important—quite reasonably, that scares us. This kind of fear is what drives the kind of living in the present that’s summed up by instagram–ready quotes like ‘Live Fast, Die Young and Leave a Beautiful Corpse’ and ‘Eat Sleep Party Repeat’. <br></br>What if, in Christianity, the older you get, the more you’ve lived for God and lived for others, the greater and more significant you get? Psalm 92 is a slap in the face of fear; the fear that says you’ll stop being important, you’ll stop mattering, you’ll lose everything. It says that those who live for God ‘stay fresh and green.’ (Psalm 92:14 NIV) Strength and energy—and more than that, an impact on the world that comes from faithfulness to God. Take a second and think: how much is your life the product of the prayer of older Christians who love you? In God’s world, the elderly are a vital, giving, part of communities. They *matter*. They are witnesses to the goodness of God across decades of life and they can testify He gives strength and zeal exactly where the world fears decay. Want your growing old to be less about frantic fear and more about confident flourishing? Absorb the Gospel now (with your whole being, not just your mind), soak it in like a plant’s roots, and look forward to an incredible return.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 12–16, John 6:35–51, Ps 98, Prov 27:23–24 </p></body><body>
<p>Sun 25 October</p>
<p>‘A great storm arose...’ Matthew 8:24 NCV</p>
<p>Jesus vs. Storm (1)</p>
<p>A storm came while Jesus and His disciples were in a boat—and Jesus was asleep. The disciples, understandably, kind of freaked out a bit and woke Him up asking for help. And Jesus, calm as anything, tells the storm to stop. It stops. <br></br>Does anyone else think that Jesus comes across as the coolest and calmest guy ever in this story? Seriously: He wakes up to a storm, tells His friends to settle down, commands the weather, then probably really casually goes back to his nap, leaving them gawking. I mean, He does have demons to expel, paralysis to heal, dinners to eat (seriously, read some chapters of Matthew) it makes sense that He’d need some sleep. <br></br>But that’s the point: of course Jesus wasn’t fazed. Of course He was calm and in control. The disciples panicked, thinking Jesus wasn’t aware of the danger and that He wouldn’t be able to save them. His response? ‘You of little faith, why are you so afraid?’ (Matthew 8:26 NIV) Now let’s be fair to the disciples: Jesus was asleep. They assumed that meant He wasn’t really with them. Jesus is telling us otherwise.<br></br>You might feel like God isn’t there in your fear. We all face our own storms, and we can feel really alone in them. Our work, school, health or whatever it is that’s making us worry—we can fall into the trap of feeling like we’re alone. But God is with us, even when we don’t believe it. As soon as the disciples asked for help, Jesus gave it. He’s able, when He’s asked. Ask God into whatever is bothering you. Pray that He’ll give you what you need to get through it.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Kings 6:8–23, Matt 5:43–48, Luke 6:27–36</p></body><body>
<p>Mon 26 October</p>
<p>‘...Who can this be...?’ Matthew 8:27 NKJ</p>
<p>Jesus vs. Storm (2)</p>
<p>If you missed yesterday’s reading, go and read that; we’re going to talk about that storm a bit more. <br></br>Let’s give some credit to the disciples who were with Jesus: they didn’t just freak out, they asked Jesus for help. But then they were so shocked when He actually calmed the storm. ‘The men were amazed and asked, “What kind of man is this? Even the winds and the waves obey Him!”’ (Matthew 8:27 NIV) We need to expect our prayers to be answered, or we’ll never be able to move past our fear. Jesus tells us so many times: ‘don’t be afraid’. Honestly, it’s normal to be scared or worried about getting through our issues (or not getting through), but if we ask God for help, we will get it. He promises us that. <br></br>Often we’ll find that we turn to God when we’ve exhausted our own resources and energy, and we’re desperate. Then maybe we’ll pray, He’ll answer, and we’ll wonder why we didn’t ask God to begin with. (Hint: because we can be a bit dim sometimes). But then next time you might remember to ask for His help a little earlier. It *will* become easier to ask for God’s help—and when it becomes your first instinct, suddenly the things that scared you won’t scare you so much, because you know that God has your back. <br></br>God wants to help—is it time for you to take Him up on it?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 17–21, John 6:52–59, Ps 127, Prov 27:25–27 </p></body><body>
<p>Tue 27 October</p>
<p>‘...He departed again to the mountain by Himself alone.’ John 6:15 NKJ</p>
<p>Burnout</p>
<p>John tells us about loads of things that Jesus did as a healer and teacher. Plus, he adds: ‘Jesus did many other things as well. If every one of them were written down...the whole world would not have room for the books that would be written.’ (John 21:25 NIV) <br></br>Our lives can get really busy with work and obligations and maybe even a little free time that can be spent worrying about all of the work and the obligations (that’s different from procrastination— honest). ‘Burnout’ might be a very familiar term, or a very familiar feeling (and, just to clarify, we mean the stress that results from lack of balance between work and rest, not the old PS1 game. Unless that’s how you’re procrastinating.) When we get bogged down with what we’re ‘supposed’ to do and take on too much, we can feel like we’re drowning. <br></br>As so often happens, the Bible can offer some help. Seriously, this book is great. We’re told that Jesus would often go off alone to pray and to recharge. He even did it when people were looking or waiting for Him (like Luke 4). He had the right priorities. He knew that it was more important to spend His time with God than doing anything else. Stuff like praying, reading our Bible, worshipping alone or just spending a quiet time with God without the pressures of other people can be an awesome help to our spiritual and mental health. <br></br>Write down the things you’re worried about doing or forgetting in a notebook. Close it. Now spend some time with God. 10/20/30 minutes—however long you need. Trust Him: your to–do list can wait.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 22–25, John 6:60–71, Ps 114, Prov 28:1–4 </p></body><body>
<p>Wed 28 October</p>
<p>‘Each of you should give what you have decided in your heart...’ 2 Corinthians 9:7 NIV</p>
<p>Bank of God unLimited</p>
<p>Giving is a big part of being a Christian, and that can mean different things: tithing, donating to food banks, giving money to charities, giving time to volunteer. But, whatever form it may take, God calls us to give—there’s no getting away from it. <br></br>But money’s tight? And the schedule is hectic? How’s this then—we’re called to do more than give; we’re called to give CHEERFULLY. Does that mean you put on your best smile as God whips that last dollar out of your hand and is never seen again? Not our God. He’s not interested in robbing you, nor does He have much use for His own pile of cash. He is very interested in getting you to have the right attitude to money, though, and in having you realise that He can provide everything you need. God wants us to see the value of giving to others and to be happy to reach out with practical help to those who need it. He also wants us to be safe in the knowledge we’ve a different sort of security and support in Him. <br></br>So is God basically Heaven’s Investment Bank? Do we ‘deposit’ our cash to poorer people here, and expect a cheque through the door from an angel next week? Not usually. That ‘different sort’ of support we mentioned means different priorities. Sometimes God gives you back what you gave, and more. He’s really generous. But sometimes, He gives you something worth more to Him: He moulds your character. If money’s your be–all–and–end–all, God’s not a sound investment. But, money *not* being your focus is just His point.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 26–29, John 7:1–13, Ps 104:1–23, Prov 28:5–8</p>
<p>October 29</p>
<p>‘…with the ability…God supplies...’ 1 Peter 4:11 NKJ</p>
<p>Use What God Gave You!</p>
<p>When God gives you an assignment He gives you all that’s needed to fulfil it. In fact, by working out what you’re really good at helps you figure out your calling. Winston Churchill said, ‘To each there comes in his or her lifetime a special moment when they are tapped on the shoulder and offered the chance to do a very special thing, unique to them and fitted to their talent. What a tragedy if that moment finds them unprepared or unqualified for that which could have been their finest hour.’ <br></br>You can’t always be what you want to be, but you can be everything God wants you to be. That’s because He assigns us ‘…each according to his own ability.’ (Matthew 25:15 NKJ) What do you love doing and do consistently well? Is music your thing? What about computers or maybe helping with little kids? Paul says, ‘Now to each one the manifestation of the Spirit is given for the common good.’ (1 Corinthians 12:7 NIV) That means some of the things other people find boring, will give you a buzz. That’s not an excuse to ONLY do the stuff you love—not many people feel gifted to be pick up rubbish or stack the chairs! Don’t confuse the Gifts of the Spirit with the Fruits of the Spirit (see August 1). Picking up rubbish and stacking chairs is one of the second type. So stop apologising for the skills you don’t have, discover the gifts God has given you and put them to work for His Kingdom.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 30–33, John 7:14–24, Ps 104:24–35, Prov 28:9–12 </p>
<p>October 30</p>
<p>‘…Jesus showed Himself again to the disciples at the Sea.’ John 21:1 NKJ</p>
<p>Bring it on, Jesus</p>
<p>You’ve been trying, trying and trying but it’s useless. It worked yesterday, but that was yesterday. We all know what that feels like, right? Well in today’s story we meet the disciples having one of those days. As He watched them struggling around in their boat, Jesus shouted from the shore, ‘Cast the net on the right side of the boat…’ (John 21:6 NKJ) When they did, they caught so many fish their net was stretched to its limit. <br></br>Lesson #1: Often, God gives the breakthrough right at the end of your struggle. As long as you think you can do it on your own, He’ll let you try. But when you run out of natural energy you discover it’s ‘Not by might, nor by power, but by My Spirit says the Lord…’ (Zechariah 4:6 NKJ) <br></br>Lesson #2: He never takes His eye off you. The mists of early dawn meant they couldn’t see Him, but He could see them. In spite of your disappointment and the frustration of your own efforts, you’re never beyond His care—or His reach. <br></br>Lesson #3: He invites you to come and eat. Jesus already had a cooked breakfast waiting for the tired fishermen and invited them to join Him. He knew there’s nothing more ‘spiritual’ that a proper brekkie! It’s the human life at its most basic—and most fantastic—beach, fire, mates, chilling, laughing. Bring it on, Jesus! </p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 34–37, John 7:25–32, Ps 9, Prov 28:13–16</p>
<p>October 31</p>
<p>‘…take up the whole armour of God…’ Ephesians 6:13 NKJ</p>
<p>Drawing the Line</p>
<p>Simon the Sorcerer was doing good business. The people ‘…followed him because he had amazed them for a long time with his magic.’ (Acts 8:11 NIV) But, no doubt to everyone’s astonishment, he chose to accept the Gospel message and got baptised. Sadly though, before long, traces of his old ways emerged: he offered Peter and John money to buy the gift of the Holy Spirit! How did the apostles handle this? Simple! They confronted this guy with the truth in Jesus’ name, saying: ‘Repent of this wickedness and pray to the Lord.’ (Acts 8:22 NIV) You see, Peter knew something that we should all know: when a new Christian starts turning back to their old ways you must quickly deal with it or they’ll end up hurting themselves and other people too. Being fuzzy and soft in those moments helps no–one. <br></br>For all of us, whether disciples for 10 minutes or 10 years, the forces of evil around us are real; we can’t just ignore them and hope they’ll play nice or maybe just go away. To fight and win you must know what you are up against. There’ll be times when you have to be decisive and draw a line saying, ‘That’s it, the other side of this line is out of bounds for me now that I follow Jesus.’ Do you need to draw or re–draw some lines around your life today?</p>
<p>SoulFood (Halloween): Deut 18:9–18, Dan 2, Is 47:5–15, Acts 16:16–34 </p></body></html>ml>