<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" lang="en-AU"><head><title>???</title><meta content="ahamilton" name="author"/><meta content="2015-09-27T06:56:00Z" name="dcterms.created"/><meta content="2015-09-27T06:56:00Z" name="dcterms.modified"/><meta content="United Christian Broadcasters Australia Ltd" name="dcterms.publisher"/><meta content="XMLmind Word To XML Professional Edition 1.0.0-beta04" name="generator"/></head><body><p>SATURDAY AUGUST 1</p><p>‘He got into one of the boats…belonging to Simon…’ Luke 5:3 NIV</p><p>When Jesus Comes on Board</p><p>One day Jesus ‘…<i>saw at the water’s edge two boats, left there by the fishermen, who were washing their nets. He got into one of the boats…belonging to Simon, and asked him to put out a little from shore. Then He sat down and taught the people from the boat. When He had finished speaking, He said to Simon, “Put out into deep water, and let down the nets for a catch.” Simon answered, “Master, we’ve worked hard all night and haven’t caught anything. But because You say so, I will let down the nets.” When they had done so, they caught such a large number of fish that their nets began to break.</i>’ (Luke 5:2–6 NIV) Are you sitting today where Peter sat? Your outlook is bleak, your nets are empty, you’ve tried everything you know and you’re ready to give up? It happens; you get to the place where you simply stop expecting anything good. You’ve experienced too many disappointments and you’re afraid to dream, reach, stretch or broaden your horizons. Jesus knows how hard you’ve tried and today He’s inviting you to try again—this time with Him. Even though you’re wrestling with depression and tormenting memories, unemployment, addiction, financial failure or sickness, the Lord of new beginnings wants to come on board. If you listen to Him, He will show you what to do. Now, what He says may not initially make sense to you. But if you’re willing to respond like Peter—‘<i>Because You say so, I will</i>’—you’re on the threshold of a miracle. Today, listen and obey the words of Jesus and watch how your situation changes.</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Jn 1:1–3:10, Mark 2:13–22, Ps 78:40–55, Prov 20:4–6</p><p>SUNDAY AUGUST 2</p><p>‘…you will be able to discern what is best…’ Philippians 1:10 NIV</p><p>Don’t Go by Your Feelings</p><p>God gave you feelings, and you should never be ashamed of them. They can alert you to danger and give you insight into various situations. God actually uses our feelings to draw us closer to Him and highlight areas in our lives that need to be submitted to His Holy Spirit. But feelings are subjective; you can’t always trust them. Jon Walker says: ‘When old feelings creep back in we feel fearful, ashamed, hopeless, not good enough, unlovable, victimised, helpless and resentful… An event can trigger these reactions…ending a relationship, stress, problems at work and at home, times of change or illness…and sometimes these feelings return for no reason.’ So you must test your feelings, otherwise you’ll end up allowing ‘…<i>your feelings [to] get out of control</i>.’ (Colossians 3:5 NIV) It can be disastrous to act on what you see, hear and feel. Instead of reacting to feelings, you must learn to act on what God’s Word says. That’s the gold standard, and it never changes! For instance, even if you feel like you can walk on water, you can only do it if God has called you to step out of the boat. Paul says, ‘…<i>my prayer [is] that [you]…abound…in knowledge and…insight…that you may be able to discern what is best</i>…’ (Philippians 1:9–10 NIV) Bottom line: don’t rely on your feelings, rely on the knowledge and truth of God’s Word. You may feel worthless, but God says, ‘…<i>You are precious to Me …I love you</i>.’ (Isaiah 43:4 NLT) You may feel like a failure, but God says, ‘<i>There is…no condemnation for those…in Christ.</i>’ (Romans 8:1 NIV) </p><p>SoulFood: Ezek 37:1–14, Matt 27:50–53, 1 Thess 4:13–18</p><p>MONDAY AUGUST 3</p><p>‘These all wait for You, that You may give them their food in due season.’ Psalm 104:27 NKJV</p><p>It All Belongs to God (1)</p><p>We fear losing our job, our health insurance and our retirement benefits, so we amass possessions, thinking the more we have, the safer we are. </p><p>Jesus told a parable of one such person: <i>‘...“The land of a rich man produced plentifully, and he thought to himself, ‘What shall I do, for I have nowhere to store my crops?’ And he said, ‘I will do this: I will tear down my barns and build larger ones, and there I will store all my grain and my goods. </i>(Luke 12:16-18 ESV) Can’t you hear the presumption in those words? Just like us stockpiling pensions, possessions and property, he accumulated and stacked until his barns of belongings were overflowing. Then he said, <i>“...Soul, you have ample goods laid up for many years; relax, eat, drink, be merry.” </i>(Luke 12:19 ESV) The Bible says, ‘<i>Command those who are rich…not to…trust in uncertain riches but in the living God…</i>’ (1 Timothy 6:17 NKJV) Riches don’t bring security. The more you have, the more you have to lose! It’s ironic; the more you accumulate the more protective you become, and the greater your concern that it could all be swept away by events you can’t control. That’s not how God intended you to live. He wants you to save and He wants you to sow. And when you’ve done all that wisdom demands, to trust in nothing but Him. The Psalmist said, ‘…<i>Living things…small and great…all wait for You, that You may give them their food in due season</i>.’ (Psalm 104:25–27 NKJV) And He does. God’s the great giver, absolutely generous and utterly dependable. The resounding message of Scripture is clear: God owns it all. God shares it all. So place your trust in Him—not in belongings. </p><p>SoulFood: 1 Jn 3:11–5:21, Mark 2:23–3:6, Ps 78:56–64, Prov 20:7–10</p><p>TUESDAY AUGUST 4</p><p>‘When I fed them, they were satisfied; when they were satisfied, they became proud; then they forgot Me.’ Hosea 13:6 NIV</p><p>It All Belongs to God (2)</p><p>Paul writes: ‘<i>Command those who are rich in this present age not to be haughty, nor to trust in uncertain riches but in the living God, Who gives us richly all things to enjoy. Let them do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to give, willing to share</i>.’ (1 Timothy 6:17–18 NKJV) Are you ‘<i>rich in this present age</i>’? Almost half the world—more than three billion people—lives on less than $4 a day. So if your income is more than that, you’re rich by comparison. But prosperity comes with a warning: don’t be arrogant. ‘<i>Pride goes before destruction, a haughty spirit before a fall</i>.’ (Proverbs 16:18 NIV) The Scottish historian Thomas Carlyle wrote, ‘Adversity is sometimes hard upon a man. But for one man who can stand prosperity, there are a hundred that will stand adversity.’ God wants you to enjoy things without becoming obsessed with them. Accumulating possessions has a way of eclipsing God, no matter how meagre they may be. There’s a predictable progression from poverty to pride. The poor man prays and works; God hears and blesses. The humble man becomes rich and forgets God. The faithful poor man becomes the proud rich man. As God said through Hosea, ‘<i>When I fed them, they were satisfied; when they were satisfied, they became proud; then they forgot Me</i>.’ How can you avoid this trap? Remember that everything you own comes from God, and He’s the source of everything you’ll need in the future. So live with a grateful heart, and in total dependence on Him. </p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 1–2, Mark 3:7–19, Ps 78:65–72, Prov 20:11–14</p><p>WEDNESDAY AUGUST 5</p><p>‘“The silver is Mine and the gold”…declares the Lord…’ Haggai 2:8 NIV </p><p>It All Belongs to God (3)</p><p>How would you describe someone who built a house without giving any forethought to the foundation? Foolish! Likewise, God says, don’t put your trust in ‘<i>uncertain riches</i>’ (1 Timothy 6:17 NKJV). Between 1948 and 2001 the U.S. economy endured ten recessions, each averaging one year, and resulting in the loss of billions of dollars. That means every five years or so, the economy dumps its suitors and starts all over again. What word would you use to describe a husband who philandered his way through nine different wives over fifty years? Fickle? And how would you describe wife number ten? Foolish? Abraham was one of the richest men of his generation, and so was Job. The New Testament church had some rich people in it. The Bible says, ‘…<i>all who were possessors of lands or houses sold them …brought the proceeds…and laid them at the apostles’ feet</i>…’ (Acts 4:34–35 NKJV) God wants you to be blessed financially so you can bless His work. But the reason He doesn’t give some of us more money is because He knows we don’t have the maturity to handle it. It would be our undoing. And to those He does entrust with money, He says, ‘<i>Let them do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to give, willing to share.</i>’ (1 Timothy 6:18 NKJV) You don’t really own anything; you’re just a steward. ‘<i>“The silver is Mine and the gold is Mine,” declares the Lord.</i>’ The truth is, you’ll never be financially secure until you’re willing to say, ‘Yes!’ to God in whatever He asks you to do, knowing that He will always take care of you. Always!</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 3:1–4:23, Mark 3:20–35, Ps 119:1–8, Prov 20:15–18</p><p>THURSDAY AUGUST 6</p><p>‘To the Lord your God belong the heavens…the earth and everything in it.’ Deuteronomy 10:14 NIV </p><p>It All Belongs to God (4)</p><p>When it comes to our money, we like to think, ‘I earned it, so it’s mine.’ But that’s where you’re dead wrong! The Bible says: ‘<i>To the Lord your God belong the heavens…the earth and everything in it.</i>’ (Deuteronomy 10:14 NIV) ‘<i>Yours, O Lord, is the greatness…the power… the glory…the majesty and the splendour, for everything in Heaven and earth is Yours</i>.’ (1 Chronicles 29:11 NIV) ‘<i>“The silver…and the gold is Mine,” declares the Lord Almighty</i>.’ (Haggai 2:8 NIV) Riches are like Monopoly money; if you’re better than your competition, you end up with the deeds to the most expensive properties. But guess what? At the end of the day when the game is over, the participants leave the table and all the stuff goes back in the box. And if you were overly aggressive, the other players may end up not liking you. Here’s a humbling Scripture: ‘Do not be overawed when others grow rich... for they will take nothing with them when they die... Though while they live they count themselves blessed— they will join those... who will never again see the light of life. People who have wealth but lack understanding are like the beasts that perish.’ (Psalm 49:16–20 NIV) The God who owns it all gives it to us for two reasons: (1) <i>To enjoy</i>. (2) <i>To invest into fulfilling His purposes on earth</i>. When we live with that attitude, we replace fear with faith in God.</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 4:24–5:26, Mark 4:1–12, Ps 119:9–16, Prov 20:19–21</p><p>FRIDAY AUGUST 7</p><p>‘…in Him we live, and move, and have our being.’ Acts 17:28 NKJV</p><p>Ask God</p><p>George Washington Carver, an agricultural chemist who discovered three hundred uses for peanuts, shared these observations about God: ‘As a very small boy exploring the almost virgin woods of the old Carver place, I had the impression someone had just been there ahead of me. Things were so orderly, so clean, so harmoniously beautiful. A few years later in these same woods…I was practically overwhelmed with the sense of some great presence. Not only had someone been there, someone was there…Years later when I read in the Scriptures, “…<i>in Him we live, and move, and have our being</i>,” I knew what the writer meant. Never since have I been without this consciousness of the Creator speaking to me… the out–doors has been to me more and more a great cathedral in which God could be continuously spoken to and heard from… Man, who needed a purpose, a mission to keep him alive, had one. He could be…God’s co–worker… My purpose alone must be God’s purpose—to increase the welfare and happiness of His people… Why, then, should we, who believe in Christ, be so surprised at what God can do with a willing man in a laboratory?’ In 1921 Carver spoke before the United States House of Representatives. The chairman asked, ‘Dr. Carver, how did you learn all these things?’ He answered, ‘From an old book.’ The chairman asked, ‘What book?’ Carver replied, ‘The Bible.’ The chairman enquired, ‘Does the Bible talk about peanuts?’ Carver replied, ‘No sir, but it tells about the God who made the peanut. I asked Him to show me what to do with the peanut, and He did.’ Do you need a creative idea or solution today? Ask God!</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 6:1–7:19, Mark 4:13–25, Ps 119:17–24, Prov 20:22–24</p><p>SATURDAY AUGUST 8</p><p>‘…think about the things that are good…’ Philippians 4:8 NCV</p><p>How to Overcome Perfectionism</p><p>Be honest: Have you ever met a perfectionist who was truly happy? No, because when things must always ‘be a certain way’, life becomes miserable because it’s constantly changing. As soon as you solve one problem, another comes along. Instead of dwelling on their blessings and being grateful, perfectionists focus on what’s wrong and why they need to fix it. It may be a job they did that was less than perfect, a few kilos they need to lose, or even a disorganised wardrobe. Or it could be someone else’s imperfections: the way they live their life, how they behave, or the way they look. Constantly dwelling on flaws—your own or someone else’s—makes it impossible to be grateful. And gratitude is at the core of happiness. Now, let’s be clear; we’re not talking about striving to do better. That’s a good thing. We’re talking about obsessing over what’s wrong. There’ll always be a better way to do something, but that doesn’t mean you can’t enjoy life the way it is right now. So what’s the cure? Catch yourself before you fall into the trap of insisting that things should be different from how they are. Stop and remind yourself that, in the absence of your judgment, everything will work out just fine. Paul says, ‘…<i>in all things God works for the good of those who love Him</i>…’ (Romans 8:28 NIV) Are you getting it? God’s in control; it’s ok for you to let go. Instead of focusing on the negative, ‘<i>think about the things that are good and worthy of praise</i>.’ (Philippians 4:8 NCV) When you do, you’ll begin to discover how wonderful life is. </p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 7:20–9:44, Mark 4:26–41, Ps 119:25–32, Prov 20:25–27</p><p>SUNDAY AUGUST 9</p><p>‘…men shall dream dreams [and]…see visions.’ Joel 2:28 NKJV</p><p>The Power of Vision (1)</p><p>A boy supposedly once asked Michelangelo why he was working so hard chipping away on the block of marble that would become his greatest masterpiece: David. The artist replied, ‘There’s an angel inside this rock and I’m setting him free.’ The power of vision enables you to see a potential masterpiece in what others overlook or consider worthless. It also helps you discover things within yourself you never knew were there. It brings out the best in you. Many of the people God used in Scripture looked like losers before they looked like winners. After the disciples fished all night and caught nothing, Jesus told them, ‘…<i>Do not be afraid. From now on you will catch men</i>.’ (Luke 5:10 NKJV) They did, and they ended up: (1) <i>building a church that’s still thriving two thousand years later</i>; (2) <i>writing history’s greatest books</i>; (3) <i>having our sons named after them</i>. </p><p>Does that mean you can just dream a dream and God will fulfil it? No. Paul says, ‘…<i>You are not your own; you were bought at a price. Therefore honour God</i>…’ (1 Corinthians 6:19–20 NIV) Belonging to Christ means you lost the right to take your talents, opportunities and experiences and run off in any direction you please. But why would you even want to? What could possibly be more fulfilling than God’s purpose for your life? And what could be more tragic than missing it? You can’t wring enough meaning out of secular accomplishments to satisfy your soul. The hole you’re trying to fill has an eternal dimension only Christ can fill. That’s why you must pray, ‘Lord, show me Your vision for my life.’</p><p>SoulFood: Eccl 11:7–12:1, Ps 39:4–13, 2 Tim 4:6–8</p><p>MONDAY AUGUST 10</p><p>‘…acknowledge Him, and He shall direct your paths.’ Proverbs 3:6 NKJV </p><p>The Power of Vision (2)</p><p>Having God’s vision for your life gives you four things: (1) <i>Passion</i>. It makes you wake up in the morning and bound out of bed because there’s something out there you love to do; something you believe in and are good at; something bigger than you; something you can hardly wait to get at. (2) <i>Motivation</i>. Author Richard B. Edler said: ‘Safe living generally makes for regrets later on. We are all given talents and dreams. Sometimes the two don’t match. But more often than not we compromise both before ever finding out. Later on, we find ourselves looking back longingly to that time when we should’ve chased our true dreams and talents for all they’re worth. Don’t be pressured into thinking your dreams or talents aren’t prudent. They were never meant to be… They were meant to bring joy and fulfilment to your life.’ (3) <i>Direction</i>. Vision simplifies decision–making. Anything that moves you closer to your vision gets a green light; everything else should be approached with caution. Vision brings what’s important to the surface, and weeds out anything that stands in your way. Without vision, good things will keep you from achieving great things. People without a clear vision are easily distracted. They’ve a tendency to drift aimlessly from one thing to another. They’ve no spiritual, relational, financial or moral compass. Consequently, they make decisions that rob them of their dreams. (4) <i>Purpose</i>. Having vision is like getting a sneak preview of things to come. It says, ‘If you don’t show up, something important won’t happen. Your life matters. Without you, what could be—won’t be.’ </p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 10:1–12:22, Mark 5:1–10, Ps 119:33–40, Prov 20:28–30 </p><p>TUESDAY AUGUST 11</p><p>‘I will instruct you…in the way you should go.’ Psalm 32:8 NKJV </p><p>The Power of Vision (3)</p><p>Mother Teresa didn’t set out searching for fame; it found her. She simply went to India, found a need no one else was meeting, heard the call of God, allowed her heart to be consumed by it, and ministered to multitudes of the world’s most neglected and forgotten people in the slums of Calcutta. One of her most famous slogans was, ‘A life not lived for others is not a life at all.’ Let’s face it; much of what we do each day doesn’t seem to matter until it’s evaluated as part of a larger picture. When you take the minutiae of any given day, drop it into the cauldron of a God–ordained vision and stir it around, suddenly there’s purpose, worth, adrenaline and the joy that comes from knowing you’re fulfilling your destiny. It’s like the difference between filling bags with dirt and building a levee to save a town. There’s nothing glamorous about filling sandbags, but saving a town from the ravages of a flood is another matter entirely. Building a levee gives meaning to the drudgery of shovelling dirt into sandbags. And it’s like that with your vision. Many times the everyday routine of life can feel like shovelling dirt. But take those same routines and view them through the lens of a God–given purpose, and suddenly everything looks very different. Vision brings your world into focus. It brings order and purpose out of chaos. It enables you to see everything in a fresh light. And the good news is that God is the giver of visions—so ask Him for one!</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 12:23–15:29, Mark 5:11–20, Ps 119:41–48, Prov 21:1–3</p><p>WEDNESDAY AUGUST 12</p><p>‘…so the power of God could be seen in him.’ John 9:3 NLT</p><p>Take It to the Lord</p><p>When Jesus encountered a blind man, His disciples immediately began to discuss the man’s condition. They asked, ‘<i>Was this man’s blindness the result of his own sins, or the sins of his parents?</i>’ Jesus answered, <i>‘This happened so the power of God could be seen in him</i>.’ Notice four things: (1) <i>The disciples were eager to attribute the man’s problem to sin</i>. Satan will try to convince you that, because of your sin, you’re disqualified from God’s grace. You’re not! ‘<i>For He says to Moses: “I will have mercy on whom I have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I have compassion</i>.”’ (Romans 9:15 ESV) (2) <i>When Jesus healed him, the neighbours wanted to debate, not celebrate.</i> They started asking, ‘“…<i>Isn’t this the man who used to sit and beg?” Some said he was… others said, “No…”</i>’ (John 9:8–9 NLT) (3) <i>His healing failed the ‘religiosity test’</i> because the Pharisees said, “…<i>This man Jesus is not from God for He is working on the Sabbath…”</i>’ (John 9:16 NLT) (4) <i>Even the man’s parents weren’t free to praise God</i>, because ‘…<i>anyone saying Jesus was the Messiah would be expelled from the synagogue.</i>’ (John 9:22 NLT) To the neighbours he was a misfit, to church leaders a topic of debate, to his parents a social stigma, so they ‘…<i>threw him out</i>.’ (John 9:34 NIV) End of story? Thank God—no! <i>‘</i> Jesus...found him... and said, “...I have come into this world, so that the blind will see...”’ ( John 9:35, 39 NIV) So instead of rehashing your problem and listening to other people’s opinions, take it to the Lord in prayer. When you share it with others, the best you’ll get is sympathy, but when you share it with Jesus you’ll get a solution.</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 16–18, Mark 5:21–30, Ps 119:49–56, Prov 21:4–6</p><p>THURSDAY AUGUST 13</p><p>‘…do not complain…’ James 5:9 NCV</p><p>Go on a Complaining Fast</p><p>Whatever you keep doing becomes a habit. That’s why James says, ‘…<i>do not complain</i>…’ Author Jon Gordon says, ‘A complaining fast won’t just make everyone around you happier…you’ll experience more joy, peace, success and positive relationships.’ So instead of complaining when things go wrong: (1) <i>Practise gratitude</i>. Giving thanks for three blessings every day energises you and makes you feel happier. It’s impossible to be grateful and negative at the same time. (2) <i>Encourage others</i>. Instead of complaining about what people do wrong, focus on what they’re doing right. ‘…<i>encourage…people who are afraid. Help those who are weak. Be patient with everyone.</i>’ (1 Thessalonians 5:14 NCV) It’s ok to criticise people’s weaknesses as long as you balance it with three times more praise. (3) <i>Focus on your success</i>. Start a success journal. Every night before you go to bed, write down something great about your day. It could be an uplifting conversation…or an accomplishment you’re proud of. There’s truth to the old saying, ‘Nothing succeeds like success.’ When you focus on success you set the stage for more to follow. (4) <i>Learn to let go</i>. Instead of obsessing about what you can’t change, focus on what you can influence. When you stop trying to control everything and place your life in God’s hands, things have a way of working out. (5) <i>Use the power of prayer</i>. Paul says, ‘…<i>pray…on all occasions with all kinds of prayers and requests</i>…’ (Ephesians 6:18 NIV) Prayer reduces stress, boosts positive energy and promotes health. When you’re under pressure, instead of complaining, plug in to God’s power and recharge your batteries. </p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 19:1–23:20, Mark 5:31–43, Ps 119:57–64, Prov 21:7–9</p><p>FRIDAY AUGUST 14</p><p>‘Wait patiently for the Lord. Be brave and courageous…’ Psalm 27:14 NLT</p><p>Wait (1)</p><p>It’s in looking back that we realise: (1) <i>God had something better in mind for us</i>. (2) <i>We weren’t mature enough at that point to handle what we were asking Him for</i>. We think we’re ready, but God knows when we are. Scripture often commands us to ‘<i>wait on the Lord</i>’. Learning to wait is a test of maturity. John MacArthur writes: ‘People find it difficult with life if they can’t instantly gratify every desire. They want to eliminate every discomfort, difficulty, injustice or deprivation instantly. Scripture responds with two revolutionary concepts: heavenly mindedness and delayed gratification.’ Waiting forces us to accept that we’re not in control. It humbles us in ways we need to be humbled. Consider the trapeze artist: for a split second, which must feel like an eternity, he or she is suspended in nothingness. They can’t go back, and it’s too soon to feel the grasp of the one who’ll catch them. They must wait in absolute trust. You may be at that same point in your life right now. You’ve let go of what God called you to let go of, but you can’t feel His hand catching you yet. Moses waited eighty years for a ministry that lasted forty years: two–thirds of his life was spent getting ready! Jesus spent thirty years preparing for a ministry that would last three–and–a–half years. From God’s perspective, your life isn’t measured by its length, but by its effectiveness and its impact for His Kingdom. So wait, and keep a good attitude while you’re doing it. God won’t disappoint you.</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 23:21–26:19, Mark 6:1–13, Ps 119:65–72, Prov 21:10–13</p><p>SATURDAY AUGUST 15</p><p>‘I waited patiently for the Lord to help me…’ Psalm 40:1 NLT</p><p>Wait (2)</p><p>The Psalmist said: ‘<i>I waited patiently for the Lord to help me, and He turned to me and heard my cry. He lifted me out of the pit of despair…He set my feet on solid ground and steadied me as I walked along. He has given me a new song to sing, a hymn of praise to our God. Many will see what He has done and be amazed</i>.’ (Psalm 40: NLT) Waiting means trusting that God knows what He’s doing, even when He doesn’t give you all the details. Perhaps you’re single and looking for someone to share your life with. Maybe there’s a relationship at your fingertips, but you know it wouldn’t be pleasing to God. It isn’t the right person, because he or she doesn’t share your values, goals, or commitment to Christ. Maybe they’re putting pressure on you to get involved sexually even though you’re not married. Sampling the product before you buy may be the world’s way, but you know it’s not God’s way. Still you’re tempted to think, ‘I’m tired of waiting. I’m going to reach for whatever satisfaction I can get and worry about the consequences later.’ Samson did that and ended up losing his sight, his strength, his reputation, his freedom and his life. Hold out for God’s best! Pray: ‘Lord, I don’t want to get involved in any relationship that I know would dishonour You, hurt me, and bring pain to the lives of others. You said the plans You have for me are good. So even though I sometimes feel no one understands how hard it is, I’ll trust in You and wait patiently.’</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Chr 26:20–29:30, Mark 6:14–29, Ps 119:73–80, Prov 21:14–16</p><p>SUNDAY AUGUST 16</p><p>‘…I will go…And if I perish, I perish.’ Esther 4:16 NIV</p><p>Give It Your All</p><p>Esther, a Jewish girl married to a pagan king, risked death to break with long–standing tradition, marched into her husband’s throne room, spoke her mind, and rescued her people from annihilation. One girl saved a nation because she was willing to put everything on the line. Are you feeling inadequate today? Are you thinking, ‘Someone else should be doing this job instead of me’? Then read these words by clergyman Edward Everett Hale: ‘I am only one; but still I am one. I can’t do everything; but still I can do something: and because I can’t do everything, I will not refuse to do the something I can do.’ How many people did it take to rescue the dying man on the Jericho road? One Good Samaritan. How many people did it take to save the whole known world from the consequences of a seven–year famine? One man, Joseph. John Maxwell writes: ‘God has put a dream inside you. It’s yours and no one else’s. It declares your uniqueness. It holds your potential. Only you can give birth to it. Only you can live it. Not to discover it, take responsibility for it and act upon it is to negatively affect yourself as well as all those who would benefit from your dream.’ Poet John Greenleaf Whittier wrote, ‘For all sad words of tongue and pen; the saddest are these, “It might have been.”’ In your twilight years, will you look back and feel you’ve spent your life struggling to fulfil other people’s expectations? Or know that you lived to the fullest by striving to fulfil your God–given dream? Think about it now, while there’s still time to change direction.</p><p>SoulFood: Jer 31:31–37, Heb 8:1–13</p><p>MONDAY AUGUST 17</p><p>‘Now faith is the substance of things hoped for…’ Hebrews 11:1 NKJV </p><p>‘Now’ Faith</p><p>When you’re in the middle of a crisis, what you really believe manifests itself in your words, attitude and actions. When Lazarus died and his sister Martha said, ‘<i>Lord, if You had been here, my brother would not have died</i>’ (John 11:21 NCV), she was voicing past–tense faith. When Jesus said, <i>‘[Lazarus] will…live again</i>’ (John 11:23 NCV) and she replied, ‘<i>I know that he will…live…in the resurrection…</i>’ (John 11:24 NCV), that was future–tense faith. And when she said, ‘…<i>Even now God will give You anything You ask</i>’ (John 11:22 NCV), she was demonstrating ‘now’ faith, which is present–tense. As believers, the Bible tells us not to ‘…<i>look at the things which are seen, but at the things which are not seen</i>…’ (2 Corinthians 4:18 NKJV) ‘Now’ faith stakes its claim on ‘<i>something…even if we do not see it.</i>’ (Hebrews 11:1 NCV) Paul says, ‘…<i>we walk by faith, not by sight</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 5:7 NKJV) Too often we base our feelings on what we see, instead of what God says in His Word. But as Jon Walker writes: ‘When we believe that reality is confined to what we see, we become trapped into thinking the only truth is what we see. We become prisoners of our own perceptions; we cease walking in faith… For those who walk by faith, appearances are never the ultimate reality… Reality extends beyond what you can see… the things we do not see are eternal [time and circumstance do not diminish or alter them] (2 Corinthians 4:18 NIV). Even though things may appear bad, God is working things out for our good (Romans 8:28). He knows how the story ends, so fix your eyes on the unseen and not on what you see.’</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 1–4, Mark 6:30–44, Ps 119:81–88, Prov 21:17–19</p><p>TUESDAY AUGUST 18</p><p>‘…God so loved the world…’ John 3:16 NKJV</p><p>Jesus Loves You Unconditionally</p><p>David said, ‘<i>Blessed is he whose transgression is forgiven, whose sin is covered</i>.’ (Psalm 32:1 NKJV) No matter how hard we worked, we could never pay off our sin debt. And thank God we don’t have to, because ‘<i>God so loved the world, that He gave His only begotten Son, that whosoever believes in Him should not perish, but has everlasting life</i>.’ Years ago a congregation decided to honour one of its retired pastors. He was ninety–two, and some people wondered why the church even asked the elderly man to speak. After a warm welcome and introduction, he rose from his chair and walked with great dignity and effort to the pulpit. Leaning on the podium to steady himself, without notes of any kind, he began to speak: ‘When your pastor invited me here, he asked me to talk about the greatest lesson I’ve learned in fifty–plus years of preaching. I’ve thought about it for a few days, and boiled it down to the one thing that has made the most difference in my life and sustained me through all my trials. The one thing I can rely on when tears, heartbreak, pain, fear and sorrow paralyse me… the one thing that always comforts me: Jesus loves me! This I know, for the Bible tells me so. Little ones to Him belong. They are weak but He is strong. Yes, Jesus loves me. Yes, Jesus loves me. Yes, Jesus loves me. The Bible tells me so.’ You could hear a pin drop as the old man shuffled back to his seat. It’s something the congregation never forgot. And it’s something you should never forget either—Jesus loves you unconditionally. That’s so today, tomorrow, and forever!</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 5–7, Mark 6:45–56, Ps 119:89–96, Prov 21:20–23</p><p>WEDNESDAY AUGUST 19</p><p>‘…God will generously provide all you need…’ 2 Corinthians 9:8 NLT</p><p>Get Rid of Your Scarcity Mentality</p><p>‘…<i>God shall supply all your need according to His riches in glory</i>.’ (Philippians 4:19 NKJV) Whose riches? God’s! And His ability to bless you is not limited by the job market, the stock market or the housing market. For forty years He fed His people in the wilderness with manna from Heaven. He sent ravens to deliver meat to Elijah during a famine. He fed over five thousand people with a boy’s lunch. Paul writes, ‘<i>God will generously provide all you need. Then you will always have everything you need and plenty left over to share with others…Yes, you will be enriched in every way</i>…’ (2 Corinthians 9:8, 11 NLT) The scarcity attitude is rooted in fear and shows distrust of the awesome power of God to supply all our needs according to His unlimited resources. It’s based upon the faulty assumption that if someone else has something, you can’t have it because there’s only one pie, and every slice that someone else gets means less is available for you. It makes you believe that the blessings of others come at your expense. It says, ‘You win, I lose.’ That’s no way to live the abundant life! Start today to reprogramme your thinking. Remind yourself that you’re not in competition with anybody, for anything, in any area of your life. Cling to the words of Jesus: ‘…<i>I have come that [you] may have life, and that [you] may have it more abundantly</i>.’ (John 10:10 NKJV) Pray: ‘Father, help me to reject all thoughts of scarcity. Show me how to help others achieve their goals by sharing my time, talents, treasure. In Jesus’ name, I pray. Amen.’</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 8–11, Mark 7:1–13, Ps 119:97–104, Prov 21:24–27</p><p>THURSDAY AUGUST 20</p><p>‘A prudent person foresees danger and takes precautions…’ Proverbs 27:12 NLT</p><p>Install Your ‘Cables’ Now</p><p>Half Dome is a granite peak that towers above the valley floor in Yosemite National Park. Your final climb is between steel cables bolted to the rock; they were designed as handholds to safeguard and help you reach the top. Columnist Mary Hunt writes: ‘The final ascent up the sheer granite surface…is by far the most challenging. Once you see the cables you experience terror like you’ve never known… and you’ve no choice but to finish the trip. At that moment you’re thankful for cables that become the guardrails you need to pull yourself to the top. The secret to [continuing] when you feel like quitting is to erect ‘cables’ in your life before you need them so that when you face difficult situations, the help you need to make it will be there to protect you from your own fears and self–defeating attitudes.’ Solomon says, ‘<i>A prudent person foresees danger and takes precautions. The simpleton goes blindly on and suffers the consequences</i>.’ Sooner or later you’ll face a mountain you can’t conquer alone. And if the ‘cables’ you need are in place, you’ll conquer it. What are they? (1) <i>God’s Word</i>. Jeremiah said, ‘<i>Your words…sustain me</i>…’ (Jeremiah 15:16 TLB) Get into God’s Word, and get God’s Word into you. That way, when trouble comes you’ll be able to handle it. It’ll ‘...<i>guide you when you walk…guard you when you sleep…speak to you when you are awake.</i>’ (Proverbs 6:22 NCV) (2) <i>A strong prayer life</i>. ‘…<i>The earnest (heartfelt, continued) prayer of a righteous man makes tremendous power available [dynamic in its working]…</i>’ (James 5:16 AMP) Time spent with God changes you; it makes you more like Jesus and strengthens you for what lies ahead.</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 12–15, Mark 7:14–23, Ps 119:105–112, Prov 21:28–31</p><p>FRIDAY AUGUST 21</p><p id="4012">‘...if...you lack wisdom, you should pray to God, who will give it to you; because God gives generously and graciously to all.’ (James 1:5 GNT) </p><p>Are You Trying To Make An Important Decision?</p><p>If you are, here are some suggestions to help you. (1) <i>Don’t ask God to bless YOUR plans</i>, instead ask for HIS wisdom and direction! And remember, God will never tell you to do anything that doesn’t line up with what He’s already told you in His Word (Isaiah 8:20). (2) <i>Make sure your goal is to glorify God</i>. Sometimes that’s hard to know, for the worst pride often masquerades behind feigned humility. The human body is amazing—just pat a man on the back and so often his head begins to swell. But God opposes pride. (James 4:6) (3) <i>Use your brain</i>. God’s guidance transcends human reasoning, but it doesn’t exclude it. When God saves you, He doesn’t remove your mind, He renews it. (Romans 12:2) So pray, then put it to work. (4) <i>Seasons aren’t meant to be ignored</i>. If it isn’t God’s timing, wait! In the right season, the plan will be clear, the people you need will show up and the funds will be provided (Ecclesiastes 3:1). God has promised it, so trust Him! (5) <i>Seek trustworthy counsel</i>. Beware of those who patronise you for selfish reasons. Listen to those who value what you value and have been where you want to go (Proverbs 27:17). (6) <i>Never act without the facts</i>, but never limit God to them. When knowledge won’t take you another step, faith will carry you through, for that’s what connects you to the power of God. Now listen again ‘...if...you lack wisdom, you should pray to God, who will give it to you; because God gives generously and graciously to all.’ (James 1:5 GNT) </p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 16–18, Mark 7:24–37, Ps 119:113–120, Prov 22:1–3</p><p>SATURDAY AUGUST 22</p><p>‘…To turn the hearts of the fathers back to the children…’ Luke 1:17 NAS</p><p>Dad, Equip Your Kids for the Real World! (1)</p><p>Research shows the results of the ‘dad deficit’. Too many children today are growing up without a father’s input. And as a result they end up making poor life, relationship and marriage choices. So how does a dad equip his kids for life in the real world?</p><p>(1) <i>Know what they’re up to</i>. Get to know what makes them tick. Ask what subjects they enjoy in school, and which ones they’re struggling with. Learn who their friends are; who they spend time with at break and after school. Try to listen and learn. Take them out occasionally for breakfast or a hamburger; they’ll feel like royalty spending one–to–one time with Dad! (2<i>) Teach them to stand tall</i>. A tragedy of their young world is the increasing suicide rate because of playground bullying. Teach your children to stand up for themselves. Teach them respect, and how to protect themselves by speaking up appropriately in class when they’re unclear about the lesson, or to courageously say what they believe. Teach them assertiveness in confronting unfair treatment. Kids who become ‘punch bags’ are set up to be victimised! (3) <i>Give them an example</i>. However accomplished your ‘preaching’ skills may be, you need to be ‘walking the walk’ in front of your children. You can tell them it’s important to be healthy and active, but if you’re a couch potato inhaling bags of chips and watching endless footy matches, they’re not convinced. Set an example by getting fit, pursuing a healthy lifestyle, activities and interests, and watch them think how ‘cool’ it is to be like Dad!</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 19–21, Mark 8:1–13, Ps 119:121–128, Prov 22:4–7</p><p>SUNDAY AUGUST 23</p><p>‘…I am your spiritual father through the Gospel; that is why I implore you to follow [my] footsteps.’ 1 Corinthians 4:15 PHPS</p><p>Dad, Equip Your Kids for the Real World! (2)</p><p>Dad, do these three things for your kids: (1) <i>Alert them to the dangers of having a sense of entitlement</i>. Yes, they need parents who express unconditional love for them. But some of us think our kids can do no wrong—even when they do! Consequently they grow up having unrealistic expectations and a distorted view of how life works. Everybody gets a scorecard in life, and it records both our wins and our losses. Let your kids know that we all make mistakes. Failing to recognise that just makes them self–deceived and sets them up for heartache. Children learn from failure how to deal with disappointment; it prepares them for later life when things don’t go their way. (2) <i>Teach them the truth about death—yours and theirs</i>. The Bible says, ‘…<i>it is appointed unto men once to die</i>…’ (Hebrews 9:27 KJV) Let them know that death is universally ordained because of the sin of humanity. Tell them that life, however long, is a gift to be maximised, and Heaven is a family reunion not to be missed. The death of a friend or loved one can be an opportunity to diminish their fears and equip them to handle loss, grief and recovery. (3) <i>Show them why you married their mother</i>. It’s the most formative relationship in their early lives; one that will influence who they ultimately become, their choice of a partner, and their future happiness. When they see you loving their mother, treating her like a queen, and giving her consideration and honour, they’ll admire, appreciate, and emulate their awesome dad!</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 17:8–16, 2 Cor 1:3–7 </p><p>MONDAY AUGUST 24</p><p>‘…We ought to obey God rather than men.’ Acts 5:29 KJV</p><p>Set Yourself Free from People Pleasing</p><p>Too often our actions are dictated by a misguided need to please others. We care so much about what they think that with every step we take we look over our shoulder to see whether they’re smiling or frowning. Understand this: if you’re always looking for people’s approval, you’re not looking where you’re going and eventually you’ll hit a wall or trip over your own two feet. The Bible says, ‘…<i>We ought to obey God rather than men</i>.’ What do you think will happen if you open your mouth and stand up for yourself? The truth is that people who don’t respect your rights and honour your wishes are not worth your time or effort. Nor are they worthy of a long drawn–out discussion; just say goodbye! (We’re not talking about your marriage or children.) When the land became too small for the flocks of Abraham and Lot to graze together, strife broke out. Abraham loved his nephew Lot, but he realised he could no longer live in this situation. So he said, ‘…<i>Please separate from me. If you take the left, then I will go to the right; or, if you go to the right, then I will go to the left</i>.’ (Genesis 13:9 NKJV) How does their story end? Lot chose the best grazing land close to Sodom, and, as a result, everything he worked for went up in smoke. But Abraham, who always sought to please God, ended up not only being blessed himself, but being a blessing to the nations of the world. So the word for you today is—God wants to set you free from people pleasing.</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 22–24, Mark 8:14–26, Ps 119:129–136, Prov 22:8–10</p><p>TUESDAY AUGUST 25</p><p>‘Husbands, love your wives, as Christ loved the church…’ Ephesians 5:25 ESV</p><p>Love Works When Nothing Else Will</p><p>After many years of marriage, John decided to divorce his wife. The reasons he gave his counsellor were: ‘She’s not attractive, she’s not interesting, she’s overweight, and she’s a poor housekeeper.’ So the counsellor gave him this suggestion: ‘Starting today, I want you to go home and treat your wife like a goddess. Start doing everything in your power to please her. Listen intently when she talks about her problems. Help around the house, and take her out to dinner at the weekend. I want you to literally pretend that she’s a goddess. Then after two months of this wonderful new behaviour, pack your bags and leave. That should get her attention!’ John agreed it was a great idea, and decided to implement it. He took his wife away on romantic weekends and read poetry to her every night. After two months the counsellor called and asked, ‘John, did you file for divorce? Are you looking forward to being a bachelor again?’ John replied, ‘Are you kidding? I’m married to a goddess. I’ve never been happier in my life. I’d never leave my wife in a million years. In fact, I’m discovering new, wonderful things about her every single day. Divorce? Not on your life!’ The Bible says, ‘…<i>A man reaps what he sows</i>.’ (Galatians 6:7 NIV) And when John changed his strategy and started sowing seeds of love, he reaped a marriage he never dreamed possible. Do you think this same strategy might possibly work for you? What’ve you got to lose? Give it a try and see what happens. Chances are you and your spouse will love the results.</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 25–28, Mark 8:27–38, Ps 119:137–144, Prov 22:11–13</p><p>WEDNESDAY AUGUST 26</p><p>‘…I am…wonderfully made…’ Psalm 139:14 NIV</p><p>Your Eyes: A Divine Masterpiece</p><p>Evolution says that, where there’s a want, nature will provide what’s needed. Really? In <i>Natural Theology</i>, Dr. William Paley writes: ‘To keep the eye moist and clean—which qualities are necessary to its brightness and its use—a wash is constantly supplied by a secretion for the purpose; and the superfluous brine is conveyed to the nose through a perforation in the bone as large as a goose quill. When the fluid has entered the nose, it spreads itself upon the inside of the nostril and is evaporated by the current of warm air which in the course of respiration is continually passing over it… It’s easily perceived that the eye must want moisture; but could the “want” of the eye generate the gland which produces the tear, or bore the hole by which it’s discharged—a hole through bone? Let the evolutionist tell us who bored the hole… and laid a water pipe through it for the dispersion of tears.’ When it encounters darkness, your eye’s ability to see increases one hundred thousand times. The finest camera ever made doesn’t even come close! And what’s more, your eye will find the object it wants to see, and focus on it automatically by elongating or compressing itself. Both eyes moving in tandem must adopt different angles in order to fix themselves on what’s to be seen. Evolution tells us when the eye got ready to create itself, it had forethought for its own protection and built a bony ridge of the brow, which provided a nose on which to position the glasses many of us need. Then it provided a shutter to protect itself from foreign objects. Perhaps it takes more faith to believe in evolution than creation! What do you think?</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 29–31, Mark 9:1–13, Ps 119:145–160, Prov 22:14–16</p><p>THURSDAY AUGUST 27</p><p>‘…Pour out your heart before Him…’ Psalm 62:8 NAS</p><p>Pray, and Keep Praying!</p><p>More than anything else in life, Hannah wanted a son. And as the years passed she wrestled with disappointment and despair. ‘…<i>and [Hannah] was in distress of soul, praying to the Lord</i>.’ (1 Samuel 1:10 AMP) However, she did two things that worked—and they’ll work for you, too! (1) <i>Instead of turning away from God, she turned to Him</i>. Instead of praying less, she prayed more. She knew that while her husband couldn’t give her a child, God could. She may not have been happy with God’s timing, but she never doubted His goodness. Unfortunately, one of the things we’re tempted to do when things fall apart is to avoid God’s presence. That’s a mistake, because He’s the one you need most! Yes, it’s hard to pray when your heart is breaking. But unless you’ve prayed with a broken heart and a deep sense of your need, you’ve never really poured out your heart before God, or learned what the Bible truly means by prayer. (2) <i>She didn’t just think about what she wanted, she also thought about what God wanted</i>. ‘…<i>she made a vow, saying, “Lord Almighty, if You will…not forget Your servant but give her a son, then I will give him to the Lord for all the days of his life…”</i>’ (1 Samuel 1:11 NIV) And shortly after that Samuel was conceived. When you’re willing to make a promise to God that He can hold you to (which is what a vow is), you’re getting serious about prayer. And that’s when God will get serious about your prayer as well! So, ‘<i>pour out your heart before Him</i>.’</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 32–34, Mark 9:14–29, Ps 119:161–168, Prov 22:17–19</p><p>FRIDAY AUGUST 28</p><p>‘…He…guided them in the wilderness like a flock.’ Psalm 78:52 NKJV</p><p>What You Need in the Wilderness (1)</p><p>Charles E. Fuller, one of the first radio Bible teachers, started his daily broadcast with the song, ‘My Lord knows the way through the wilderness; all I have to do is follow.’ To get them from Egypt to Canaan, God took His people through the wilderness—and, spiritually speaking, you’ll have to go through it, too! You can have a wilderness experience anywhere. At a graveside, in a cancer ward, in a divorce court, in an unemployment queue, or when you lose your house. But the wilderness can also be a place of miracles. So for the next few days, let’s look at some things you need to survive in the wilderness. <i>Direction!</i> Without it you end up going round in circles. Notice how God led Israel. He ‘<i>went before them by day in a pillar of a cloud…and by night in a pillar of fire, to give them light…He took not away the pillar of the cloud…nor the pillar of fire…from before the people</i>.’ (Exodus 13:21–22 NKJV) God basically told Moses: ‘Whenever the pillar moves, you move. And when the pillar stops, you stop.’ But what do you do at night when it’s pitch black? There are no candles or oil lamps, and you risk sharing your bed with a scorpion or stepping on a snake on your way to the bathroom. Don’t worry; God’s got you covered! The wilderness isn’t alien territory to Him. The Psalmist said, ‘<i>Your Word is a lamp to my feet and a light to my path</i>.’ (Psalm 119:105 NKJV) For every contingency, condition and circumstance you face, your Bible will guide you, protect you, and keep you safe. So stop worrying and start reading it every day.</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Chr 35–36, 2 Jn, Mark 9:30–37, Ps 119:169–176, Prov 22:20–23</p><p>SATURDAY AUGUST 29</p><p>‘…He led them on safely, so that they did not fear…’ Psalm 78:53 NKJV</p><p>What You Need in the Wilderness (2)</p><p>You can be in the wilderness and still be in the centre of God’s will. ‘…<i>He made His own people go forth like sheep, and guided them in the wilderness like a flock… He led them on safely, so…they did not fear</i>…’ (Psalm 78:52–53 NKJV) In the wilderness you get to know God in a way you never knew Him before. So, what else did Israel need to survive in the wilderness? Food! Someone calculated it would have taken about twenty–six wagonloads of food to feed that many Israelites every day. The problem is there were no trains and no tracks! But they had something much better—God! For forty years He delivered manna, ‘the perfect food’, to the doors of their tents. The supply was according to each family’s individual need—and God never missed a day. So if the economy has you feeling anxious and wondering whether or not God can take care of you—this is the word for you today! God may not give you everything you want, but He will give you everything you need. The God we serve doesn’t suffer from lack or limitation! The Psalmist said, ‘<i>I have been young, and now am old; yet I have not seen the righteous forsaken, nor his descendants begging for bread</i>.’ (Psalm 37:25 NKJV) The old country preacher got it right when he said, ‘Where He leads me I will follow; what He feeds me I will swallow.’ Think of it: for forty years Israel never missed a meal or went without. And their God is your God, so put your trust in Him today and stop worrying!</p><p>SoulFood: 3 Jn, Jude, Mark 9:38–50, Ps 84, Prov 22:24–26 </p><p>SUNDAY AUGUST 30</p><p>‘…He brought you water out of hard rock.’ Deuteronomy 8:15 NIV</p><p>What You Need in the Wilderness (3) </p><p>What else do you need in the wilderness? <i>Water!</i> You can live without food for about forty days, but without water you’ll die much faster. It’s the same in the spiritual realm; you can get by in life without a lot of things, but you won’t make it without God. In the wilderness God was teaching His people a lesson He wanted them to remember when they arrived in the Promised Land: ‘<i>Otherwise, when you eat and are satisfied, when you build fine houses and settle down, and when your herds and flocks grow large and your silver and gold increase and all you have is multiplied, then your heart will become proud and you will forget the Lord…Who brought you out of…slavery. He led you through the vast and dreadful wilderness, that thirsty and waterless land, with its venomous snakes and scorpions. He brought you water out of hard rock. He gave you manna to eat in the wilderness, something your ancestors had never known, to humble and to test you so that in the end it might go well with you</i>.’ (Deuteronomy 8:12–16 NIV) Note the words ‘<i>that it might go well with you</i>’. In spite of what you’re going through today, God has great blessings in store for you. But in order to handle them properly you must learn humility, develop a heart of gratitude, and never forget that He alone is the source of every good thing you’ll ever have. Then God added this P.S.: ‘<i>If you ever forget…you will surely be destroyed</i>.’ (Deuteronomy 8:19 NIV) That’s how serious He is about making sure you depend on Him each day.</p><p>SoulFood: Gen 11:1–9, Phil 2:1–11</p><p>MONDAY AUGUST 31</p><p>‘…And there was none feeble among His tribes.’ Psalm 105:37 NKJV</p><p>What You Need in the Wilderness (4) </p><p>Notice something else Israel enjoyed in the wilderness: <i>divine health</i>. Think of the health issues you’d expect among two million people walking through endless desert with no doctor or hospital in sight. Yet from the youngest to the oldest, ‘<i>He…brought them out…and there was none feeble among His tribes</i>.’ That’s because they lived on a diet provided by God Himself. Their troubles began when they complained and wanted to go back to the food they ate as slaves in Egypt. Hello! There’s an important lesson here for those who live on fast foods that promote ailments like heart disease, cancer and diabetes. Imagine pouring five pounds of sugar into the fuel tank of your car and complaining that it won’t run properly. Now, when health problems run in your family, or economic circumstances force you to eat less than ideal food, God understands and you can go to Him with confidence, believing, ‘…<i>the prayer of faith will save the sick, and the Lord will raise him up</i>…’ (James 5:15 NKJV) But when the choice is between exercising wisdom in order to have good health or exercising faith in order to be healed, your choice is clear. When Israel entered the Promised Land, God told them, ‘…<i>serve the Lord…and He will bless your bread and your water…take sickness away from the midst of you…[and] fulfil the number of your days</i>.’ (Exodus 23:25–26 NKJV) But don’t forget, He also gave them dietary laws to live by that set them apart from the surrounding nations. Question: How many of us fail to ‘<i>fulfil the number of [our] days</i>’ and the assignment God gives us, because we refuse to exercise wisdom and discipline when it comes to our diet? Think about it! </p><p>SoulFood: Josh 1–4, Mark 10:1–12, Ps 103:1–12, Prov 22:27–29</p><p>TUESDAY SEPTEMBER 1</p><p>‘Acquaint now yourself with Him, and be at peace…’ Job 22:21 NKJV</p><p>What You Need in the Wilderness (5)</p><p>When you find yourself in the wilderness, what’s the one thing you need more than anything else? <i>God!</i> That’s why the Lord told Moses to build the tabernacle and He used it as a teaching tool to show His people that: (1) <i>He wants to meet with us regularly</i>. The word ‘tabernacle’ means ‘tent of meeting’. God wants you to spend time with Him. He wants you to get to know Him. Because when you do, you’ll worry less and trust Him more. The Bible says, ‘<i>Acquaint now yourself with Him, and be at peace…</i>’ It’s important to listen to God’s Word being taught, to meet with other believers, and be encouraged by their testimonies. But at some point you’ve got to stop trading in second–hand information and get ‘up close and personal’ with God. James writes, ‘<i>Draw near to God and He will draw near to you…</i>’ (James 4:8 NKJV) (2) <i>God wants to be at the centre of our lives</i>. When Israel set up camp each night, the twelve tribes pitched their tents in formation surrounding the tabernacle, where God’s presence dwelt. Every man, woman, boy and girl could stand in the door of their tent and see God in their midst. Could the message be clearer? When your deepest affections and greatest ambitions are centred around Christ, your life will take an upward swing. ‘…<i>delight yourself in the Lord and He will give you the desires of your heart</i>.’ (Psalm 37:4 NIV) The formula for thriving in the wilderness is: centre your life on Christ and soak yourself in His Word!</p><p>SoulFood: Josh 5:1–8:29, Mark 10:13–22, Ps 103:13–22, Prov 23:1–3</p><p>WEDNESDAY SEPTEMBER 2</p><p>‘…You are to receive the offering for Me from everyone whose heart prompts them to give.’ Exodus 25:2 NIV </p><p>What You Need in the Wilderness (6)</p><p>God’s people already possessed everything necessary to build the tabernacle. So Moses went to God for the plan, and to the people for the resources. And that’s still how it works! Pastor, don’t come up with a plan of your own, or one you got from somebody else, and then ask God to underwrite it. Ask God for His plan, because that’s the only one He will bless. And don’t feel intimidated about going to the people and asking them to give. Perhaps you’re reluctant to talk about finances because some people in church complain and say, ‘All the pastor ever talks about is money.’ Of course, if they’re right, you need to get back into balance. But generally speaking, people need clear biblical teaching on giving; to see it as a privilege and an opportunity to go into partnership with God. Over and over the Bible refers to giving as ‘sowing’. And when you sow, you should expect to reap. The law of giving is like the law of gravity; it never fails. God said, ‘<i>As long as the earth endures, seedtime and harvest…will never cease.</i>’ (Genesis 8:22 NIV) Observe how it works: first you sow your seed, then there’s a time of waiting, and finally you get to reap. Money can be a touchy subject; it can stir up resistance and resentment. But God promised that when you sow generously, you will reap generously: ‘...<i>whoever sows sparingly will also reap sparingly, and whoever sows bountifully will also reap bountifully... for God loves a cheerful giver</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 9:6–7 ESV) Now, either God told the truth or He didn’t. And you need to find out whether or not it’s true. The only way to do that is to try it and see for yourself.</p><p>SoulFood: Josh 8:30–10:43, Mark 10:23–34, Ps 111, Prov 23:4–6</p><p>THURSDAY SEPTEMBER 3</p><p>‘…Remember the Lord your God…’ Deuteronomy 8:18 NIV</p><p>Today, Let’s Remember That!</p><p>On March 3, 1863, anguished by the ravages of civil war, Abraham Lincoln declared a Proclamation Appointing a National Fast Day: ‘Whereas it is the duty of nations as well as of men to own their dependence upon the overruling power of God, to confess their sins and transgressions, in humble sorrow, yet with assured hope that genuine repentance will lead to mercy and pardon; and to recognise the sublime truth announced in the Holy Scriptures and proven by all history, that those nations only are blessed whose God is the Lord… We have been the recipients of the choicest bounties of Heaven. We have been preserved these many years in peace and prosperity; we have grown in numbers, wealth and power as no other nation has ever grown. But we have forgotten God. We have forgotten the gracious hand which preserved us in peace, and multiplied and enriched and strengthened us; and we have vainly imagined, in the deceitfulness of our hearts, that all these blessings were produced by some superior wisdom and virtue of our own. Intoxicated with unbroken success, we have become too self–sufficient to feel the necessity of redeeming and preserving grace, too proud to pray to the God that made us! It behooves us then to humble ourselves before the offended Power, to confess our national sins, and to pray for clemency and forgiveness.’ God warned Israel: ‘<i>When…your silver and your gold are multiplied, and all that you have is multiplied… you shall remember the Lord your God, for it is He who gives you power to get wealth, that He may establish His covenant…</i>’ (Deuteronomy 8:13, 18 NKJV) Today, let’s remember that!</p><p>SoulFood: Josh 11–13, Mark 10:35–52, Ps 142, Prov 23:7–9</p><p>FRIDAY SEPTEMBER 4</p><p>‘He restores my soul…’ Psalm 23:3 NKJV</p><p>Practise Soul Care</p><p>David said, ‘<i>The Lord is my shepherd; I shall not want. He makes me to lie down in green pastures; He leads me beside the still waters. He restores my soul…</i>’ (Psalm 23:1–3 NKJV) Today car engines are computerised. A light on your dashboard will let you know something’s wrong and that it’s time for a checkup. Your soul will do that too. But you’ve got to pay attention to the signals! Don’t wait until you have a spiritual, moral, emotional or relational breakdown before you stop and pay attention. When your soul’s thirst is not quenched and its needs are not met, it will seek relief some other way, often a way that will hurt you. You must know when to say ‘when’. Most of us don’t take breaks that enable us to ‘<i>restore our souls</i>’. We’re ensnared by guilt, as if stopping would somehow be irresponsible. Or we fear losing ground because we took a minute for ourselves. One of the hardest things in life to achieve is not success, but a sense of balance. So in all your goal–setting and ‘go–getting’, don’t forget your soul. Even God rested (Genesis 2:2). And if He did, then you need to also. The power of rest is that it allows you to enjoy the journey of life and not just the destination. Indeed, if you don’t learn to walk in the park by choice, you may end up in the hospital by necessity. When God ‘<i>makes you lie down in green pastures</i>’, enjoy them. When He ‘<i>leads you beside the still waters</i>’, it’s to refresh and restore you. So practise soul care!</p><p>SoulFood: Josh 14–15, Mark 11:1–11, Ps 20, Prov 23:10–12</p><p>SATURDAY SEPTEMBER 5</p><p>‘…If someone slaps you on the right cheek, offer the other cheek also.’ Matthew 5:39 NLT</p><p>Turn the Other Cheek</p><p>There are two ways you can respond to negative criticism. If there’s truth in it, humbly accept it and grow through it. If not, practise what Jesus taught: ‘<i>You have heard the law that says the punishment must match the injury: “An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth.” But I say…If someone slaps you on the right cheek, offer the other cheek also</i>.’ (Matthew 5:38–39 NLT) Sometimes a person’s criticism may actually have nothing to do with you at all; they simply feel cheated by life. And rather than take control of their heart’s dreams, they go around trying to squelch other people’s dreams in an attempt to drag them down to their own level of despair. And while it’s tempting to want to retaliate and point out their weaknesses and failures, that’s not the example Jesus set for you. Nor is it the high road you are called to take. ‘<i>Never pay back evil with more evil. Do things in such a way that everyone can see you are honourable. Do all that you can to live in peace with everyone</i>.’ (Romans 12:17–18 NLT) What does it mean to turn the other cheek? It means don’t let your critics get under your skin. Simply listen to them, thank them, and take their criticism with a grain of salt. Save your time and energies for those you trust, those who love you enough to tell you the truth even when it hurts. Someone has said, ‘You owe nothing to a critic!’ Actually, you do. Jesus said, ‘…<i>Pray for those who persecute you!</i>’ (Matthew 5:44 NLT)</p><p>SoulFood: Josh 16:1–19:23, Mark 11:12–26, Ps 112, Prov 23:13–15</p><p>SUNDAY SEPTEMBER 6</p><p>‘…the Spirit pleads for us…in harmony with God’s own will.’ Romans 8:27 NLT</p><p>Different Ways to Pray (1)</p><p>Someone who’s better at prayer than you are is already at work on your behalf. ‘...<i>the Holy Spirit helps us in our weakness. For example, we don’t know what God wants us to pray for. But the Holy Spirit prays for us... [and] pleads for us believers in harmony with God’s own will</i>.’ (Romans 8:26–27 NLT) Notice, the Holy Spirit ‘<i>prays for u</i>s’. Sometimes we’ve a hard time being ‘fully present’ in prayer. We all know what it’s like to be with another person when their mind is a million miles away. What’s the answer? Try jotting down what goes on while you’re praying. The two most common hindrances to praying successfully are: (a) <i>your mind gets easily distracted by other thoughts</i>; (b) <i>you get tired</i>. When author John Ortberg shared these two frustrations with a friend, he suggested that John go outside alone and simply invite Jesus to come along with him. Ortberg writes: ‘The next day I went to the ocean, took off my shoes, started to run and invited Jesus to come along. I found the strangest thing. When I thought I was supposed to be talking to Him, I found it effortful and difficult. Now that all I had to do was invite Him, I couldn’t stop thinking about Him. My mind kept reflecting on His being with me. I found myself wanting to point out the pelicans and the waves to Him. People and concerns would pop into my mind, and I would find myself telling Jesus about them. Everything changed.’ So, invite Jesus to come along with you today and share each thing you do with Him.</p><p>SoulFood (Father’s Day): Dan 6:1–24, Acts 12:1–19</p><p>MONDAY SEPTEMBER 7</p><p>‘Hezekiah received the letter…and spread it out before the Lord.’ Isaiah 37:14 NIV</p><p>Different Ways to Pray (2)</p><p>Hezekiah, King of Israel, received a threatening letter from a much more powerful king—the King of Assyria. The Assyrian potentate demanded unconditional surrender, and told Hezekiah not to trust in God. The letter was graphic, warning that resistance meant the Israelites would have to ‘<i>eat their own excrement and drink their own urine</i>’ before they died (2 Kings 18:27 NIV). So Hezekiah went to the temple ‘<i>and spread it out before the Lord.</i>’ Then he prayed: ‘…<i>God of Israel, enthroned between the cherubim, You alone are God over all the kingdoms of the earth. You have made Heaven and earth. Give ear, O Lord, and hear; open Your eyes, O Lord, and see</i>…’ (Isaiah 37:16–17 NIV) Hezekiah basically said, ‘Lord, would you read this, then do something about it!’ And God did. Indeed, what He did was spectacular. ‘<i>Then the angel of the Lord went out and put to death a hundred and eighty–five thousand in the Assyrian camp. When the people got up the next morning—there were all the dead bodies!</i>’ (Isaiah 37:36 NIV) So, what piece of paper would you like to spread out before the Lord? A financial statement that’s overwhelming? A divorce decree? A medical diagnosis? An angry email? Any piece of paper that causes you stress can be an invitation to prayer, and a candidate to be spread out before the Lord. If it’s important to you, it’s important to Him. You say, ‘I’ve never done anything like that before.’ Try it. Give it to God, trust Him, and watch how He works things out for you.</p><p>SoulFood: Josh 19:24–21:45, Mark 11:27–33, Ps 27, Prov 23:16–18</p><p>TUESDAY SEPTEMBER 8</p><p>‘I lay prostrate before the Lord…’ Deuteronomy 9:25 NIV</p><p>Different Ways to Pray (3)</p><p>Find a prayer style that works for you. In Scripture people pray as they stand, kneel, lie on the ground, sit, stretch out their hands, lift their faces toward the sky, or bow them toward the earth. Just find the method that works best for you, and use it. Some people pray better when they are moving. If you’re one of them, take a walk, go for a drive, or run. You are free to use your body and posture to help you turn your mind and heart towards God. When you’re acknowledging your sins, you may find it helpful to have your head bowed and to kneel; it’ll help you to remember and experience the humility of the moment. In worship, you may want to turn your face towards the sky. In asking for guidance, you may find it helpful to turn your palms upwards as a way of expressing with your body: ‘Lord, whatever You want.’ When praying for someone, say at a restaurant, you may want to look that person right in the eye while talking to God and say, ‘Father, I’m so grateful for this person. You know what they need. Give them what is required by their heart.’ When you’re praising God, put on a worship CD and sing along. The point is you should approach God with the joy, excitement and simplicity with which a child runs into the arms of a loving parent. Just as you don’t have anyone else’s fingerprints, you don’t have anyone else’s temperament. So just approach God in a way that’s natural, spontaneous and comfortable for you.</p><p>SoulFood: Josh 22–24, Mark 12:1–12, Ps 78:1–8, Prov 23:19–21</p><p>WEDNESDAY SEPTEMBER 9</p><p>‘He will call upon Me, and I will answer him…’ Psalm 91:15 NIV</p><p>Different Ways to Pray (4)</p><p>When we try to spend an extended period of time in prayer, our minds tend to wander. When that happens, is God upset with us? No, when your mind wanders—God’s Spirit is still with you. Sometimes your wandering thoughts can actually guide you into prayer. Jon Ortberg writes: ‘I begin praying, and then I imagine myself being wildly successful at something. Or I replay a conversation with a person I’m upset with. Or I try to figure out how to solve a problem I’m worried about. I used to think of those kinds of thoughts as obstacles to prayer, but I’ve come to think of them as prayers waiting to be offered. Maybe the reason they pop into my mind isn’t simply my short attention span, but rather what my mind is really concerned about. So instead of trying to suppress these thoughts, it’s better to begin to talk to God about them. And just like that, I’m back in the flow of prayer. Indeed, we are free to pray in ways that will best help us live in the joyful awareness of God’s presence.’ Obviously, things like getting your hair done or your car fixed are distractions. When these arise, just write them down and say, ‘I’ll get to that later,’ then get back to prayer. Developing a rich and rewarding prayer life isn’t something you accomplish overnight; you have to work at it. But the rewards are more than worth the effort. You’re not unique; everybody battles distractions in prayer. Those who succeed are those who learn to deal with the distractions.</p><p>SoulFood: Col 1–2, Mark 12:13–27, Ps 78:9–16, Prov 23:22–25</p><p>THURSDAY SEPTEMBER 10</p><p>‘…I was afraid and went out and hid your talent in the ground…’ Matthew 25:25 NIV</p><p>Are You Burying Your Talent?</p><p>One of the most familiar parables Jesus told illustrates how things work in God’s Kingdom: ‘<i>Then he who had received one talent came. “Master,” he said, “…I was afraid and went out and hid your talent in the ground.”…His master replied, “You wicked, lazy servant!… You should have put my money on deposit with the bankers, so that when I returned I would have received it back with interest. Take the talent from him and give it to the one who has the ten talents. For everyone who has will be given more, and he will have an abundance. Whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken from him …throw that worthless servant outside.”</i>’ (Matthew 25:24–29 NIV) Can you imagine going to work next Friday and watching your boss hand your pay packet to someone else, while you stand there? That’s exactly what’s going on in this story. It’s a picture of what will happen at the judgment seat of Christ—and you’ll be there to see it. Why did the Lord come down so hard on this guy? Because he buried his talent. And why did he bury it? Because he ‘was afraid’. Afraid of what? (a) Afraid the talent God had given him wasn’t equal to the task. (b) Afraid to take a risk in case he failed. (c) Afraid he didn’t have the talents others had, therefore his didn’t count. Just like there are degrees of punishment at the Last Judgment (Matthew 11:21–24; James 3:1; Matthew 18:6), there will be degrees of reward in Heaven. And how you steward your talent now determines what your reward will be then. </p><p>SoulFood: Col 3–4, Philemon, Mark 12:28–44, Ps 78:17–31, Prov 23:26–28</p><p>FRIDAY SEPTEMBER 11</p><p>‘…God is love. Whoever lives in love lives in God, and God in them.’ 1 John 4:16 NIV</p><p>The Power of Love</p><p>When Dr E Stanley Jones preached a sermon on love in India, a church leader told him how a layman, whom he loved and had helped, was making trouble and threatening to split the church. The frustrated clergyman asked Dr Jones what to do because, in this case, love didn’t seem to be working. ‘Increase the dosage!’ retorted Jones. Our self–centred nature would have us believe that happiness comes when we get what we want and all of our needs are met. Yet, when we do get a better job, or a bigger house, or a bit of fame, we find ourselves empty because these things don’t bring us lasting joy and fulfilment. They actually whet our appetite for more—and around and around it goes. Peter Gillquist said, ‘Every time we have a chance in any way to flesh out the love of God to others, our joy cycle gets fulfilled all over again.’ Francis of Assisi may have expressed it best in his famous prayer: ‘Lord, make me an instrument of Your peace. Where there is hatred let me sow love; where there is injury, pardon; where there is doubt, faith; where there is despair, hope; where there is darkness, light; and where there is sadness, joy. Oh Divine Master, grant that I may not so much seek to be consoled as to console; to be understood as to understand; to be loved as to love. For it is in giving that we receive; it is in pardoning that we are pardoned; and it is in dying that we are born to eternal life.’ </p><p>SoulFood: Neh 1–4, Mark 13:1–11, Ps 78:32–39, Prov 23:29–35</p><p>SATURDAY SEPTEMBER 12</p><p>‘Where there is no counsel, the people fall…’ Proverbs 11:14 NKJV</p><p>Can You Take Advice?</p><p>The only thing that’s worse than making a mistake is concealing it and allowing pride to lock us in to it. Why do we do that? Insecurity! Low self–esteem! We’re all prone to being defensive from time to time. But if you find that this has become a pattern in your life, you must do something about it. So: (1) <i>Try to listen to yourself as you speak</i>; become aware of your tendency to defend and justify your actions. (2) <i>Guard against defensive body language</i>. For example, crossing your arms when someone is offering their opinion could be your subconscious way of saying, ‘I’m closed to what you’re saying.’ (3) <i>Counter the anxiety that comes with feeling attacked</i>, by breathing deeply and silently praying, ‘Lord, I receive Your strength now.’ Combining this physical and spiritual act will help to minimise your emotional response. (4) <i>If there is a genuine and credible justification for your action, state it in a calm, unemotional manner.</i> And if you are really brave, ask a trusted friend or co–worker if you are being defensive. Then refuse to become defensive if the response is, ‘Yes!’ (5) <i>Don’t attack your attacker</i>. Simply ask them what they would have done in the situation under discussion. Then thank them for sharing their insights. (6) <i>If you are guilty of a bad decision or wrong behaviour, try admitting it before it comes to light</i>. A simple ‘I made a mistake’ will give you credibility, preserve your integrity, and not allow your mistake to redefine who you are in the eyes of others. It may even increase their level of trust in you.</p><p>SoulFood: Neh 5–7, Mark 13:12–23, Ps 78:40–55, Prov 24:1–4</p><p>SUNDAY SEPTEMBER 13</p><p>‘…He will see the blood…and…not permit the destroyer to enter your houses…’ Exodus 12:23 NIV </p><p>Divine Protection</p><p>When the angel of death visited Egypt, only those whose doorposts were painted with lamb’s blood were protected from ‘<i>the destroyer</i>’. And the blood of Jesus [the Lamb of God] is still your best protection from the enemy who ‘…<i>prowls around like a roaring lion, looking for someone to devour</i>.’ (1 Peter 5:8 NLT) His atoning death on the cross to secure forgiveness of our sins. (Ephesians 2:12–16) Christians have also been sealed with the Spirit of God (Ephesians 1:13), and our salvation is assured by the Lord (Romans 8:38–39). So when Satan confronts us he knows he cannot ultimately succeed... but he still wants to try and make us stumble. Generally speaking, he’s looking for an ‘easy mark’. Just like a thief who cases your house for a hole in your security, he’ll be on the lookout for a weakness in your life. But if you <i>‘put on the whole armour of God, [you’ll] ...be able to stand against the schemes of the devil’ </i>(Ephesians 6:11 ESV), and he’ll have to move on. God put a hedge around Gomer, the prophet Hosea’s wife, a promise that He would always draw her back to her husband. He said, <i>‘…I will fence her in with thornbushes. I will block her path with a wall to make her lose her way.’ </i>(Hosea 2:6 NLT) Before your family leaves home in the morning, remind them of Christ’s ultimate ‘hedge of protection’—His victory at the cross. Remind them to stand firm in the finished work of Jesus, wearing the whole armour of God (Ephesians 6:10–18). In prayer speak out His promises (Psalm 118:6, Psalm 27:1, James 4:7) and ask Him to safeguard you and your family throughout the day, directing all your paths away from wrong influences.</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Kings 6:8–20, Eph 1:15–23</p><p>MONDAY SEPTEMBER 14</p><p>‘Those who look to Him are radiant…’ Psalm 34:5 NIV</p><p>Beauty Is an Inside Job</p><p>It’s said, ‘Beauty is in the eye of the beholder’, but you can waste your life trying to please the wrong beholder. Kristin Armstrong says: ‘When it comes to beauty, each of us carries baggage from childhood… I’ve fretfully hung clothes of every size in my wardrobe… messed with make–up when I should have slapped on sunscreen and gone outside to play. I’ve eaten close to nothing in an effort to stay small… wasted time worrying I wasn’t pretty enough when I should have been enjoying the things that made me interesting. Throughout history the definition of beauty has shifted to reflect society. Sometimes we should be curvy, other times thin as a lathe; sometimes tanned, sometimes pale; sometimes with long hair, sometimes with short… We devote our energies to meeting the latest standards and… guess what? There’s always another mandate… We must seriously consider whose heart we’re trying to capture… God’s is the only one worth pursuing.’ Paul says, ‘…<i>Don’t let the world around you squeeze you into its own mould, but let God re–mould your minds from within…</i>’ (Romans 12:1–2 PHPS); <i>‘If anyone belongs to Christ…The old things have gone; everything is made new!</i>’ (2 Corinthians 5:17 NCV) You won’t find the secret to inner beauty and peace by comparing yourself with the photoshopped models on magazine covers. That kind of image is unsustainable. You’ll find peace by asking God to remove the scales from your eyes and show you what you look like in His eyes. ‘<i>Those who look to Him are radiant</i>.’ The only healthy and lasting definition of beauty comes from God because He judges people by ‘...<i>what is in their hearts</i>.’ (1 Samuel 16:7 CEV) </p><p>SoulFood (Feast of Trumpets): Num 29:1–6, Matt 24, Rev 11:15–19, 1 Cor 15:50–58</p><p>TUESDAY SEPTEMBER 15</p><p>‘…secret things belong to the Lord… things revealed belong to us…’ Deuteronomy 29:29 NIV</p><p>When You Don’t Understand</p><p>When you don’t understand what’s happening in your life, start with what you know for sure; namely, that God is good all the time, and His ‘…<i>love for those who respect Him continues forever</i>…’ (Psalm 103:17 NCV) He’s not fickle. He doesn’t bless you one day and curse you the next: His ‘<i>mercies…are new every morning</i>.’ (Lamentations 3:22–23 KJV) But there are things God chooses to reveal to us, and ‘secret things’ He doesn’t—for our own good. Writer Beth Jones says: ‘If God keeps a secret from us, it’s for our benefit and the benefit of others… For example, He doesn’t go around blaming, tattling or disclosing our sins, weaknesses, unbelief, carnality, selfishness or pride to others. When things happen, God knows why… Secret things belong to the Lord. And when He reveals something to us, it’s because He wants us to walk in that truth by faith. For example, He reveals His character and His will in His Word… so we can live by faith knowing that He’s good, fair, kind, generous, merciful, faithful, gracious, patient, and He’s in the saving, healing, redeeming, restoring, sanctifying, and blessing business. Things revealed belong to us. When we don’t know why… here’s what we know for sure. God’s Word is truer than our circumstances or experiences… and just because He knows everything about us doesn’t mean He tells us about everything. We also know that when things look bad, God is still good.’ ‘<i>The Lord gave, and the Lord has taken away; blessed be the name of the Lord</i>.’ (Job 1:21 ESV) No matter what happens or doesn’t happen, at the end of the day—God is still in control and worthy of our praise! </p><p>SoulFood: Neh 8–10, Mark 13:24–37, Ps 78:56–64, Prov 24:5–10</p><p>WEDNESDAY SEPTEMBER 16</p><p>‘…your heavenly Father already knows all your needs.’ Matthew 6:32 NLT</p><p>Are You Struggling Financially? (1)</p><p>Donna Savage writes: ‘In my husband’s first years as a pastor our mortgage payment gobbled up half his income… I learned to replace panic with peace by praying for: <i>Clarity</i>. Money is linked to our self–esteem. It can trigger feelings of shame, fear, pride, and anger. But “<i>understanding [God’s] Word brings light to the minds of ordinary people.</i>” (Psalms 119:130 CEV) <i>Creativity</i>. If you want more money, you must earn more or spend less. We serve a creative God, and He rewards those who “…<i>diligently seek Him</i>.” (Hebrews 11:6 NKJV) Ask Him to show you how to increase your income. <i>Connections</i>. Kids are familiar with connect–the–dot puzzles, where you join a random collection of dots to produce an image you’d otherwise miss. It’s all about the right connections, and God can send the right people into your life with answers to your money problems. <i>Contentment</i>. Just like earthquakes expose structural weaknesses in buildings, financial pressure exposes our spiritual weakness. Paul said, “<i>I have learned the secret of being content</i>.” (Philippians 4:12 NIV) Key phrase: I have learned. Hardship enrols us all in a basic contentment course, but we don’t all get the same homework. Some of us learn through financial hardship and proving God’s faithfulness for ourselves.’ Savage continues: ‘I’ve given God an “I can’t do this” ultimatum more than once… I’ve also celebrated the adventure of moment–by–moment dependence on His resources. I’ve proved God’s faithfulness in my prayers and in my pantry, and it’s never limited by my bank balance.’</p><p>SoulFood: Neh 11–13, Mark 14:1–11, Ps 78:65–72, Prov 24:11–14</p><p>THURSDAY SEPTEMBER 17</p><p>‘…all these things shall be added unto you.’ Matthew 6:33 KJV</p><p>Are You Struggling Financially? (2)</p><p>Pray: ‘Heavenly Father, Your Word says, “<i>Seek ye first the kingdom of God, and His righteousness; and all these things shall be added unto you</i>.” You are well able to take care of my financial situation; You know what needs to be done. Direct my steps (Proverbs 3:5–6). Help me to remember that Your resources are meant to flow freely from the place of abundance to the place of need (2 Corinthians 8:14). I believe You have a financial plan for my life, and when fear of the future threatens to overwhelm me, I will hope continually and praise You more and more (Psalms 71:14). As You walk with me through this crisis and I stay focused on You, You promised to keep me in perfect peace (Isaiah 26:3). Forgive me for worrying. I cast all my cares on You right now (1 Peter 5:7)… I don’t have to bear these burdens on my own… I lay them down and receive Your divine rest (Matthew 11:28). You promised to supply all my needs (Philippians 4:19); that it’s Your good pleasure to give me the blessings and benefits of Your Kingdom (Luke 12:32). You told me not to worry about anything and instead make my requests known to You with thanksgiving (Philippians 4:6–7). I know You’ll take care of tomorrow because You’re Jehovah–Jireh, my provider (Matthew 6:34). You know what I need and when I need it… You’re the God of more than enough (Ephesians 3:20). Thank You for meeting my every need, and for the sense of peace and security You’re imparting to me. In Jesus’ name. Amen.’</p><p>SoulFood: Mic 1–4, Mark 14:12–26, Ps 24, Prov 24:15–18</p><p>FRIDAY SEPTEMBER 18</p><p>‘He who…forgives an offence seeks love, but he who…harps on a matter separates…friends.’ Proverbs 17:9 AMP</p><p>Get Over It!</p><p>Countless friendships are destroyed because one person gets offended by something the other one said or did. A mark of spiritual growth is how quickly you get over slights and insults; the more mature you are, the less time it takes to ‘forgive an offence’ and move on. One Christian writer says: ‘Okay, your friend ditches you and your feelings are hurt… or she’s too busy to return your phone call or email… or you’re out to dinner with another couple and the other man insults your husband in an attempt to be funny …Offences come…Jesus said they would (John 16:33). People are people. If you’ve been offended by a friend, or felt slighted, get over it! Hit the Control&gt;Alt&gt;Delete buttons. Don’t let bitterness even think about putting down roots… “<i>Love…is not irritable…it keeps no record of being wronged…never gives up…and endures through every circumstance</i>” (1 Corinthians 13:4–7 NLT) …It seems impossible…and without God’s love it is. So yield to His love, overlook offences and walk in love, because next week you’ll be the one needing unconditional love. When it comes to being perfect, we’ve all failed. If you want your friends to overlook your offences, be quick to overlook theirs.’ Make this your prayer today: ‘Father, thank You for the relationships You’ve blessed me with. I make a decision today to release anyone who has ever offended me in the slightest… to overlook it… forget about it, and move on. I will not keep a record of their wrongs. I will offer mercy and unconditional love. In Jesus’ name. Amen.’</p><p>SoulFood: Mic 5–7, Mark 14:27–42, Ps 19, Prov 24:19–22</p><p>SATURDAY SEPTEMBER 19</p><p>‘…Sharper than any double–edged sword…’ Hebrews 4:12 NIV</p><p>God’s Laser </p><p>Does reading the Bible sometimes make you uneasy? Does the sermon feel like it’s directed at you? ‘…<i>the Word of God is…sharper than any double–edged sword…it penetrates even to dividing soul and spirit…Nothing in all creation is hidden from God’s sight. Everything is uncovered…before…Him to whom we must give account.</i>’ (Hebrews 4:12–13 NIV) When it comes to judging our motives, Jesus, the Great Physician, can determine with laser precision the difference between what’s healthy in our lives and what needs to be removed. Jon Walker writes: ‘A cyst developed under the skin of my right hand…and since I was a journalist I had to do something about it. The procedure was delicate, requiring the surgeon to cut at just the right point… He was confident he could do it …but I was nervous… He did an excellent job and the only reminder I have is a slight scar …The Word of God is as delicate and precise as a surgeon skilfully removing a cyst from cartilage…He operates with perfection… slices away bad attitudes, thoughts, motives, and actions... When God speaks to you it’s for a purpose—to bring your life into conformity to Christ. And your response should always be, ‘<i>Search me, O God, and know my heart</i>…’ (Psalm 139:23 NIV) Let the Word of God highlight the areas in your life that need work. Don’t run from the process.’ Remember ‘…<i>do not despise the discipline of the Almighty... He wounds, but He also binds up; He injures, but His hands also heal</i>.…’ (Job 5:17–18 NIV) </p><p>SoulFood: 2 Tim 1–4, Mark 14:43–52, Ps 3, Prov 24:23–25 </p><p>SUNDAY SEPTEMBER 20</p><p>‘This I recall to my mind, therefore I have hope.’ Lamentations 3:21 NAS</p><p>The Importance of God’s Sovereignty </p><p>Lamentations chapter three describes Jeremiah’s despair, and how he conquered it. He opens with: <i>‘I am the man who has seen affliction…’ </i>(Lamentations 3:1 NAS), and it intensifies as he lists all his troubles. The fact is, when our circumstances deteriorate, we can sound a lot like Jeremiah. At first he sounds like he’s blaming God for his afflictions. In prayer he recites his troubles and fears of being singled out as an object of public ridicule. No wonder he felt powerless and hopeless! (Lamentations 3:18) That kind of situation, handled badly, can initiate and intensify despair, depression and feed a negative outlook on life. But here’s the lesson to be learned: <i>‘This I recall to my mind, therefore I have hope.’ </i>Jeremiah acknowledged God’s goodness and mercy: <i>‘Because of the Lord’s great love we are not consumed… His compassions never fail. They are new every morning; great is Your faithfulness.’ </i>(Lamentations 3:22–23 NIV) He also acknowledged the Lord’s sovereignty in his trouble: ‘<i>For the Lord... though He causes grief, yet He will show compassion according to the multitude of His mercies... Is it not from the mouth of the Most High that woe and well–being proceed?’ </i>(Lamentations 3:31–38 NKJV) When you acknowledge the sovereignty of God in all things it gives your faith in Him a boost, no matter what! It doesn’t happen automatically; you have to deliberately refocus your thinking at the very time when you feel least like doing it. Notice: Jeremiah’s circumstances didn’t improve—his outlook did. He was reminded of the sovereign goodness and faithfulness of God—and his depression lifted: <i>‘“The Lord is my portion,” says my soul, “therefore I have hope in Him.”’ </i>(Lamentations 3:24 NAS)</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Kings 3:4–28, James 1:2–8</p><p>MONDAY SEPTEMBER 21</p><p>‘Love…keeps no record of being wronged...’ 1 Corinthians 13:4–5 NLT </p><p>Dump Your Grudges!</p><p>Holding a grudge is costly, and you and the people in your life end up footing the bill! In all probability the offender has moved on, forgotten the offence and left you holding the bag. But in reality, blame, not the offender, is the crux of the problem. And until you understand and accept that, you will continue to be upset. Don’t let your grudges fester and turn into: (1) <i>Self–victimisation</i>. Negative energy expended on others just drains your resources and robs you of the chance to fulfil your God–given potential. Stop cheating yourself. Don’t surrender your power to your grudges! (2) <i>Bitterness</i>. It’s like a deadly poison; a little of it can contaminate your entire system. The hurt you harbour pollutes the stream of your daily experience, including your experience with God! (3) <i>Isolation</i>. There’s no joy in being around someone who constantly indulges in blame, defensiveness and anger. Others pick up the vibes and feel at risk, so they keep a safe distance in case they become a target in the event that they displease you. It’s a formula for isolation and self–induced loneliness. (4) <i>Negative role–modelling</i>. Maybe you think, ‘My feelings are nobody’s business!’ Maybe—if you live on a desert island. Grudges are highly communicable. ‘…<i>Watch out that no poisonous root of bitterness grows up…corrupting many</i>.’ (Hebrews 12:15 NLT) (5) <i>Sabotaged repentance</i>. Genuine repentance and forgiveness aren’t possible until you’re willing to face up to your grudges. If you’re still blaming others, you’re avoiding responsibility. A bad attitude is like a flat tyre—until you change it, you’re not going to get anywhere. </p><p>SoulFood: Zech 1–4, Mark 14:53–65, Ps 39, Prov 24:26–28</p><p>TUESDAY SEPTEMBER 22</p><p>‘…God created mankind in His own image…’ Genesis 1:27 NIV</p><p>Start Thinking Creatively (1)</p><p>The Bible calls you a ‘<i>child of God</i>’. Stop and consider what that means. God’s creativity is already built into your DNA; your job is to identify it, release it and put it to work. Writers and even ad–men have recognised the great power of creativity is in its defeat of habit by originality. But for your creativity to be released, you must first identify the barriers and start taking them down. Here’s a common one: ‘We’ve always done it this way.’ People who say that have stopped thinking for themselves. They’re just putting in their time, waiting for a pay packet and going home at the end of the day without thinking, reflecting or even considering the possibilities of change. If you’re one of these people, it’s time to wake up and start looking around you. Mind–deadening routine is the cancer of creativity. If you mindlessly go about your business the same way every day, your routine is opening you up to mistakes. Why? Because, the chances are, your habits have caused you to lose the ability to think critically and question your methods. Start questioning policies, techniques, forms, rules, paperwork—anything that’s become routine. Ask, ‘Why do we do that? Is it even necessary? Can we do it better?’ On the farm of success there are no sacred cows. If you insist on doing things the way they’ve always been done, you’ll end up being out–thought, out–sold, out–produced and finally out of business. So start thinking creatively.</p><p>SoulFood: Zech 5–8, Mark 14:66–72, Ps 34, Prov 24:29–31</p><p>WEDNESDAY SEPTEMBER 23</p><p>‘Do you see a man skilful in his work? He will stand before kings; he will not stand before obscure men.’ Proverbs 22:29 ESV</p><p>Start Thinking Creatively (2)</p><p>God has given you the skills and creativity you need to succeed, but you need to steward them and continue stretching your capacity. In other words, thinking creatively. Film director Frank Capra said, ‘A hunch is creativity trying to tell you something.’ So if you’re part of a church or a business that continually throws up obstacles to productivity, forms barriers to originality and puts the brakes on momentum, it’s time to speak up. And if nobody will listen, it’s time to pray and ask God if you’re in the right place. An environment doesn’t just ‘happen’, it’s created by the people who live and work in it. People, systems and policies either stoke the fire of creativity or put it out. Alexander the Great once visited the famed teacher Diogenes and asked whether he could do anything for him. Diogenes replied, ‘Only stand out of my light.’ One of the best things you can do for a creative person is not to get in their way! Michelangelo, Rembrandt and Leonardo da Vinci all used the best equipment and went to extraordinary lengths to find the finest materials for their paints, brushes and canvas. And they’d be no different today. But don’t expect change to come easily. Insecure leaders tend to penalise honesty and feel threatened by creativity, especially when it suggests there’s a better way of doing things. But you owe it to God, to yourself and the people you work with to give it your best shot. </p><p>SoulFood (Yom Kippur): Lev 16, Lev 23:26–32, Heb 9:1–14, Heb 13:11–16 </p><p>THURSDAY SEPTEMBER 24</p><p>‘Diotrephes…does not acknowledge our authority…’ 3 John 1:9 ESV</p><p>Start Thinking Creatively (3)</p><p>Not everybody is willing to think creatively, and where it becomes problematic is when people disregard the authority of those who have been put in charge. The apostle John said: ‘<i>I have written briefly to the church; but Diotrephes, who likes to take the lead among them and put himself first, does not acknowledge my authority and refuses to accept my suggestions or listen to me</i>.’ Every organisation has at least one of these people; just make sure it’s not you. Author Phil Cooke says: ‘One of the most damaging sacred cows in organisations is basing employee status on seniority rather than talent. Yes, loyalty is important, but some of the most loyal employees I’ve ever met are loyal because of selfishness. They project loyalty to keep their jobs, retain their benefits, or hold on to their authority. Real loyalty is about innovation, original thinking and helping the company get to the next level… Every person has worth and is important. But a great leader always knows the people who bring the most value to the organisation. Those are the people to be developed, trained and cultivated. When you create an atmosphere of original thinking, you’ll have more loyalty than you’ll know what to do with. Most companies are so ignorant of how to develop an environment of innovation that if you’ll do it, you will have people coming from every direction to work with you.’ The apostle Paul practised and taught this principle: ‘<i>We urge you… to recognise those who labour among you… and to esteem them very highly in love for their work’s sake</i>…’ (1 Thessalonians 5:12–13 NKJV) To become a creative thinker, you must value creative thinking.</p><p>SoulFood: Zech 9–11, Mark 15:1–11, Ps 52, Prov 24:32–34</p><p>FRIDAY SEPTEMBER 25</p><p>‘...Having believed, you were marked…with a seal...’ Ephesians 1:13 NIV</p><p>The Deal is Sealed</p><p>If you are having doubts about your salvation, understand this clearly: the moment you trusted in Christ as your Saviour, His blood cleansed you from all sin. At that point ‘<i>you were marked…with a seal, the promised Holy Spirit…guaranteeing [your]…redemption</i>.’ (Ephesians 1:13–14 NIV) The Bible says, ‘<i>You should not be like cowering fearful slaves. You should behave instead like God’s very own children, adopted into His family—calling Him, “Father, dear Father!” For the Holy Spirit speaks to us deep in our hearts and tells us we are God’s children. And since we are His children, we will share His treasures—for everything God gives to His Son, Christ, is ours too</i>.’ (Romans 8:15–16 NLT)</p><p>In the book of Ruth we read that ‘<i>the custom…in Israel concerning redeeming…[was] one man took off his sandal…gave it to the other, and this was a confirmation</i>...’ (Ruth 4:7 NKJV) Notice, the ‘redeemer’ put on another man’s sandal, signifying his willingness to stand in his place. That’s what Jesus did for us at the cross. He stood in our shoes so we could stand before God in His—redeemed and righteous! Don’t let doubt steal your joy. Refuse to go by your feelings. Make up your mind to believe what God says, for until you do you’ll be plagued by uncertainty. Study God’s Word until you can say with assurance, ‘...<i>I know whom I have believed and am persuaded that He is able to keep what I have committed to Him until that Day.</i>’ (2 Timothy 1:12 NKJV) Are you trusting in Christ as your Saviour? Then your salvation is not in doubt. The deal is sealed!</p><p>SoulFood: Zech 12–14, Mark 15:12–20, Ps 54, Prov 25:1–3</p><p>SATURDAY SEPTEMBER 26</p><p>‘…If God has given you leadership ability, take the responsibility seriously…’ Romans 12:8 NLT</p><p>Characteristics of Godly Leadership</p><p>Leadership in business, politics and public service doesn’t automatically qualify you for leadership in church. J Oswald Sanders says, ‘The overriding need of the church... is for a leadership that’s authoritative, spiritual and sacrificial.’ Let’s look at each of those qualities: (1) <i>Authoritative leadership</i>. People respect leaders who are certain about where they’re going, and inspire confidence in those who choose to follow them. Tentative leaders don’t motivate others to get on board and stay on board. Uncertainty confuses and disheartens followers. People follow, almost without question, someone who’s wise, strong and faithful to what he or she believes. (2) <i>Spiritual leadership</i>. We’re attracted to leaders who are gifted and charismatic. But these natural characteristics alone aren’t enough. Followers can be captivated by human traits—often to their own cost. Don’t settle for being a popular ‘Pied Piper’. Godly leaders are committed to connecting their followers with Jesus, not with themselves! Do your people know, love and serve God more because of your leadership? If so, you’re a godly leader. (3) <i>Sacrificial leadership</i>. Would you still lead if, like Paul, you were betrayed, falsely accused, beaten, half–drowned, starved, stoned and left for dead? Godly leaders lead when it’s uncomfortable, inconvenient, unrewarding and costly. They’re dedicated to the sheep they’re responsible for, and the ‘Chief Shepherd’ they’re responsible to! They recognise that Jesus drafted and modelled the prototype of godly leadership at the cost of His own life: ‘<i>To this you were called, because Christ suffered for you, leaving you an example, that you should follow in His step</i>s.’ (1 Peter 2:21 NIV)</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 1–3, Mark 15:21–32, Ps 13, Prov 25: 4–8</p><p>SUNDAY SEPTEMBER 27</p><p>‘…Jesus…went around doing good…’ Acts 10:38 NIV</p><p>What Are You Called to Do?</p><p>Your value in God’s eyes was established at the Cross. The Bible says, ‘<i>He who did not spare His own Son, but gave Him up for us all—how will He not also, along with Him, graciously give us all things</i>?’ (Romans 8:32 NIV) Notice the words ‘<i>all things</i>’. We are all equal in Christ. But when it comes to your career, your value is determined by the problem you solve. That’s why we pay a cardiologist more money than a chef in a fast–food restaurant. Jesus was a problem solver. People were spiritually hungry so He said, ‘…<i>I am the bread of life</i>…’ (John 6:35 NIV) They were sick so He ‘<i>went about doing good…healing all</i>.’ He discerned what He had, that others needed, and provided it for them. What do you have to offer? What would you attempt to do if you knew it was impossible to fail? You are not here by accident. God told Jeremiah, ‘<i>Before I formed you in the womb I knew you; before you were born I sanctified you; I ordained you a prophet to the nations</i>.’ (Jeremiah 1:5 NKJV) Everything God makes is to meet a need and solve a problem. So what are you called and gifted to do? That’s where you’ll find your highest level of joy! Think of your contribution to others as an assignment from God. Paul made tents to support his ministry. So your ministry may be supported by your job. But whether you are in a full–time ministry or a part–time ministry, don’t leave this earth until you have found and fulfilled what God called you to do. </p><p>SoulFood: Eph 5:21–33, Song of Songs 2:1–7, Ps 45, Prov 5:15–19</p><p>MONDAY SEPTEMBER 28</p><p>‘…through love serve one another.’ Galatians 5:13 NKJV</p><p>Get Rid of Your Entitlement Attitude</p><p>The Bible says, ‘…<i>through love serve one another</i>.’ In other words, ‘Get rid of the you–owe–me attitude and develop an IOU mindset.’ Some of us think: (1) A lifetime job with good pay and a guaranteed retirement plan at sixty–five come with just being born. (2) Promotion is just a matter of time. (3) Forty hours a week is the maximum endurance for any worker. (4) The last hour of each day is there to make the transition to home easier. (5) A ten–minute coffee break should take at least half–an–hour. (6) A half–hour lunch break should take at least an hour–and–a–half. (7) An equal share of company profits belongs to all workers regardless of their contribution. What gives us our source of entitlement anyway? Part of it is found in the middle of the word entitlement itself: ‘title’. We think people ‘owe us’ because of the title we hold in their lives: mother, daughter, brother, wife, husband, friend, donor, pastor, employee, boss, etc. We treat our title as if it were a title deed that gives us the right to whatever benefit we expect. But life doesn’t work that way! When the Prodigal Son left home and landed in a pig sty, the Bible says, ‘…<i>no one gave him anything</i>.’ (Luke 15:16 NKJV) Humbled and slapped with reality, he became willing to work in the servants’ quarters of his father’s house. Fortunately, his father loved him and restored him. But the point is, life ‘owes you’ nothing. God ‘owes you’ nothing. Anything we receive from Him is an act of His grace and benevolence. He has given us opportunities to study, work hard, grow, and sacrifice to get to where we want to be but ultimately we must remember that ‘Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, coming down from the Father of lights...’ (James 1:17 ESV) </p><p>SoulFood: Lev 23:33–44, Jn 7:1–40, Zech 14:16–21, Heb 11:8–16</p><p>TUESDAY SEPTEMBER 29</p><p>‘…lay your hand upon your mouth.’ Proverbs 30:32 AMP</p><p>Making Yourself Look Good (1)</p><p>Your tongue is just centimetres from your brain, but the way some of us rattle on, you’d think our mouths and minds were kilometres apart! James says, ‘…<i>The tongue…corrupts the whole body</i>…’ (James 3:5–6 NIV) Ramona Cramer Tucker writes: ‘I admit I’m a talker …I don’t set out to break a confidence, but somehow my mouth kicks into gear before my brain… But God takes a clear stand on gossip. He knows loose lips can ruin another person’s reputation, introduce mistrust into a relationship, encourage the gossiper to embellish their tale, and cause them to sin by being tempted to lie when confronted… I love to share news, to be “in the know”, and because I’m wired this way it’s easy for me to spread gossip under the guise of being well–meaning, even prefacing my news with “I wish you’d pray for”… But just because my sharing is well–meant doesn’t mean it’s appropriate.’ The most common reason for making someone else look bad—is to make ourselves look good! We are like the proud Pharisee in the temple who stood alone and prayed, ‘…<i>God, I thank you that I am not like other people</i>…’ (Luke 18:11 NCV) The writer of Proverbs says, ‘<i>If you have done foolishly in exalting yourself, or…thought evil, lay your hand upon your mouth</i>.’ (Proverbs 30:32 AMP) It’s one thing to think bad thoughts—it’s another to voice them. The saying goes: ‘You can’t stop the birds from flying over your head, but you can stop them from building a nest in your hair!’ So do yourself and everybody around you a favour—practise putting your brain in gear before engaging your mouth.</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 4–6, Mark 15:33–47, Ps 91, Prov 25:9–12</p><p>WEDNESDAY SEPTEMBER 30</p><p>‘…if we could control our tongues…’ James 3:2 NLT</p><p>Making Yourself Look Good (2)</p><p>When you’re upset, it’s tempting to ‘hand out other people’s dirty laundry’. But making yourself look good at somebody else’s expense always backfires. One Christian author observes: ‘That righteous feeling turns to shame faster than you can walk away, hang up the phone, or hit “send”…I can’t emphasise enough how crucial it is to get control over your tongue. I wish someone had warned me to stop talking and start praying.’ A lady named Michelle learned her lesson the hard way. She was having lunch with a co–worker at a restaurant and they visited the ladies’ toilet. While they were fixing their hair they started to talk about people at work who drove them crazy. Immediately Michelle launched into a diatribe about Beth, a co–worker who had no idea how much trouble she created for the rest of the team. As Michelle prepared to launch into more specifics, a cubicle door opened and out walked Beth, flushed and upset. In a split second what felt like a pressure–relief session turned into an embarrassing mess… Beth ran out in tears, and Michelle couldn’t take back the words she’d said. Beth never returned to work, and the next day she resigned. While her co–workers openly cheered what they considered to be good news, Michelle was miserable… She tried to call Beth, and even wrote a letter of apology, but there was no response. And what’s worse, Michelle is a Christian and Beth made no such profession. Treat others the way you’d like to be treated (Matthew 7:12). What goes around comes around, and idle chatter will surely come back to haunt you.</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 7–9, Mark 16:1–8, Ps 68:1–18, Prov 25:13–16 </p><p>THURSDAY OCTOBER 1</p><p>‘…overwhelming victory is ours through Christ, who loved us.’ Romans 8:37 NLT</p><p>The Power to Solve the Problem</p><p>Everyone has problems. The only people who don’t—are in cemeteries. The real problem is—how we handle our problems. Often we try to solve them with our own power. How can you tell when you’re doing that? Because you’re tired all the time! You’re like the guy who said, ‘I’m sick and tired of being sick and tired.’ Or we’re like the lady who said, ‘Just about the time I manage to make ends meet, somebody moves the ends.’ We say things like, ‘I’m doing ok under the circumstances.’ Well, what are you doing <i>under</i> them? Someone has said that circumstances are like a mattress; if you’re on top you rest easy, but if you’re underneath you suffocate! What’s the answer? Take your focus off your problems and put it on God’s promises. Here’s one of them: ‘<i>Can anything ever separate us from Christ’s love? Does it mean He no longer loves us if we have trouble?...</i>’ (Romans 8:35 NLT) Paul answers, ‘<i>No, despite all these things, overwhelming victory is ours through Christ, who loved us</i>.’ (Romans 8:37 NLT) The word ‘conqueror’ means ‘one who overcomes by gaining control’. And Paul says that we are ‘<i>more than</i> <i>conquerors</i>.’ (Romans 8:37 NKJV) To be a conqueror means to fight a battle and win. To be more than a conqueror means to win a battle without having to fight. Jesus fights on your behalf; He does it in you, and through you, and that makes you ‘<i>more than</i>’ a conqueror. </p><p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 10–11, Mark 16:9–20, Ps 68:19–35, Prov 25:17–20</p><p>FRIDAY OCTOBER 2</p><p>‘…I will strengthen you and help you…’ Isaiah 41:10 NIV</p><p>The Power to Change</p><p>We go to seminars and conferences looking for a painless cure by which our lives can be zapped and changed. We go on diets. We join health clubs and our enthusiasm runs strong for about two weeks. Then we fall back into the same old rut. We don’t change. We read self–help books, but the problem with self–help books is that they tell us what to do but can’t give us the power to do it. We are told things like: ‘Get rid of all your bad habits. Be positive; don’t be negative.’ But how? Where do we get the power to change? The Greek word for ‘power’, <i>dunamis</i>, is used in the New Testament to describe the most powerful event that ever happened—the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead. And that resurrection power is available to change your life today. The most important thing in life is knowing Christ and experiencing the power of His resurrection. Paul writes, ‘<i>I want to know Christ… to know the power of His resurrection</i>…’ (Philippians 3:10 NIV) Again he writes, ‘<i>I pray that you will begin to understand how incredibly great His power is to help those who believe in Him. It is that same mighty power that raised Christ from the dead</i>…’ (Ephesians 1:19–20 TLB). This Greek word for ‘power’, <i>dunamis</i>, can be understood in two ways: (1) ‘<i>dynamite</i>’, which is an explosive force, or (2) ‘<i>dynamo</i>’, which is a constant flow of power. And in Christ, you have both. Through Him you can break the chains that bind you and the limits that constrain you, and walk victoriously in His power today.</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 12–14, John 1:1–13, Ps 60, Prov 25:21–22</p><p>SATURDAY OCTOBER 3</p><p>‘Don’t just pretend to love others. Really love them…’ Romans 12:9 NLT</p><p>Rules for Serving</p><p>When it comes to serving others, try to live by these three rules: (1) <i>Serve sincerely</i>. ‘<i>Don’t just pretend to love others. Really love them…</i>’ God knows your heart, so be honest with yourself about your true motives in serving and sacrificing for others. If you need help in this area, turn to the Scriptures: ‘<i>For the Word of God is living and powerful, and sharper than any two–edged sword…and is a discerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart.</i>’ (Hebrews 4:12 NKJV) (2) <i>Serve silently</i>. ‘…<i>when you do a charitable deed, do not sound a trumpet…that [you] may have glory from men</i>…’ (Matthew 6:2 NKJV) Note the words, ‘<i>do not sound a trumpet</i>’. When people take your kindness for granted or fail to appreciate the things you do for them, don’t toot your own horn. Look to God for your reward, not people; otherwise you’ll be disappointed. ‘…<i>as the eyes of servants look to the hand of their masters… so our eyes look to the Lord our God</i>…’ (Psalm 123:2 NKJV) (3) <i>Serve selectively</i>. You’re not called to go to every place, meet every need, and help every person. On two different occasions God stopped Paul from going into Asia to preach the Gospel. But look what happened next: ‘<i>And a vision appeared to Paul in the night. A man of Macedonia stood and pleaded with him, saying, “Come over to Macedonia and help us.”…immediately we sought to go to Macedonia, concluding that the Lord had called us to preach the Gospel to them.</i>’ (Acts 16:9–10 NKJV) Why is this important to know? Because when God guides you, He provides for you!</p><p>SoulFood: 1 Cor 15–16, John 1:14–28, Ps 51, Prov 25:23–25</p><p>SUNDAY OCTOBER 4</p><p>‘…shake the dust off your feet…’ Mark 6:11 NIV</p><p>Shake It Off</p><p>Here’s some good advice Jesus gave His disciples. When someone rejects you or won’t listen to you, ‘…<i>shake the dust off your feet when you leave, as a testimony against them</i>.’ When you experience rejection, you have two choices: allow it to affect your confidence and self–worth, or ‘shake it off’ and move on. Now, Jesus was not talking about sincere minds that don’t understand, but proud minds that reject the truth. He was saying, ‘Don’t let it break your stride and keep you from accomplishing what needs to be done.’<i> </i>When Paul was shipwrecked on the island of Malta, he was bitten by a snake while gathering firewood. Immediately the islanders said to one another, <i>‘…this man is a murderer, whom, though he has escaped the sea, yet justice does not allow to live.</i>’ (Acts 28:4 NKJV) How did Paul respond? ‘…<i>he shook off the creature into the fire and suffered no harm.</i>’ (Acts 28:5 NKJV) What did the islanders say about him then? ‘…<i>they changed their minds and said that he was a god</i>.’ (Acts 28:6 NKJV) Wow! People’s minds change like the wind! So don’t let their compliments puff you up, or their criticisms tear you down. God’s will is for you to help others. If they accept your help, give it. If not, go where you will be accepted and appreciated. Jesus said, ‘…<i>I say to you, he who receives whomever I send, receives Me</i>…’ (John 13:20 NKJV) In the final analysis it’s not you they are rejecting, but the One who sent you. Knowing that, gives you confidence and peace of mind.</p><p>SoulFood: Jos 1:7–8, 2 Tim 3:14–17, Ps 119:1–16</p><p>MONDAY OCTOBER 5</p><p>‘You will keep in perfect peace all who trust in You…’ Isaiah 26:3 NLT</p><p>Are You Afraid? Trust God!</p><p>Fear is a normal part of living. And the most successful and confident people you know experience it. The difference is they refuse to be ruled by fear because they know that, when it gets out of control, it can paralyse you. The Bible says, ‘…<i>fear involves torment</i>…’ (1 John 4:18 NKJV) Neuroscientists at Yale University discovered that patients who expected to experience an electric shock had anxiety levels similar to those who responded to the real thing. Researcher Elizabeth Phelps writes, ‘A lot of our fears and anxieties are learned through communication. If someone tells you to be afraid of a dog, then the brain responds as if you actually were.’ In other words, our brains don’t know the difference between real and imagined threats. This goes a long way toward explaining why the National Institute of Mental Health reported that almost twenty million Americans suffer from anxiety disorders. Someone who’s perfectly safe, but has a fear of being robbed, suffers just as much as someone living in a situation with a high risk of robbery, or someone actually in the act of being robbed. Because our brains don’t discriminate between emotions that are real or imagined, fear can dominate our lives, and it’s just as devastating as physical injury. Psychologist Marilyn Barrick said, ‘For the most part, fear is nothing but an illusion. When you share it with someone, it tends to disappear.’ So share your fears with God and watch them begin to disappear. The Bible says, ‘<i>You will keep in perfect peace all who trust in You, all whose thoughts are fixed on You!</i>’</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 1–3, John 1:29–42, Ps 63, Prov 25:26–28</p><p>TUESDAY OCTOBER 6</p><p>‘…in Him we live and move and exist…’ Acts 17:28 NLT</p><p>A Blank Only God Can Fill</p><p>Here’s a time–tested maxim: ‘The heart is a God–shaped blank, and only God can fill it.’ In <i>Through the Valley of the Kwai: From Death–Camp Despair to Spiritual Triumph</i>, Ernest Gordon writes about soldiers who were captured, tortured and starved by the Japanese in the Malay Peninsula in World War II. As a result they started acting like animals, clawing, fighting and stealing food. In an effort to turn things around, the group decided to start reading the New Testament. And as Gordon read it to them they were converted to Christ, and this community of animals was transformed into a community of love. That’s because Jesus is God and is willing to live in the hearts of those who trust Him. He offers joy, peace, a transformed life and assurance of eternal life to all those who place their trust in His atoning death. So what are you using to try to fill the void in your life? Material possessions? Mood–altering substances? Sex? Career success? The pursuit of intellectual growth? Excitement? You may as well give it up now—it won’t work! Paul explained it like this to the philosophers in Athens: ‘…<i>God…made the world and everything in it… He…gives life…to everything… He satisfies every need… His purpose was [that we should] seek after God…feel [our] way towards Him and find Him—though He is not far from…us. For in Him we live and move and exist</i>…’ (Acts 17:24–28 NLT) In the words of the time–honoured hymn: ‘Now none but Christ can satisfy; none other name for me. There’s love, and life, and lasting joy, Lord Jesus, found in Thee.’</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 4–6, John 1:43–51, Ps 92, Prov 26:1–3</p><p>WEDNESDAY OCTOBER 7</p><p>‘…what will be the sign of Your coming?...’ Matthew 24:3 NKJV</p><p>Signs of the Times (1) </p><p>When the disciples came to Jesus and asked Him, ‘…<i>what will be the sign of Your coming, and of the end of the age?</i>’, He told them things were going to get worse before they got better. Then He added these words: ‘…<i>see to it that you are not alarmed</i>…’ (Matthew 24:6 NIV) The word ‘alarmed’ is one Jesus used only on this occasion; it means ‘to wail, to cry aloud’. In essence, what He was saying is this: ‘Don’t fall apart when bad things happen.’ For the next few days let’s look at some of the signs Jesus said would herald His return. <i>Spiritual deception</i>. ‘…<i>Watch out that no one deceives you. For many will come in My name, claiming, “I am the Messiah,” and will deceive many.</i>’ (Matthew 24:4–5 NIV) Notice, there’ll be many deceived, as well as many deceivers. Jesus also said they’ll come ‘<i>in My name</i>’, masquerading as ministers of God and claiming special status and superior spirituality. They’ll boast of insider information and adorn their teachings with phrases like ‘God told me,’ implying they have access to information the common people like you don’t have. Don’t be misled. Jesus also warned, ‘…<i>false Messiahs and false prophets will appear and perform great signs and wonders to deceive, if possible, even the elect.</i>’ (Matthew 24:24 NIV) Multitudes and miracles—when you see them, be careful. Satan can counterfeit both. Be doctrinally diligent. Focus on one question: ‘Is this person pointing listeners to the real, Biblical Jesus?’ There is only room for one name on the marquee—and that’s His!</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 7–9, John 2:1–11, Ps 29, Prov 26:4–6</p><p>THURSDAY OCTOBER 8</p><p>‘…wars and rumours of wars…’ Matthew 24:6 NIV </p><p>Signs of the Times (2)</p><p>Jesus said: ‘<i>You…hear of wars and rumours of wars… see to it that you are not alarmed. Such things must happen, but the end is still to come. Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. There will be famines and earthquakes in various places. All these are the beginning of birth pains</i>.’ Those who suffered through two world wars have no difficulty comprehending the word ‘wars’. But for the next six decades or so, their children and grandchildren had a more limited concept of what war meant. To them, wars were mostly regional and overseas but not on the homeland. Then came 9/11, and Americans began to understand the words, ‘<i>Men’s hearts failing them for fear</i>…’ (Luke 21:26 NKJV) Some dates will forever stand out in our memory. Like the day President Kennedy was assassinated, and the day three thousand people perished in the World Trade Centre. Today the political rationale is if we fight terrorism ‘over there’, we won’t have to fight it here at home. But don’t be deceived. Borders will always need checkpoints. War correspondents will always have jobs. The world will never see lasting peace this side of Heaven. Jesus said, ‘…<i>All these are the beginning of birth pains</i>.’ Rejoice! God is still on the throne. His plan is still being worked out. The death throes of the old order we live in are the ‘birth pains’ of a new and glorious order, when Christ will return to set up His Kingdom. An old Prudential Insurance Company slogan says, ‘Get a piece of the rock.’ But when you’re trusting in Jesus for your security, you have the whole Rock!</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 10–12, John 2:12–25, Ps 131, Prov 26:7–9</p><p>FRIDAY OCTOBER 9</p><p>‘…you will be…put to death…because of Me.’ Matthew 24:9 NIV </p><p>Signs of the Times (3)</p><p>Jesus said to His disciples: ‘...<i>you will be handed over to be persecuted…put to death, and…hated by all nations because of Me. At that time many will turn away from the faith and will betray and hate each other, and many false prophets will appear and deceive many people. Because of the increase of wickedness, the love of most will grow cold</i>.’ (Matthew 24:9–12 NIV) Notice the words ‘<i>put to death</i>’. Heaven is filled with those who have already fulfilled this prophecy—and hatred of Christians still abounds. <i>Voice of the Martyrs</i>, a Christian agency that defends religious liberties, contends that more of Christ’s followers have been killed for their faith in the last century than in most of the previous centuries combined. The global evangelism movement reports an average of 165,000 martyrs a year, more than four times the number in the past century. Today countries that facilitate religious freedom are experiencing increasing hostility toward Christians. Professors publicly mock Bible–believing students. TV talk show hosts denigrate people of faith. We can expect the persecution to increase, and when it does, fragile convictions will collapse and ‘…<i>the love of many will grow cold</i>.’ (Matthew 24:12 NLT) The half–hearted will become the cold–hearted. Spiritual stowaways will jump ship. Many church attendees will be exposed as faith pretenders. They’ll not only leave the faith, they’ll make the lives of the faithful miserable. When these things begin to happen, Jesus counselled, ‘…<i>See to it that you are not alarmed</i>…’ (Matthew 24:6 NIV) When the outlook is bleak, the ‘…<i>blessed hope</i>…’ (Titus 2:13 AMP) of Christ’s return calms our fears.</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 13–15, John 3:1–8, Ps 23, Prov 26:10–12</p><p>SATURDAY OCTOBER 10</p><p>‘…this Gospel…will be preached in all the world…’ Matthew 24:14 NKJV</p><p>Signs of the Times (4)</p><p>Jesus said when we see calamity and apostasy, don’t give in to fear because they’re signs of His imminent return. ‘<i>But he who endures to the end shall be saved. And this Gospel of the Kingdom will be preached in all the world as a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come</i>.’ (Matthew 24:13–14 NKJV) Every prophecy concerning Christ’s first coming was fulfilled in detail, and so will every prophecy concerning His second coming. Our mandate is to work, pray, give, and take the Gospel to the whole world—then Christ will return. Though the church is winnowed down like Gideon’s army, and the world is in a state of upheaval, don’t overreact. ‘<i>Be still in the presence of the Lord, and wait patiently for Him to act. Don’t worry about evil people who prosper or fret about their wicked schemes.</i>’ (Psalm 37:7 NLT) God’s hand is still on the wheel. ‘…<i>the Most High rules in the kingdom of men</i>…’ (Daniel 4:17 NKJV) Avoid Pollyanna optimism. Though you may be personally blessed, the world order as you know it will continue to disintegrate. But that doesn’t mean you should join the ‘Chicken Licken chorus’ and declare, ‘The sky’s falling down!’ Don’t give in to the extremes of blind denial or blatant panic. When the bombs of World War II levelled Warsaw, only one skeletal structure remained standing on the city’s main street. It was the British and Foreign Bible Society, and on its walls was clearly written: ‘<i>Heaven and earth shall pass away, but My words shall not pass away</i>.’ (Matthew 24:35 KJV)</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 16–18, John 3:9–21, Ps 110, Prov 26:13–16</p><p>SUNDAY OCTOBER 11</p><p>‘You intended to harm me, but God intended it for good…’ Genesis 50:20 NIV</p><p>Are You Selling Your Dream?</p><p>In the movie <i>Up in the Air</i>, actor George Clooney is hired by a major corporation to handle big lay–offs. His job is to fire people. In one scene when he’s about to fire an ageing middle manager, he notices on the man’s CV that he’d been trained as a French chef. As the man expresses despair over losing his job, Clooney reminds him of his original dream and asks him this soul–searching question: ‘Back when you started, how much did it take to buy you away from your dream?’ At that pivotal moment the middle manager thought back to the time he decided to settle for a steady pay packet in exchange for what he really wanted to do with his life. Are you doing that? Understand this: the day you were born God had a track for you to run on and an assignment for you to fulfil. So the question you must ask yourself is this: ‘Is the difficult situation I’m in right now a God–given opportunity for me to go back and fulfil the dream God gave me in the first place?’ Looking back on the most painful chapter in his life, when he was betrayed by his family, Joseph said, ‘<i>You intended to harm me, but God intended it for good</i>.’ His greatest loss led Joseph to the fulfilment of the dream God gave him in the beginning. Is that your story too? Are you realising that you’ve settled for second best, and now God’s giving you a second chance; a chance to do the thing He put you in the world to do?</p><p>SoulFood: Joel 2:23–32, Acts 2:1–21</p><p>MONDAY OCTOBER 12</p><p>‘…go and tell him his fault between you and him alone…’ Matthew 18:15 NKJV</p><p>Sometimes You Must Confront</p><p>Jesus said, ‘…<i>if your brother sins against you, go and tell him his fault between you and him alone. If he hears you, you have gained your brother</i>.’ Confronting someone requires these three things: character, courage and caution. Let’s look at each: (1) <i>Character</i>. Since Jesus was secure in His identity and character as God’s Son, He was able to let go of the need to please and be accepted by those around Him. Being grounded in who you are in Christ and in what your heavenly Father created you to be, allows you the freedom to confront people when necessary without worrying about the fall–out or the negative consequences. (2) <i>Courage</i>. The Pharisees had the power to undermine Christ’s reputation, which eventually led to His death on the cross. But He told them the truth nonetheless. And you must do the same. You must be willing to take up your cross and follow Him, even when it means risking an argument and handling hurt feelings. To ‘confront’ means to get in ‘front’ of someone, look into their face, and deal with the issue honestly and lovingly because you value the relationship. (3) <i>Caution</i>. Make sure you’re following God’s timing and not your own. It’s easy to use false courage or bravado to challenge others in order to get your own way. It’s easy to claim a confrontation is necessary, when what you actually want is control. No, you must ask God to show you when, how and where to confront others. Your goal should always be to reconcile and restore the relationship. So ‘<i>go and tell him [or her]</i>’.</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 19–21, John 3:22–36, Ps 89:1–14, Prov 26:17–19</p><p>TUESDAY OCTOBER 13</p><p>‘Faithful are the wounds of a friend; but the kisses of an enemy are deceitful.’ Proverbs 27:6 NKJV</p><p>Can You Give and Receive Correction?</p><p>The word ‘correction’ is not one we are always comfortable with. It sometimes recalls memories of frowning parents and painful consequences. Or we think of the risk of destroying a relationship rather than the possibilities of strengthening and enriching it. ‘<i>Faithful are the wounds of a friend, but the kisses of an enemy are deceitful</i>.’ We all need someone to tell us the truth because others have 20/20 vision where we have blind spots. Yes, someone may react defensively, but they may also be thrilled to realise you care more about their ultimate well–being than their immediate response to you. Corrections made from a loving spirit, not a self–righteous, ‘I–know–what’s–best’ attitude are usually well received. If others sense you are genuinely concerned for them and long for a better relationship, they are likely to consider what you have to say and be open to making changes. Think of the courage Nathan the prophet showed in confronting David over his sin with Bathsheba. As king, David held the power of life and death over him. But Nathan loved David too much to allow sin to rob him of his destiny. God often uses us in each other’s lives to restore us to the narrow yet rich paths of destiny that He has preordained. Looking back, David could say, ‘<i>Before I was afflicted I went astray: but now I keep Your Word.</i>’ (Psalm 119:67 NKJV) There are times when wisdom says, ‘Mind your own business and stay out of it.’ And there are other times when wisdom says, ‘Because you love them, get involved.’</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 22–24, John 4:1–12, Ps 89:15–37, Prov 26:20–22 </p><p>WEDNESDAY OCTOBER 14</p><p lang="en-GB">‘Many shall run to and fro, and knowledge shall increase.’ Daniel 12:4 NKJV</p><p lang="en-GB">Information Overload! (1)</p><p lang="en-GB">Technology lets us do things we’ve never been able to do, but it can be addictive. You can become tied to it in ways that are exhausting. One expert notes: ‘There’s a strong tendency for humans to do everything they’re able to. Combine that with constant connectivity, and the workday need never end. It’s easy to contact anyone anytime, and with information always available on line you can keep clicking forever.’ Paul writes about ‘<i>making the most of your time</i>.’ (Ephesians 5:16 NAS) We say, ‘Time is money,’ but in actuality time is much more valuable, because it’s a non–renewable resource. Once spent, it’s gone forever. Managing information overload means re–establishing boundaries that technology has demolished. So:</p><p lang="en-GB"><i>Recognise the signs</i>: if you communicate with people all day yet you’re still lonely, chances are, technology is dominating your life. <i>Take baby steps</i>: make yourself unavailable for short periods and see what happens. The wheels of industry won’t grind to a halt! Remember you have a choice: people who think they should be available 24/7 exaggerate their own importance or the control others have over them. <i>Establish boundaries</i>: rein in the emails, instant messages and on–line feeds. Do you really need all those ‘FYI’s’ about the same thing? <i>Give clear instructions</i>: tell people you answer emails at designated times throughout the day, and let them know who to contact for an immediate response. <i>Make a task list</i>: that way if you’re interrupted you’ll get back on track faster. <i>Stick to a schedule</i>: constantly dipping in and out on the computer is classic self–interruption. <i>Do a reality check</i>: after a few minutes of surfing the web ask yourself, ‘Should I be doing this now?’ </p><p>SoulFood: Ex 25–27, John 4:13–26, Ps 89:38–52, Prov 26:23–26 </p><p>THURSDAY OCTOBER 15</p><p lang="en-GB">‘The servant is not greater than his lord.’ John 13:16 KJV</p><p lang="en-GB">Information Overload! (2)</p><p lang="en-GB">When you’re constantly multi–tasking, important things can fall between the cracks. A lawyer who negotiated an unbelievable deal in favour of his client was asked how he did it. He replied, ‘I was the only person at the meeting that day who didn’t spend the whole time text messaging!’ A respected researcher says we’ve trained our brains ‘to constantly flit around the universe of messages and information, seeking brief hits of excitement. Grazing ceaselessly, we never dig too deeply before moving on to the next distraction…and it ratchets up our stress levels in ways we’re only starting to understand.’ Another expert says: ‘We get more information in 72 hours than our parents received in a month, and most people don’t have the skills to deal with it. They let new things in, but don’t get rid of old information they wanted to act on.’ </p><p lang="en-GB">When was the last time you enjoyed some relaxed, uninterrupted down time? Can you even remember? We’re so results–oriented that unless we’re doing something that can be quantified, we think it’s a waste of time. The fact is you <i>need</i> time away from the unrelenting onslaught of information to regroup, reflect and recharge. Jesus had a schedule to keep, people to minister to, disciples depending on Him, and a short time to do it all. Nevertheless, ‘<i>He withdrew…into the wilderness, and prayed.</i>’ (Luke 5:16 KJV) Now, since ‘<i>the servant is not greater than his lord</i>,’ do <i>you</i> think you’re above all that? Are you wiser than He? Or more spiritual? Jesus said, ‘<i>Come… apart…and rest a while</i>’ (Mark 6:31 KJV), because when you don’t come apart, you fall apart! </p><p>SoulFood: Ex 28–29, John 4:27–38, Ps 100, Prov 26:27–28 </p><p>FRIDAY OCTOBER 16</p><p>‘…People speak the things that are in their hearts.’ Luke 6:45 NCV</p><p>How’s Your Self–Talk These Days?</p><p>When John Roebling devised a plan to build a bridge between Manhattan and Brooklyn, experts thought it was impossible. They said a bridge spanning that distance couldn’t withstand the winds and tides. But Roebling refused to concede defeat; instead, he and his son, Washington, worked to solve the problems. Then just as construction was about to start, Roebling was killed in an underwater accident that left his son brain–damaged and unable to walk or talk. The prevailing wisdom was to abandon the project, but Washington Roebling was determined to fulfil his father’s dream. He developed a system of communication by touching a finger to his wife’s arm, and she in turn conveyed his ideas to the project engineers. For thirteen years that’s how he supervised construction—and in 1883 the first car drove across the Brooklyn Bridge. The ‘impossible’ had become reality! Are you facing a seemingly impossible situation at home, on the job, with your finances, or in a relationship? If so, what you tell yourself about it is important. Your self–talk sets you up for joy or misery. You can tell where your faith is by what comes out of your mouth: ‘<i>Good people bring good things out of the good they stored in their hearts</i>…’ (Luke 6:45 NCV) One pastor says: ‘When the pressure’s on, what comes out of your mouth lets you know if you need to make some adjustments… When you want something to show up in your outward man, deposit God’s Word in the inward man. Feed on it continually… once you believe it, you’ll find yourself saying it, and once you start saying it, your entire being will reflect the treasure of His Word inside.’</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 30–32, John 4:39–54, Ps 32, Prov 27:1–3 </p><p>SATURDAY OCTOBER 17</p><p>‘…to everyone who has, more will be given, but from the one who has not, even what he has will be taken away…’ Luke 19:26 ESV</p><p>Going Out on a Limb</p><p>Risk. Some people are naturally cautious and some revel in risk. Jon Walker says: ‘If God tells you to take a step of faith but you hesitate to take it until he shows you what the second step will be, you’re not waiting on God. He’s waiting on you.’ Patience is no excuse for hesitation. ‘God uses risks, large and small, to push us into a deeper faith. And so he wants us to step forward in faith, even if we don’t know where the second step will take us. The not knowing is what requires faith, and the not knowing compels us to rely on God to guide us forward.’</p><p>The Bible says, ‘<i>If you wait for perfect conditions, you’ll never get anything done</i>.’ (Ecclesiastes 11:4 TLB) Helen Keller said, ‘Security is mostly a superstition. It doesn’t exist in nature nor do the children of men as a whole experience it… Life is either a daring adventure, or nothing.’ If you want ‘more than you ever dreamed’, you’ve got to go out on a limb. That’s where the best fruit is. Acting in faith with no ‘earthly’ guarantee what’s on the other side means attempting something you couldn’t possibly do unless God gave you the ability. Jon Walker goes on: ‘Faith grows when we take risks—not just any kind of risks, but ones specifically directed by God. These God–nudges push us beyond the borders of our “independent states” into “the promised land” of life by faith.’ </p><p>SoulFood: Ex 33–35, John 5:1–15, Ps 87, Prov 27:4–6 </p><p>SUNDAY OCTOBER 18</p><p>‘Do all things without complaining…’ Philippians 2:14 NKJV</p><p>Stop Complaining (1)</p><p>A lady who worked at the post office was approached by a customer who said, ‘I can’t write. Would you mind addressing this postcard for me?’ After addressing it for him and writing a short message, the postal clerk asked, ‘Is there anything else I can do for you, sir?’ The man thought for a moment and said, ‘Yes, could you add a P.S. at the end saying, “Please excuse the sloppy handwriting.”’ Now, there’s gratitude for you! The Bible says, ‘<i>Do all things without complaining</i>’ because when you don’t, you end up hurting: (1) <i>Yourself</i>. Complaining leads to anger and depression. God loves you and He doesn’t want you hurting yourself. (2) <i>God</i>. Complaining calls into question God’s care, His character and His competence. In reality, what you’re saying is, ‘Lord, You blew it! You had a chance to fulfil my demands and You chose not to.’ (3) <i>Others</i>. Your words affect the people around you and nobody enjoys spending time with a member of ‘the cold–water bucket brigade’. Complaining temporarily satisfies our selfish nature, but it changes nothing. When you complain, you explain your pain for no gain. But here’s the good news: The Bible says, ‘…<i>the people became like those who complain of adversity</i>…’ (Numbers 11:1 NAS) You didn’t start out as a complainer; you ‘became’ that way, and by God’s grace you can become a thanks–giver! Once you acknowledge your habit of moaning and fault–finding, it becomes possible to choose a better one. A bad habit is like a nice soft bed; it’s easy to get into and hard to get out of. So if you’ve fallen into the habit of ‘complaining’—stop it!</p><p>SoulFood: Isa 61:1–9, Luke 4:16–30</p><p>MONDAY OCTOBER 19</p><p>‘…when the people complained, it displeased the Lord…’ Numbers 11:1 NKJV</p><p>Stop Complaining (2)</p><p>If you think complaining is no big deal, read this: ‘…<i>when the people complained…the Lord heard…and His anger was aroused. So the fire of the Lord burned among them, and consumed some in the outskirts of the camp</i>.’ A wise man once said, ‘I complained that I had no shoes, until I met a man who had no feet.’ God has blessed you in 101 different ways, and He doesn’t want to hear you whining. What were the Israelites grumbling about anyway? ‘<i>Adversity</i>’. For some of us adversity comes through illness. For others it’s a faltering career, not enough money to pay the bills, or a family situation that happened years ago and now you’re left shouldering the responsibility. Some of us made poor decisions earlier in life, and as a result our plans fell apart. Now we’re struggling with marital problems, blended families, and the consequences of our choices. We all have to deal with some level of adversity. We each have something in our life that God doesn’t want to hear us griping about! Understand this: it’s hard to live with adversity but, when you complain, you forego the grace that’ll get you through it. By choosing to complain and cling to the image of a perfect life, you forfeit the grace that’s available to you and will bring you victory. So change your way of thinking. Get down on your knees and pray: ‘Lord, I want the landscape of my life to be different; to experience the joy You give to those who leave the wilderness of ingratitude and move into the Promised Land of thanksgiving.’ That’s a prayer that will change you!</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 36–38, John 5:16–30, Ps 41, Prov 27:7–9</p><p>TUESDAY OCTOBER 20</p><p>‘…Naaman…went away in a rage.’ 2 Kings 5:12 NLT</p><p>Don’t Be Inflexible</p><p>As a general in the Syrian army, Naaman was accustomed to having things his own way. So when Elisha told him to dip seven times in the muddy Jordan River to be healed of leprosy, he ‘<i>went away in a rage</i>’. He said, ‘<i>I expected him to wave his hand over the leprosy and call on the name of the Lord his God and heal me!</i>’ (2 Kings 5:11 NLT) Fortunately, he listened to his servants, swallowed his pride and received a miracle. There are important lessons here. Since all progress calls for adapting to change and overcoming obstacles, ask yourself: (1) <i>What’s at the core of my fear and anger over this situation?</i> Am I afraid of the unknown and the changes it may bring? (2) <i>Am I being inflexible and trying to impose my will in this situation?</i> Am I willing to forfeit God’s perfect will by resisting a change He’s orchestrating? Many of us miss God’s best. Why? Like Naaman, we are accustomed to being waited on and having our ego stroked. E.G.O. means Edging God Out! Are you doing that? (3) <i>Am I being lazy or incompetent, not wanting to invest the necessary time and effort into the change?</i> Unless you’re willing to change, you won’t grow. And if you don’t grow, you won’t position yourself to receive the blessing God has in mind for you. Charles Franklin Kettering said, ‘The world hates change, yet it is the only thing that has brought progress.’ Today ask God for the emotional and spiritual strength to embrace the changes He’s bringing into your life, and to help you to see them as being for your good (Romans 8:28).</p><p>SoulFood: Ex 39–40, John 5:31–47, Ps 15, Prov 27:10–12</p><p>WEDNESDAY OCTOBER 21</p><p>‘A friend loves at all times, and a brother is born for a time of adversity.’ Proverbs 17:17 NIV</p><p>You Need Friends Who Encourage You</p><p>If you’re wise, you’ll surround yourself with people who support you emotionally and spiritually, and you can share your dreams and ideas with them. CS Lewis and JRR Tolkien were members of The Inklings, an informal literary discussion group associated with Oxford University. It was comprised of teachers, writers and friends who met regularly at a well–known Oxford pub to discuss passages from their favourite books as well as their own writings. In 1936, they decided the world needed more novels that had faith and morality as their central theme. Lewis and Tolkien decided to write science fiction after realising the inferior quality of similar stories being published at the time. They literally tossed a coin to decide who would write a book on space travel versus time travel. Tolkien got the time travel nod, but his early efforts with such a story never really worked out. Later, however, he achieved great success with <i>The Lord of The Rings</i>. Lewis wrote his famous series of novels called <i>The Space Trilogy</i>, and from that momentum he eventually penned <i>The Chronicles of Narnia</i>. Now, you may not reach that level of success, but you’ll go further with the encouragement of true friends than you will without it. So ask yourself what’s involved in cultivating the kinds of friendships that’ll help you fulfil your God–given potential. It may mean coming out of your shell and reaching out to others. Could you encounter hurt and rejection? Sure! But you’ll succeed only if you’re willing to take that chance.</p><p>SoulFood: Is 1–3, John 6:1–15, Ps 5, Prov 27:13–16 </p><p>THURSDAY OCTOBER 22</p><p>‘A tithe of everything…belongs to the Lord…’ Leviticus 27:30 NIV</p><p>Give God His Tithe (1)</p><p>If you put your mortgage before your gifts to God, you show more gratitude to your bank than you do to the One who made you. You say, ‘I earned it, so I own it.’ No. The Bible says, ‘<i>The earth is the Lord’s, and everything in it, the world, and all who live in it</i>.’ (Psalm 24:1 NIV) God owns every square metre of land on earth and every person who walks on it—including you. You’re not an owner, you’re a steward! And while a good steward deserves to be well rewarded by his master, his first priority is to please him and carry out his will. The Bible says, ‘<i>A tithe of everything… belongs to the Lord…</i>’ Get your thinking straight on this issue! In God’s eyes 10 per cent of your income is ‘dedicated funds’ to be used for one thing only—His purposes on the earth. Tithing isn’t how the church raises its budget; it’s how God raises His children. We distort God’s Word when we teach tithing as a means of getting money to pay off church debt, or as a substitute for other worn–out methods of fundraising, or as a cure–all for the church’s financial shortfalls. The Bible says, ‘…<i>son (daughter)… give Me your heart</i>…’ (Proverbs 23:26 NIV) When God has your heart’s deepest affection you’ll give gladly, not grudgingly. The first man in Scripture to tithe was Abraham. Why did he do it? Gratitude, because God had delivered him from the hand of an enemy who was out to destroy him. Has God delivered you? Has He blessed you? Then show your gratitude by giving Him His portion! </p><p>SoulFood: Is 4–7, John 6:16–24, Ps 126, Prov 27:17–19</p><p>FRIDAY OCTOBER 23</p><p>‘…I will give you a tenth.’ Genesis 28:22 NIV </p><p>Give God His Tithe (2)</p><p>Jacob wasn’t a giver by nature. Quite the opposite, in fact! He cheated his brother Esau out of his birthright, which entitled him to twice as much of their father’s inheritance. And when he worked for his father–in–law, Laban took advantage of him too. But one night Jacob met God in a life–changing dream, and when he woke the next morning he told God, ‘…<i>of all that You give me, I will give You a tenth</i>.’ Note, this was hundreds of years before the Law of Moses was instituted, which said, ‘<i>A tithe of everything…belongs to the Lord</i>…’ (Leviticus 27:30 NIV) Jacob wasn’t motivated by law, he was motivated by love for God. You can give without loving; some folks give under pressure, or to impress others or to get an income tax deduction. But you can’t love without giving! The Bible says, ‘<i>For God so loved the world, that He gave His only begotten Son</i>…’ (John 3:16 KJV) You’re never more like God than when you’re in the act of giving. Jesus said, ‘…<i>seek first the Kingdom of God, and His righteousness; and all these things shall be added to you</i>.’ (Matthew 6:33 NKJV) Tithing is about putting God and His Kingdom first. When self, home, business and pleasure come first in your life, your priorities are out of whack. Tithing reverses that order and puts God where He rightfully belongs—in first place. When God instructs you to tithe, He’s telling you to establish the habit of putting Him in the number one slot as a life principle. When you do, Jesus said ‘all these things’ you’re so concerned about will be ‘added to you’. </p><p>SoulFood: Is 8–11, John 6:25–34, Ps 85, Prov 27:20–22</p><p>SATURDAY OCTOBER 24</p><p>‘Bring the whole tithe into the storehouse…’ Malachi 3:10 NIV </p><p>Give God His Tithe (3)</p><p>When you honour the Lord in your business, He will bless your business. Imagine the advantage you’d have in the marketplace with God as your partner! Many famous Christian business people throughout history were faithful tithers, including Henry John Heinz of Heinz 57 Varieties, and William Colgate, the toothpaste magnate. Some of these people were so blessed that, before their lives were over, they gave God 90 per cent of their income and lived on the other 10 per cent. God says: ‘<i>Bring the whole tithe into the storehouse, that there may be food in My house. Test Me in this…and see if I will not throw open the floodgates of Heaven and pour out so much blessing that you will not have room enough to store it…all the nations will call you blessed…</i>’ (Malachi 3:10–12 NIV) When you demonstrate that God’s business means more to you than your own, He will prosper you. And He invites you to ‘test’ Him in this. How long have you known that you should tithe, wanted to tithe, said you were going to, and yet you’ve never got round to it? Start now—and start with what you have! What you can do now is the only influence you have over your future. John D Rockefeller is reputed to have made the following statement concerning the habit of tithing: ‘I never would’ve been able to tithe the first million dollars I made if I hadn’t tithed my first salary, which was a dollar fifty per week.’ Tithing demonstrates that you’ve conquered self–interest and the fear of lack. It’s a demonstration of faith—and God always rewards faith!</p><p>SoulFood: Is 12–16, John 6:35–51, Ps 98, Prov 27:23–24 </p><p>SUNDAY OCTOBER 25</p><p>‘…those who fear Him lack nothing.’ Psalm 34:9 NIV </p><p>Give God His Tithe (4)</p><p>There are three kinds of givers: the flint, the sponge and the honeycomb. To get even a spark from a flint you have to hammer it. To get anything out of a sponge you have to squeeze it. But a honeycomb just overflows with sweetness. Which kind of giver would you like to be? The Psalmist writes, ‘<i>Taste and see that the Lord is good; blessed is the man who takes refuge in Him…for those who fear Him lack nothing</i>.’ (Psalm 34:8–9 NIV) Tithing is an act of worship. Of the 100 to 110 hours you’re awake each week, one–third to one–half generally involve earning money. So when you give God your money, you’re giving Him your brain, your brawn and yourself. When you go to the Lord’s house on the Lord’s Day, partake of the Lord’s Supper and put the Lord’s tithe into the Lord’s treasury, it’s an act of profound worship. Now, let’s be clear: a God who paves Heaven’s streets with gold isn’t going to go broke because you don’t give Him a tithe of your income. The act of tithing isn’t about the tithe; it’s about the attitude of the tither to the Creator. It’s not about the gift; it’s about the attitude of the giver to the Giver. It’s not about the money; it’s about the attitude of the man or woman to the Maker. It’s not about possessions; it’s about the attitude of the loved ones to the Lover. As the songwriter Isaac Watts said, ‘Were the whole realm of nature mine; that were an offering far too small. Love so amazing, so divine, demands my soul, my life, my all.’</p><p>SoulFood: 2 Kings 6:8–23, Matt 5:43–48, Luke 6:27–36</p><p>MONDAY OCTOBER 26</p><p>‘Carry each other’s burdens…’ Galatians 6:2 NIV</p><p>Find People Who Believe in You</p><p>Mark Twain said, ‘Keep away from people who try to belittle your ambitions. Small people always do that, but the really great make you feel that you, too, can become great.’ Why does the Bible say, ‘Carry each other’s burdens’? Because one person can only carry a burden so far on their own. American novelist John Kennedy Toole quickly discovered that. As a young writer he worked alone writing a novel in New Orleans. When it was finished he sent it to publisher after publisher, but they all turned him down. Overcome by rejection, he took his own life. Some time after the funeral, his mother found a coffee–stained manuscript in the attic and took it to a professor at Louisiana State University who agreed to read it. Immediately he recognised its genius and recommended it to a major publisher. After its release, John Kennedy Toole’s novel, <i>A Confederacy of Dunces</i>, won a Pulitzer Prize and was heralded as one of the major novels of the twentieth century. If only he’d surrounded himself with friends who knew how to share his burden, encourage him when he faced rejection and motivate him to keep going, his life would have turned out very differently. So the word for you today is—‘Find people who believe in you.’ Encourage and support them, and welcome their support in return. Spend more time with those who sharpen you and make you better, and less time with those who drain your energy, time and talent. The truth is, friends who speak encouragement into your life are priceless. Their words are ‘<i>Like apples of gold in settings of silver</i>…’ (Proverbs 25:11 NIV)</p><p>SoulFood: Is 17–21, John 6:52–59, Ps 127, Prov 27:25–27</p><p>TUESDAY OCTOBER 27</p><p>‘…meditate on these things…and the God of peace will be with you.’ Philippians 4:8–9 NKJV</p><p>Always Keep a Good Attitude </p><p>When you’re going through bad times, your goal should be to keep a good attitude. And with God’s help you can. Dr Viktor Frankl, a Nazi Holocaust camp survivor, said: ‘If a prisoner felt that he could no longer endure the realities of camp life, he found a way out in his mental life—an invaluable opportunity to dwell in the spiritual domain, the one that the SS was unable to destroy. Spiritual life strengthened the prisoner, helped him to adapt, and thereby improved his chances of survival.’ Here is some practical advice on keeping a good attitude in bad times: (1) <i>Always believe the best about others, but don’t get bent out of shape when they disappoint you</i>. Nobody is perfect, including you. Just be grateful for the people that bring joy and endeavour to be counted among them. (2) <i>When you are tempted to retaliate, judge or become impatient, say to yourself, ‘This is an opportunity for me to model a great attitude for the glory of God.’</i> You say, ‘But this person is driving me crazy.’ Then refuse to be a ‘passenger’ and go along with them. Take back the wheel, get into the driver’s seat of your life, and determine which direction you’ll go and what attitude you’ll have. The Bible says: ‘…<i>whatever things are true, whatever things are noble, whatever things are just, whatever things are pure, whatever things are lovely, whatever things are of good report, if there is any virtue and if there is anything praiseworthy—meditate on these things…and the God of peace will be with you</i>.’</p><p>SoulFood: Is 22–25, John 6:60–71, Ps 114, Prov 28:1–4</p><p>WEDNESDAY OCTOBER 28</p><p>‘…perfect love expels all fear…’ 1 John 4:18 NLT</p><p>God’s Forgiveness, Mercy, and Grace (1)</p><p>God cares about you too much to leave you in any doubt about His love. The Bible says His ‘<i>perfect love expels all fear</i>.’ If God loved us with an imperfect love, we’d have cause to worry. Human love is flawed; it keeps a checklist of our sins and shortcomings—and consults it often. God keeps no such list. His love casts out our fear because it casts out our guilt. John writes, ‘…<i>if our heart condemns us, God is greater than our heart</i>…’ (1 John 3:20 NKJV) When you feel unforgiven, question your feelings but don’t question God. Go back to His Word; it outranks self–criticism and self–doubt. Nothing fosters confidence like a clear grasp of God’s grace, and nothing fosters fear like ignorance of it. The fact is if you haven’t accepted God’s grace, you’re doomed to live in fear. No pill, pep talk, psychiatrist or earthly possession can put your mind at ease. Those things may help numb your fear, but they can’t eradicate it. Only God’s grace can do that. Have you accepted Christ’s forgiveness? If not, get down on your knees and do it now. The Bible says, ‘<i>If we confess our sins, He is faithful and just to forgive us…and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness</i>.’ (1 John 1:9 NKJV) The place of confession is also the place of cleansing and restored confidence towards God. Your prayer can be as simple as this: ‘Lord, I admit I’ve turned away from You. Please forgive me. I place my soul in Your hands and my trust in Your grace. In Jesus’ name I pray. Amen.’ Now, having received God’s forgiveness, mercy and grace—live like it! </p><p>SoulFood: Is 26–29, John 7:1–13, Ps 104:1–23, Prov 28:5–8 </p><p>THURSDAY OCTOBER 29</p><p>‘Many are saying of me, “God will not deliver him.”’ Psalm 3:2 NIV </p><p>God’s Forgiveness, Mercy and Grace (2)</p><p>Regardless of how badly you have failed or how often you have failed—God won’t give up on you. So don’t give up on yourself! Nothing you’ve done is beyond the scope of His grace. Others may give up on you, but not God. King David fell as low as a person can get. He was guilty of adultery, deception and murder—all major offences. But God forgave and restored him. He writes about it in two psalms. In the first psalm he writes: ‘<i>Many are saying of me, God will not deliver him. But You, Lord, are a shield around me, O Lord; You bestow glory on me and lift up my head. To the Lord I cry aloud, and He answers me from His holy hill. I lie down and sleep; I wake again, because the Lord sustains me. I will not fear the tens of thousands drawn up against me on every side… From the Lord comes deliverance.’</i> (Psalm 3:2–7 NIV) Later on in the psalms he writes: ‘…<i>He turned to me and heard my cry. He lifted me out of the slimy pit, out of the mud and mire; He set my feet on a rock and gave me a firm place to stand. He put a new song in my mouth, a hymn of praise to our God. Many will see and fear the Lord and put their trust in Him</i>.’ (Psalm 40:1–3 NIV) And the God who turned David’s greatest mess into a message, and his greatest test into a testimony, will do the same for you when you turn to Him and receive His forgiveness, mercy and grace.</p><p>SoulFood: Is 30–33, John 7:14–24, Ps 104:24–35, Prov 28:9–12 </p><p>FRIDAY OCTOBER 30</p><p>‘…he who heeds rebuke gets understanding.’ Proverbs 15:32 NKJV</p><p>Acknowledge Your Mistakes</p><p>In spite of his faults, flaws and failures, God called David ‘…a man after My own heart…’ (Acts 13:22 NKJV) And one of the qualities that made David great was his willingness to acknowledge his mistakes. Here were two instances of it: (1) <i>When fleeing the wrath of King Saul, he sought the help of a certain priest</i>—a decision that caused Saul to order the death of eighty–five priests and their families. Devastated but not defensive, David told the surviving son of the slain priest who had assisted him, ‘…<i>I have caused the death of all your father’s family</i>.’ (1 Samuel 22:22 NLT) Can you imagine taking responsibility for such a tragic consequence? (2) <i>When the prophet Nathan confronted him about his affair with Bathsheba and his attempt to cover up her resulting pregnancy by having her husband killed, David acknowledged</i>, ‘…<i>I have sinned against the Lord</i>…’ (2 Samuel 12:13 NLT) Would you have the emotional and spiritual maturity to make such an admission? Or do you have a tendency to defend your actions for fear of being judged, criticised or rejected? Do you sometimes feel attacked when someone offers feedback, whether it is positive or negative? Do you retreat in silence? Do you counter–accuse or blame your attacker? Do you make hostile comments? Do you become sarcastic? Making mistakes doesn’t make you a lesser person, but defending them does. Don’t let pride rob you of the wisdom that comes from acknowledging your mistakes and ultimately growing through them. ‘<i>He who disdains instruction despises his own soul, but he who heeds rebuke gets understanding</i>.’</p><p>SoulFood: Is 34–37, John 7:25–32, Ps 9, Prov 28:13–16</p><p>SATURDAY OCTOBER 31</p><p>‘…as the clay is in the potter’s hand, so are you in My hand…’ Jeremiah 18:6 NKJV</p><p>Be Willing to Let God Mould You</p><p>Henry Poppen, one of China’s first missionaries, spent forty years telling its people about the love of Jesus and how He died to take away their sin. One day, after he had finished speaking, a man approached him and said, ‘We know this Jesus! He’s been here.’ Dr Poppen explained how that wasn’t possible because Jesus had lived and died long ago in a country far from China. ‘Oh no,’ the man insisted, ‘He died here. I can even show you his grave.’ He led Dr. Poppen outside the city to a cemetery where an American was buried. There, inscribed on a crumbling gravestone was the name of a medical doctor who felt called by God to live and die among the people of this remote Chinese village. And when its people heard Dr Poppen describe the attributes of Jesus—His mercy, His love, His kindness, His willingness to forgive—they remembered the missionary doctor. God will use you when you’re willing to become ‘<i>clay in the potter’s hand</i>’. Clay has no aspirations; it’s mouldable, pliable and completely subject to the potter’s will. Henry Blackaby says: ‘When God’s assignment demands humility, He finds a servant willing to be humbled. When it requires zeal, He looks for someone He can fill with His Spirit. God uses holy vessels, so He finds those who’ll allow Him to remove their impurities. It’s not a noble task being clay. There’s no glamour to it, nothing boast–worthy, except it’s exactly what God’s looking for.’</p><p>SoulFood (Halloween): Deut 18:9–18, Dan 2, Is 47:5–15, Acts 16:16–34 </p></body></html>