<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE j2xml PUBLIC "-//eshiol.it//DTD J2XML data file 1.5.6//EN" "http://www.eshiol.it/j2xml/1506/j2xml.dtd">
<j2xml version="1.5.6">
<content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2361]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Set Yourself Free from People Pleasing]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[set-yourself-free-from-people-pleasing]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...We ought to obey God rather than men.' Acts 5:29 KJV<br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150824.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>Too often our actions are dictated by a misguided need to please others. We care so much about what they think that with every step we take we look over our shoulder to see whether they’re smiling or frowning. Understand this: if you’re always looking for people’s approval, you’re not looking where you’re going and eventually you’ll hit a wall or trip over your own two feet. The Bible says, ‘…<em>We ought to obey God rather than men</em>.’ What do you think will happen if you open your mouth and stand up for yourself? The truth is that people who don’t respect your rights and honour your wishes are not worth your time or effort. Nor are they worthy of a long drawn–out discussion; just say goodbye! (We’re not talking about your marriage or children.) When the land became too small for the flocks of Abraham and Lot to graze together, strife broke out. Abraham loved his nephew Lot, but he realised he could no longer live in this situation. So he said, ‘…<em>Please separate from me. If you take the left, then I will go to the right; or, if you go to the right, then I will go to the left</em>.’ (Genesis 13:9 NKJV) How does their story end? Lot chose the best grazing land close to Sodom, and, as a result, everything he worked for went up in smoke. But Abraham, who always sought to please God, ended up not only being blessed himself, but being a blessing to the nations of the world. So the word for you today is—God wants to set you free from people pleasing. </p><br /><br />SoulFood: 2 Chr 22-24, Mark 8:14-26, Ps 119:129-136, Prov 22:8-10 <br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67641&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-23 15:12:23]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-23 15:12:23]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[set, you, free, from, people, pleasing, soulfood, chr, mark, prov]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...We ought to obey God rathe]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[101]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2360]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Dad, Equip Your Kids for the Real World! (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[dad-equip-your-kids-for-the-real-world-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...I am your spiritual father through the Gospel; that is why I implore you to follow [my] footsteps.' 1 Corinthians 4:15 PHPS<br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150823.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>Dad, do these three things for your kids: (1) <em>Alert them to the dangers of having a sense of entitlement</em>. Yes, they need parents who express unconditional love for them. But some of us think our kids can do no wrong—even when they do! Consequently they grow up having unrealistic expectations and a distorted view of how life works. Everybody gets a scorecard in life, and it records both our wins and our losses. Let your kids know that we all make mistakes. Failing to recognise that just makes them self–deceived and sets them up for heartache. Children learn from failure how to deal with disappointment; it prepares them for later life when things don’t go their way. (2) <em>Teach them the truth about death</em>—yours and theirs. The Bible says, ‘…<em>it is appointed unto men once to die</em>…’ (Hebrews 9:27 KJV) Let them know that death is universally ordained because of the sin of humanity. Tell them that life, however long, is a gift to be maximised, and Heaven is a family reunion not to be missed. The death of a friend or loved one can be an opportunity to diminish their fears and equip them to handle loss, grief and recovery. (3)<em> Show them why you married their mother</em>. It’s the most formative relationship in their early lives; one that will influence who they ultimately become, their choice of a partner, and their future happiness. When they see you loving their mother, treating her like a queen, and giving her consideration and honour, they’ll admire, appreciate, and emulate their awesome dad! </p><br /><br />SoulFood: Ex 17:8-16, 2 Cor 1:3-7 <br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67640&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-22 15:09:11]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-22 15:09:11]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[dad, soulfood, cor, the, word, for, today, authored, bob, and]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...I am your spiritual father]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[275]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2359]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Dad, Equip Your Kids for the Real World! (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[dad-equip-your-kids-for-the-real-world-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...To turn the hearts of the fathers back to the children...' Luke 1:17 NAS<br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150822.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>Research shows the results of the ‘dad deficit’. Too many children today are growing up without a father’s input. And as a result they end up making poor life, relationship and marriage choices. So how does a dad equip his kids for life in the real world? (1) K<em>now what they’re up to</em>. Get to know what makes them tick. Ask what subjects they enjoy in school, and which ones they’re struggling with. Learn who their friends are; who they spend time with at break and after school. Try to listen and learn. Take them out occasionally for breakfast or a ham-burger; they’ll feel like royalty spending one–to–one time with Dad! (2) <em>Teach them to stand tall</em>. A tragedy of their young world is the increasing suicide rate because of playground bullying. Teach your children to stand up for themselves. Teach them respect, and how to protect themselves by speaking up appropriately in class when they’re unclear about the lesson, or to courageously say what they believe. Teach them assertiveness in confronting unfair treatment. Kids who become ‘punch bags’ are set up to be victimised! (3) <em>Give them an example</em>. However accomplished your ‘preaching’ skills may be, you need to be ‘walking the walk’ in front of your children. You can tell them it’s important to be healthy and active, but if you’re a couch potato inhaling bags of chips and watching endless footy matches, they’re not convinced. Set an example by getting fit, pursuing a healthy lifestyle, activities and interests, and watch them think how ‘cool’ it is to be like Dad! </p><br /><br />SoulFood: 2 Chr 19-21, Mark 8:1-13, Ps 119:121-128, Prov 22:4-7 <br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67639&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-21 15:12:39]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-21 15:12:39]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[dad, deficit, too, many, children, today, are, growing, without, father]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...To turn the hearts of the ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[476]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2358]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Are You Trying To Make An Important Decision?]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[are-you-trying-to-make-an-important-decision]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...if...you lack wisdom, you should pray to God, who will give it to you; because God gives generously and graciously to all.' (James 1:5 GNT) <br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150821.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>If you are, here are some suggestions to help you. (1)<em> Don’t ask God to bless YOUR plans</em>, instead ask for HIS wisdom and direction! And remember, God will never tell you to do anything that doesn’t line up with what He’s already told you in His Word (Isaiah 8:20). (2) <em>Make sure your goal is to glorify God</em>. Sometimes that’s hard to know, for the worst pride often masquerades behind feigned humility. The human body is amazing—just pat a man on the back and so often his head begins to swell. But God opposes pride. (James 4:6) (3) <em>Use your brain</em>. God’s guidance transcends human reasoning, but it doesn’t exclude it. When God saves you, He doesn’t remove your mind, He renews it. (Romans 12:2) So pray, then put it to work. (4) <em>Seasons aren’t meant to be ignored</em>. If it isn’t God’s timing, wait! In the right season, the plan will be clear, the people you need will show up and the funds will be provided (Ecclesiastes 3:1). God has promised it, so trust Him! (5) <em>Seek trustworthy counsel</em>. Beware of those who patronise you for selfish reasons. Listen to those who value what you value and have been where you want to go (Proverbs 27:17). (6) <em>Never act without the facts</em>, but never limit God to them. When knowledge won’t take you another step, faith will carry you through, for that’s what connects you to the power of God. Now listen again ‘...<em>if...you lack wisdom, you should pray to God, who will give it to you; because God gives generously and graciously to all</em>.’ (James 1:5 GNT) </p><br /><br />SoulFood: 2 Chr 16-18, Mark 7:24-37, Ps 119:113-120, Prov 22:1-3 <br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67638&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-20 15:05:01]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-20 15:05:01]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[are, here, some, suggestions, help, you, don, ask, god, bless]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...if...you lack wisdom, you ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[755]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2357]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Install Your 'Cables' Now]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[install-your-cables-now]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['A prudent person foresees danger and takes precautions...' Proverbs 27:12 NLT<br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150820.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>Half Dome is a granite peak that towers above the valley floor in Yosemite National Park. Your final climb is between steel cables bolted to the rock; they were designed as handholds to safeguard and help you reach the top. Columnist Mary Hunt writes: ‘The final ascent up the sheer granite surface…is by far the most challenging. Once you see the cables you experience terror like you’ve never known… and you’ve no choice but to finish the trip. At that moment you’re thankful for cables that become the guardrails you need to pull yourself to the top. The secret to [continuing] when you feel like quitting is to erect ‘cables’ in your life before you need them so that when you face difficult situations, the help you need to make it will be there to protect you from your own fears and self–defeating attitudes.’ Solomon says, ‘<em>A prudent person foresees danger and takes precautions. The simpleton goes blindly on and suffers the consequences</em>.’ Sooner or later you’ll face a mountain you can’t conquer alone. And if the ‘cables’ you need are in place, you’ll conquer it. What are they? (1) <em>God’s Word</em>. Jeremiah said, ‘<em>Your words…sustain me</em>…’ (Jeremiah 15:16 TLB) Get into God’s Word, and get God’s Word into you. That way, when trouble comes you’ll be able to handle it. It’ll ‘...<em>guide you when you walk…guard you when you sleep…speak to you when you are awake</em>.’ (Proverbs 6:22 NCV) (2)<em> A strong prayer life</em>. ‘…<em>The earnest (heartfelt, continued) prayer of a righteous man makes tremendous power available [dynamic in its working]</em>…’ (James 5:16 AMP) Time spent with God changes you; it makes you more like Jesus and strengthens you for what lies ahead. </p><br /><br />SoulFood: 2 Chr 12-15, Mark 7:14-23, Ps 119:105-112, Prov 21:28-31 <br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67637&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-19 15:09:44]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-19 15:09:44]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[install, your, self, the, top, that, when, you, face, difficult]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['A prudent person foresees dan]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[641]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2356]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Get Rid of Your Scarcity Mentality]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[get-rid-of-your-scarcity-mentality]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...God will generously provide all you need...' 2 Corinthians 9:8 NLT<br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150819.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>‘…<em>God shall supply all your need according to His riches in glory</em>.’ (Philippians 4:19 NKJV) Whose riches? God’s! And His ability to bless you is not limited by the job market, the stock market or the housing market. For forty years He fed His people in the wilderness with manna from Heaven. He sent ravens to deliver meat to Elijah during a famine. He fed over five thousand people with a boy’s lunch. Paul writes, ‘<em>God will generously provide all you need. Then you will always have everything you need and plenty left over to share with others…Yes, you will be enriched in every way</em>…’ (2 Corinthians 9:8, 11 NLT) The scarcity attitude is rooted in fear and shows distrust of the awesome power of God to supply all our needs according to His unlimited resources. It’s based upon the faulty assumption that if someone else has something, you can’t have it because there’s only one pie, and every slice that someone else gets means less is available for you. It makes you believe that the blessings of others come at your expense. It says, ‘You win, I lose.’ That’s no way to live the abundant life! Start today to reprogramme your thinking. Remind yourself that you’re not in competition with anybody, for anything, in any area of your life. Cling to the words of Jesus: ‘…<em>I have come that [you] may have life, and that [you] may have it more abundantly.</em>’ (John 10:10 NKJV) Pray: ‘Father, help me to reject all thoughts of scarcity. Show me how to help others achieve their goals by sharing my time, talents, treasure. In Jesus’ name, I pray. Amen.’ </p><br /><br />SoulFood: 2 Chr 8-11, Mark 7:1-13, Ps 119:97-104, Prov 21:24-27 <br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67636&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-18 15:07:56]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-18 15:07:56]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[get, means, less, available, for, you, ion, with, anybody, anything]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...God will generously provid]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[897]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2355]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Jesus Loves You Unconditionally]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[jesus-loves-you-unconditionally]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...God so loved the world...' John 3:16 NKJV<br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150818.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>David said, ‘<em>Blessed is he whose transgression is forgiven, whose sin is covered</em>.’ (Psalm 32:1 NKJV) No matter how hard we worked, we could never pay off our sin debt. And thank God we don’t have to, because <em>‘God so loved the world, that He gave His only begotten Son, that whosoever believes in Him should not perish, but has everlasting life</em>.’ Years ago a congregation decided to honour one of its retired pastors. He was ninety–two, and some people wondered why the church even asked the elderly man to speak. After a warm welcome and introduction, he rose from his chair and walked with great dignity and effort to the pulpit. Leaning on the podium to steady himself, without notes of any kind, he began to speak: ‘When your pastor invited me here, he asked me to talk about the greatest lesson I’ve learned in fifty–plus years of preaching. I’ve thought about it for a few days, and boiled it down to the one thing that has made the most difference in my life and sustained me through all my trials. The one thing I can rely on when tears, heartbreak, pain, fear and sorrow paralyse me… the one thing that always comforts me: Jesus loves me! This I know, for the Bible tells me so. Little ones to Him belong. They are weak but He is strong. Yes, Jesus loves me. Yes, Jesus loves me. Yes, Jesus loves me. The Bible tells me so.’ You could hear a pin drop as the old man shuffled back to his seat. It’s something the congregation never forgot. And it’s something you should never forget either—Jesus loves you unconditionally. That’s so today, tomorrow, and forever! </p><br /><br />SoulFood: 2 Chr 5-7, Mark 6:45-56, Ps 119:89-96, Prov 21:20-23<br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67635&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-17 15:35:07]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-17 15:35:07]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[jesus, loves, this, know, for, the, bible, tells, little, ones]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...God so loved the world...']]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[796]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2353]]></id>
<title><![CDATA['Now' Faith]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[now-faith]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Now faith is the substance of things hoped for...' Hebrews 11:1 NKJV <br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150817.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>When you’re in the middle of a crisis, what you really believe manifests itself in your words, attitude and actions. When Lazarus died and his sister Martha said, ‘<em>Lord, if You had been here, my brother would not have died</em>’ (John 11:21 NCV), she was voicing past–tense faith. When Jesus said, ‘<em>[Lazarus] will…live again</em>’ (John 11:23 NCV) and she replied, ‘<em>I know that he will…live…in the resurrection…</em>’ (John 11:24 NCV), that was future–tense faith. And when she said, ‘…<em>Even now God will give You anything You ask</em>’ (John 11:22 NCV), she was demonstrating ‘now’ faith, which is present–tense. As believers, the Bible tells us not to ‘…l<em>ook at the things which are seen, but at the things which are not seen</em>…’ (2 Corinthians 4:18 NKJV) ‘Now’ faith stakes its claim on ‘<em>something…even if we do not see it</em>.’ (Hebrews 11:1 NCV) Paul says, ‘…<em>we walk by faith, not by sight.</em>’ (2 Corinthians 5:7 NKJV) Too often we base our feelings on what we see, instead of what God says in His Word. But as Jon Walker writes: ‘When we believe that reality is confined to what we see, we become trapped into thinking the only truth is what we see. We become prisoners of our own perceptions; we cease walking in faith… For those who walk by faith, appearances are never the ultimate reality… Reality extends beyond what you can see… the things we do not see are eternal [time and circumstance do not diminish or alter them] (2 Corinthians 4:18). Even though things may appear bad, God is working things out for our good (Romans 8:28). He knows how the story ends, so fix your eyes on the unseen and not on what you see.’ SoulFood: 2 Chr 1–4, Mark 6:30–44, Ps 119:81–88, Prov 21:17–19</p><br /><br /><br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67634&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-16 15:07:28]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-16 15:07:28]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[now, that, will, live, the, resurrection, john, ncv, was, future]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Now faith is the substance of]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[879]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2352]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Give It Your All]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[give-it-your-all]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...I will go...And if I perish, I perish.' Esther 4:16 NIV<br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150816.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>Esther, a Jewish girl married to a pagan king, risked death to break with long–standing tradition, marched into her husband’s throne room, spoke her mind, and rescued her people from annihilation. One girl saved a nation because she was willing to put everything on the line. Are you feeling inadequate today? Are you thinking, ‘Someone else should be doing this job instead of me’? Then read these words by clergyman Edward Everett Hale: ‘I am only one; but still I am one. I can’t do everything; but still I can do something: and because I can’t do everything, I will not refuse to do the something I can do.’ How many people did it take to rescue the dying man on the Jericho road? One Good Samaritan. How many people did it take to save the whole known world from the consequences of a seven–year famine? One man, Joseph. John Maxwell writes: ‘God has put a dream inside you. It’s yours and no one else’s. It declares your uniqueness. It holds your potential. Only you can give birth to it. Only you can live it. Not to discover it, take responsibility for it and act upon it is to negatively affect yourself as well as all those who would benefit from your dream.’ Poet John Greenleaf Whittier wrote, ‘For all sad words of tongue and pen; the saddest are these, “It might have been.”’ In your twilight years, will you look back and feel you’ve spent your life struggling to fulfil other people’s expectations? Or know that you lived to the fullest by striving to fulfil your God–given dream? Think about it now, while there’s still time to change direction. </p><br /><br />SoulFood: Jer 31:31-37, Heb 8:1-13 <br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67633&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-15 15:11:59]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-15 15:11:59]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[give, birth, only, you, can, live, not, discover, take, responsibility]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...I will go...And if I peris]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[985]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2351]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Wait (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[wait-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['I waited patiently for the Lord to help me...' Psalm 40:1 NLT<br /><br /><hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /><br /><br /><br />http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150815.mp3<br /><br /><br /><p>The Psalmist said: ‘<em>I waited patiently for the Lord to help me, and He turned to me and heard my cry. He lifted me out of the pit of despair…He set my feet on solid ground and steadied me as I walked along. He has given me a new song to sing, a hymn of praise to our God. Many will see what He has done and be amazed</em>.’ (Psalm 40: NLT) Waiting means trusting that God knows what He’s doing, even when He doesn’t give you all the details. Perhaps you’re single and looking for someone to share your life with. Maybe there’s a relationship at your fingertips, but you know it wouldn’t be pleasing to God. It isn’t the right person, because he or she doesn’t share your values, goals, or commitment to Christ. Maybe they’re putting pressure on you to get involved sexually even though you’re not married. Sampling the product before you buy may be the world’s way, but you know it’s not God’s way. Still you’re tempted to think, ‘I’m tired of waiting. I’m going to reach for whatever satisfaction I can get and worry about the consequences later.’ Samson did that and ended up losing his sight, his strength, his reputation, his freedom and his life. Hold out for God’s best! Pray: ‘Lord, I don’t want to get involved in any relationship that I know would dishonour You, hurt me, and bring pain to the lives of others. You said the plans You have for me are good. So even though I sometimes feel no one understands how hard it is, I’ll trust in You and wait patiently.’ </p><br /><br />SoulFood: 1 Chr 26:20-29:30, Mark 6:14-29, Ps 119:73-80, Prov 21:14-16 <br /><br /><small><em>The Word for Today</em> is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015</small><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67632&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-14 15:05:40]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-14 15:05:40]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[wait, patiently, for, the, lord, help, psalm, nlthttp, lthttp, www]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['I waited patiently for the Lo]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1043]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><section mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[10]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[The Word for Today]]></title>
<name><![CDATA[]]></name>
<alias><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></alias>
<image><![CDATA[]]></image>
<scope><![CDATA[content]]></scope>
<image_position><![CDATA[left]]></image_position>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
<published><![CDATA[1]]></published>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<ordering><![CDATA[10]]></ordering>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<params><![CDATA[]]></params>
</section><category mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[34]]></id>
<parent_id><![CDATA[0]]></parent_id>
<title><![CDATA[Devotional]]></title>
<name><![CDATA[]]></name>
<alias><![CDATA[devotional]]></alias>
<image><![CDATA[]]></image>
<image_position><![CDATA[left]]></image_position>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
<published><![CDATA[1]]></published>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<ordering><![CDATA[1]]></ordering>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<params><![CDATA[]]></params>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
</category><user mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[77]]></id>
<name><![CDATA[Bob Gass]]></name>
<username><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></username>
<email><![CDATA[skip.parker@rbg.co.nz]]></email>
<password><![CDATA[c9fdc2928775a20cdf4c882e2660a530:8gj3gG1oaxo5gPlmcPnluVotFk04AZZN]]></password>
<usertype><![CDATA[Super Administrator]]></usertype>
<block><![CDATA[0]]></block>
<sendEmail><![CDATA[0]]></sendEmail>
<gid><![CDATA[25]]></gid>
<registerDate><![CDATA[2010-07-14 07:23:31]]></registerDate>
<lastvisitDate><![CDATA[2012-12-13 01:57:21]]></lastvisitDate>
<activation><![CDATA[]]></activation>
<params><![CDATA[admin_language=
language=
editor=
helpsite=
timezone=12

]]></params>
</user></j2xml>