<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" lang="en-GB"><head><title>WFT NDJ 15/16</title><meta content="Ellen Glass" name="author"/><meta content="2015-09-03T02:43:00Z" name="dcterms.created"/><meta content="2015-09-29T10:39:00Z" name="dcterms.modified"/><meta content="Ellen Glass Graphic Design" name="dcterms.publisher"/><meta content="XMLmind Word To XML Professional Edition 1.0.0-beta04" name="generator"/></head><body><p>SUNDAY 1 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Commit your actions to the Lord, and your plans will succeed.’ Proverbs 16:3 NLT</p><p>Never, Never Quit!</p><p>The moment you start believing you’re successful enough to rest on your laurels, you’re in trouble. You’ve put a lid on your growth! Solomon wrote, ‘<i>Do you know a hard-working man? He shall be successful and stand before kings!</i>’ (Proverbs 22:29 TLB) Success is always a possibility, but never a guarantee. It belongs to the man or woman who’s willing to show up early, stay late, go the extra mile, and keep asking, ‘Is there a better way?’ An agency once created an ad for an automobile company. It said, ‘At sixty miles an hour the loudest noise in this new Rolls-Royce comes from the electric clock.’ When they ran the ad by the company’s CEO, he smiled and said, ‘I guess we’ve got to do something about that clock!’ A young man once asked Henry Ford, ‘How can I make a name for myself and be successful?’ He replied, ‘Decide what you want, then stick with it. Never deviate from your course no matter how long it takes or how hard the road, until you’ve accomplished your purpose.’ Successful people have one thing in common: they refuse to quit! No matter how many times they fall, they get back up, dust themselves off, learn from it, and start over. Paul J. Meyer says, ‘Ninety-nine per cent of those who fail are not actually defeated, they simply quit.’ The Bible says, ‘<i>And let us not grow weary of doing good, for in due season we will reap, if we do not give up.</i>’ (Galatians 6:9 ESV) The only people who never fail are those who never try. So keep going, and don’t even think about quitting!</p><h2>SoulFood: Heb 11:4–12:3, 1 Chron 17:1–20, Ps 18:20–29</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 2 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Husbands… be considerate.’ 1 Peter 3:7 NIV</p><p>‘Wives… be…worthy of respect.’ 1 Timothy 3:11 NIV</p><p>Strengthen Your Marriage</p><p>A couple celebrating their fiftieth wedding anniversary was asked the secret to their success. The husband replied, ‘The day we got married we agreed that if an argument arose I’d go out and stand on the porch until I cooled off. And it worked like a charm; fifty years of being outdoors in all that fresh air was exactly what this relationship needed!’ If you’ve been spending too much time out on the porch, here are three ways to strengthen your marriage: (1) Commitment— ‘You’re first.’ Speaking those words on special occasions is easy, but you need to speak them seven days a week. A film star who’d been through several failed marriages told an interviewer, ‘I’ve given up trying to find the right person. Now I’m working at becoming the right person.’ That formula always works! (2) Concern— ‘What do you need?’ Husbands and wives are as different as chalk and cheese. And to complicate things further, their needs change according to the season of life they’re in. So when you ask, ‘How are you today?’ slow down and listen. Your wife may not want you to solve the problem, but to share it. Closeness in marriage isn’t an accident: it’s a decision you make, and keep making every day. (3) Coping— ‘We can work it out.’ Marriage may alleviate the problem of loneliness, but it presents the challenge of getting along with another person. It teaches you that you can’t always avoid conflict, but you can make it work for you. The truth is, unless there are two winners in a marriage, there are none at all. </p><h2>SoulFood: Is 38–41, John 7:33–44, Ps 96, Prov 28:17–20</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 3 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘I will…remember their sins no more.’ Hebrews 8:12 NIV</p><p>You’ve Been Forgiven, So Live Like It!</p><p>When an accusing voice confronts you with your past, respond in the manner Jesus did—It is written: ‘<i>I will… remember their sins no more</i>.’ It’s not that God’s forgetful; it’s that He chooses not to remember your sins. And when you choose otherwise, you question His forgiveness, allow the enemy to guilt-trip you, and forfeit the confidence you need to receive what God has promised you (See 1 John 3:21–22). When you keep rehearsing your past you not only keep it alive, you empower it. What you keep on deposit, you’re more likely to withdraw and act on in a moment of weakness. Just as nobody knows when a dormant volcano may erupt, you can’t predict when an unresolved issue will resurface, turning your words into hot coals and your behaviour into a blaze of destruction. Only by the power of God’s forgiveness, and by forgiving others, is the hold your past has over you broken. Shame isn’t a blessing; it’s a weight Jesus bore for you on the cross. So set it down and walk away! God’s Word says, ‘<i>As far as the east is from the west, so far has He removed our transgressions from us</i>.’ (Psalm 103:12 NKJV) Notice, there’s a North Pole and a South Pole, but no east or west pole. Why? Because that distance is infinite and beyond measure. Are you getting the idea? Whenever you are reminded of past sin, the enemy hopes you’re ignorant of the truth in order to rob you of your future. Don’t take the bait! Instead look to the cross of Christ, refuse to dwell on it further, and keep moving forward.</p><h2>SoulFood: Is 42–44, John 7:45–53, Ps 86, Prov 28:21–24</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 4 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘If you love someone, you will…always believe in him.’ 1 Corinthians 13:7 TLB</p><p>Don’t Be Cynical</p><p>There are very few monuments erected to sceptics. That’s because instead of building people up, they tear them down. David’s older brother Eliab was like that. Here’s his story. When nobody else in Saul’s army, including Eliab—who was a general—was willing to take on Goliath, David volunteered to go out and fight this ‘<i>uncircumcised Philistine</i>.’ (1 Samuel 17:36 KJV) In Bible times circumcision was a sign of God’s covenant of protection and provision for the Israelites. And David knew this bully had no such relationship with God; only the Israelites could claim such a benefit. As a result, David was very secure in the covenant, and embraced God’s promise. Obviously this wasn’t the case for Eliab. His ‘<i>anger burned against David and he said: “Why have you come down? And with whom have you left those few sheep in the wilderness? I know your insolence and the wickedness of your heart; for you have come down in order to see the battle.”</i>’ (1 Samuel 17:28 NAS) Interestingly, the name Eliab means ‘God is my Father’, so Eliab not only represents secular cynics, but Christian ones too. Yes, we have them in the Church! All it takes is one sceptical member and soon all those with weaker faith, or no faith at all, start chiming in and perpetuating the negativity. Beware: cynicism can wreak havoc in any relationship and environment. That’s why the Bible says, ‘<i>How blessed is the man who does not... sit in the seat of scoffers</i>.’ (Psalm 1:1 NAS) Think twice before sitting down in that seat. If you stay there too long you may not be able to get up again!</p><h2>SoulFood: Is 45–48, John 8:1–11, Ps 30, Prov 28:25–28</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 5 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Seek first the Kingdom of God.’ Matthew 6:33 NKJV</p><p>Your Quiet Time with God (1)</p><p>Jesus said, ‘<i>Seek first the Kingdom of God and His righteousness, and all these things shall be added to you</i>.’ What kind of ‘<i>things</i>’ was He talking about? Things like money, houses, relationships, health and jobs. What did He mean by ‘<i>the Kingdom of God</i>’? Living under the rule of Christ each moment and submitting to His will in all things. When Jesus used the word ‘seek’, He called for three things: (1) Intentionality. When something important is lost, you must put aside other things and seek until you find it. (2) Importance. Position, performance, prosperity, and popularity can be good things when properly used. But without the rule of Christ in your life, you’ll always be vulnerable to the devil. (3) Importunity. No matter how long it takes, how hard you must work, or what you must rearrange, restore your quiet time with God to its rightful place. The psalmist wrote, ‘<i>When You said, “Seek My face,” My heart said to You, “Your face, Lord, I will seek.”</i>’ (Psalm 27:8 NKJV) ‘Quiet time’ has been called many things throughout the history of the Church: morning watch, daily devotions, appointment with God or personal devotional time. It really doesn’t matter what you call it, as long as you have it regularly. Your quiet time with God is just daily fellowship with Him through His Word and prayer. It’s a time you deliberately set aside to meet with Him. The goal is that you might grow in your personal relationship with God so that you can know Him, love Him, serve Him and become more like Him.</p><h2>SoulFood: Is 49–52, John 8:12–20, Ps 123, Prov 29:1–3</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 6 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘...it is for Your pleasure that they exist and were created.’ Revelation 4:11 NLT </p><p>Your Quiet Time with God (2)</p><p>Did you know: (1) God created you for<i> His own pleasure and His greater glory.</i> He also saved you <i>‘both to will and to work for His good pleasure.’</i> (Philippians 2:13 ESV) Your attitude towards quiet time with God will be transformed when you realise this. Time spent with God brings Him great pleasure, honour and glory. He waits for you and welcomes you into His presence—He knows how much benefit you will receive from Him. (2) The cross is what made this relationship possible. When Adam sinned, God drove him from the Garden of Eden and placed angels with swords at its entrance so that mankind could never re-enter. Then God did something truly amazing; He took on human form, lived among us, died in our place, and was cut down by the sword of divine judgment at the cross, providing us with a way back into His presence. Wonderful, isn’t it? In the Old Testament only one man, the high priest, could go into the Holy of Holies. And he could only do it one day a year. A thick veil separated God from the people. They stood outside wondering what God’s voice sounded like, what His presence felt like and what His glory looked like. Only the high priest knew. But when Jesus cried, ‘<i>It is finished!</i>’ (John 19:30 NKJV), the Bible says, ‘<i>The veil of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom</i>.’ (Mark 15:38 NKJV) Now, as ‘<i>priests unto God</i>’ we can come into His presence at any time and meet with Him (Revelation 1:6 KJV). What a privilege! Grace makes it possible. And gratitude should be the magnet that draws you there each day.</p><h2>SoulFood: Is 53–57, John 8:21–30, Ps 15, Prov 29:4–6</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 7 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘He went out into the mountains to pray, and prayed all night.’ Luke 6:12 TLB</p><p>Your Quiet Time with God (3)</p><p>Why do you need a quiet time with God each day? Because Jesus did, and He’s your example: ‘<i>He was up long before daybreak and went…to pray</i>.’ (Mark 1:35 TLB) The truth is, we make time for what we value most, for the people we love most, for our highest priorities, and what we find most rewarding. Notice, Jesus seldom prayed for anybody in public. Why? Because He’d already done His praying before He got there! He made deposits each morning so that He could make withdrawals all day long. And the busier He got, the more He prayed. Did He know something we don’t? Jesus had no difficulty choosing between the crowd’s agenda and His Father’s will. ‘<i>I can do nothing on My own. I judge as God tells Me. Therefore, My judgment is just, because I carry out the will of the One who sent Me.</i>’ (John 5:30 NLT) Why do spiritual leaders sometimes fall? Because they get caught up in the work of the Lord and neglect their relationship with Him. Throughout history, anyone who has been greatly used by God was a person of prayer. Martin Luther said, ‘I have so much to do that I must spend the first three hours each day in prayer.’ Ceaseless activity will drain you and leave you vulnerable to Satan’s attack. The sign on a church bulletin board says it all: ‘Seven prayerless days make one weak Christian.’ So the busier you become, the more time you need to spend with God. Simply stated: if you’re too busy to have a quiet time with God, you’re too busy! </p><h2>SoulFood: Is 58–62, John 8:31–41, Ps 115, Prov 29:7–10</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 8 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘I have…treasured His words more than daily food.’ Job 23:12 NLT</p><p>Your Quiet Time with God (4)</p><p>Your quiet time with God is more than just a good idea, it’s vital to your spiritual survival. It’s also essential to your spiritual growth and maturity. You say, ‘But I go to church every week.’ Can you imagine what would happen if you ate only once a week? The patriarch Job said, ‘<i>I have…treasured His words more than daily food</i>.’ Peter described the Scriptures as nourishing milk (1 Peter 2:2), and the writer to the Hebrews called the Word of God solid food (Hebrews 5:14). Your quiet time is also like a spiritual bath. Jesus said, ‘<span lang="en-US">You are already clean because of the Word which I have spoken to you.</span>’ (John 15:3 NKJV) You shower every day to stay clean and avoid body odours. It’s not easy to be around someone who smells badly, and you run the risk of offending them by telling them so. But if you love them you’ll do it. Paul describes the Christian as: <i>‘...the aroma of Christ to God.’ </i>(2 Corinthians 2:15 ESV) Here’s the bottom line. Unless you protect your quiet time with God: (1) you’ll be cut off from your source of strength, guidance, and wisdom; (2) your usefulness to God will be limited; (3) you’ll be inconsistent in your Christian life. You say, ‘But I don’t have time!’ You have the same 168 hours each week that everybody else has! And how you spend them is determined by what you think is most important. So if you think being in fellowship with God is important, begin to make time for it. </p><h2>SoulFood: 2 Kings 6:1–7, Matt 14:22–33 </h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 9 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘I am humble and gentle at heart, and you will find rest for your souls.’ Matthew 11:29 NLT</p><p>Be Gentle</p><p>Jesus said, ‘I am humble and gentle at heart, and you will find rest for your souls.’ We’d all be a lot better off if people like Jesus ran the world, because those who aren’t gentle are making a real mess of things! Francis de Sales said, ‘Nothing is so strong as gentleness, and nothing so gentle as real strength.’ Just as you catch more flies with honey than with vinegar, people respond more readily to gentleness than aggressiveness. The famous football coach, John Wooden, told the following story: ‘My dad, Joshua Wooden, was a strong man in one sense, but a gentle man. He could lift heavy things men half his age couldn’t, but he would also read poetry to us each night after a day working in the fields raising corn, hay, wheat, tomatoes, and watermelons. We had a team of mules named Jack and Kate on our farm. Kate would often get stubborn and lie down on me when I was ploughing. I couldn’t get her up no matter how roughly I treated her. Dad would see my predicament and walk across the field until he got close enough to say, “Kate.” Then she would get up and start working again. He never touched her in anger. It took me a long time to understand that even a stubborn mule responds to gentleness.’ When the Bible speaks of humility and meekness, it’s not speaking of weakness. Meekness means ‘power under control’. An unbroken horse is useless; an overdose of medicine kills rather than cures; wind out of control destroys everything in its path. Jesus was powerful but He was gentle. And you are called to follow in His footsteps (1 Peter 2:21). </p><h2>SoulFood: Is 63–66, John 8:42–59, Ps 99, Prov 29:11–14</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 10 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘...let God transform you...by changing the way you think.’ Romans 12:2 NLT</p><p>Through Christ, You Can Conquer Your Habit</p><p>Let’s say you’re trying to lose weight, but you love doughnuts. How can you overcome temptation? By repeating, ‘I must not eat doughnuts, I must not eat doughnuts, I must not eat doughnuts’? No, the more you think about doughnuts, the more you’re going to want them. Instead you must focus on something else (or someone else—Jesus!) who can help you overcome the temptation. Your problem is not in the doughnut shop, it’s in your mind. That’s where victory is won or lost. Paul writes: ‘<i>Dear brothers and sisters, I plead with you to give your bodies to God because of all He has done for you. Let them be a living and holy sacrifice—the kind He will find acceptable. This is truly the way to worship Him. Don’t copy the behaviour and customs of this world, but let God transform you into a new person by changing the way you think. Then you will learn to know God’s will for you, which is good and pleasing and perfect</i>.’ (Romans 12:1–2 NLT) You can lock yourself up in a room and still think about doughnuts. On the other hand, you can get your mind on Jesus, draw strength from Him, and drive victoriously past every doughnut shop in town. The same principle applies to any habit you want to break and any sin you want to conquer. Does victory come easily or overnight? No, Satan tempted Jesus repeatedly in the wilderness, and he’ll keep tempting you until he realises his strategies no longer work. ‘<i>Then the devil left Him, and behold, angels came and ministered to Him.</i>’ (Matthew 4:11 NKJV) Through Christ, you can conquer your habit.</p><h2>SoulFood: Rom 1:1–3:20, John 9:1–12, Ps 133, Prov 29:15–18</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 11 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘You meant evil…but God meant it for good.’ Genesis 50:20 NKJV</p><p>You Won’t Talk About It </p><p>Twenty-two years after selling Joseph into slavery, his brothers now stand before him as prime minister of Egypt. They don’t recognise him, and he holds their fate in his hands. If you’d been in his shoes, what would you have done? Got even? Reminded them of their past offences? For the next few days, let’s look at what Joseph did: he kept it to himself. ‘<i>There was no one with Joseph when he made himself known to his brothers.</i>’ (Genesis 45:1 NIV) Joseph made sure no one in Egypt would ever know what they’d done to him. And isn’t that how God treats us? The fact is He has enough on each of us to bury us, yet He refuses to resurrect our past sins. So why do we? To punish! ‘<i>Perfect love drives out fear, because fear has to do with punishment.</i>’ (1 John 4:18 NIV) What are we afraid of? That they’ll get away with it. We want them punished, so we tell everybody what happened. And when we do: (1)<i> We play God!</i> God says, ‘<i>Vengeance is mine; I will repay</i>.’ (Romans 12:19 KJV) He alone knows the weakness in your offenders that caused them to hurt you, and whether they’ve repented and changed. (2)<i> We set the standard by which we ourselves will be judged.</i> ‘<i>You will be judged in the same way that you judge others.</i>’ (Matthew 7:2 NCV) If that’s a truth you’re not comfortable with: ‘<i>Get rid of all bitterness…Instead, be kind to each other, tenderhearted, forgiving one another, just as God…has forgiven you</i>.’ (Ephesians 4:31–32 NLT) When you’ve been wronged, ‘forgive and forbear’ is the right response!</p><h2>SoulFood: Rom 3:21–6:23, John 9:13–23, Ps 83:1–8, Prov 29:19–22</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 12 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘You did not receive a spirit…to fear, but…of sonship.’ Romans 8:15 NIV </p><p>You Won’t Try to Intimidate Them</p><p>Joseph’s brothers ‘<i>were…stunned with surprise. “Come over here,” he said. So they came closer. And he said again, “I am Joseph, your brother whom you sold into Egypt! But don’t be angry with yourselves that you did this to me, for God did it!”</i>’ (Genesis 45:3–5 TLB) You’ll notice that Joseph didn’t react the way we so often do when someone hurts us. He didn’t: (1) distance his brothers; (2) enjoy watching them squirm; (3) practise one-upmanship; (4) gloat and say ‘gotcha!’; (5) remind them of how they’d put him down and despised his dreams; (6) demand they acknowledge that he was right and they were wrong; (7) say, ‘I told you so!’ No, Joseph knew at the heart of the matter was God’s sovereign purposes being accomplished—even through the evil deeds of his brothers. Having the right view of God’s providence freed Joseph and allowed him to seek love from his brothers, not fear—restoration in place of revenge. He knew the long-term benefits of healing a relationship far outweighed any short-term satisfaction you get from retaliation. The Bible also says, ‘<i>You did not receive a spirit…to fear, but…the Spirit of sonship. And by him we cry, “Abba, Father.”</i>’ The word ‘Abba’ is a term of endearment which means ‘Daddy’. God doesn’t bring up your past, or keep you at arm’s length because of your failures. He wants you to know you can come to Him at any time, know that you’re accepted, feel secure in His presence, and call Him ‘Daddy’. And that’s the kind of love He wants you to show to others—a love that doesn’t want them to feel afraid in your presence. </p><h2>SoulFood: Rom 7:1–9:16, John 9:24–41, Ps 83:9–18, Prov 29:23–27</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 13 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Don’t be angry with yourselves.’ Genesis 45:5 TLB </p><p>You Won’t Lay a Guilt Trip on Them</p><p>Joseph told his brothers, ‘<i>Don’t be angry with yourselves that you did this to me…God has sent me here to keep you and your families alive, so that you will become a great nation</i>.’ (Genesis 45:5–7 TLB) When are we most likely to lay a guilt trip on others? When we’ve forgotten the grace we ourselves received from God. A right perspective on God’s providence helps us realise that <i>‘for those who love God, all things work together for good, for those... called according to His purpose.’ </i>(Romans 8:28 ESV) Often we forget the grace and forgiveness God extends to us, expecting us to forgive others in turn! Paul wrote, ‘<i>I…wasted [the Church].</i>’ (Galatians 1:13 KJV) He uses a mafia term for killing people. Now he goes back to those same towns and preaches, and who’s in the audience? The widows and orphans! If Paul hadn’t learned to receive God’s grace he could never have fulfilled God’s will. Some ancient societies punished murderers by strapping the victim to their back. Paul may have had this in mind when he wrote, ‘<i>Who will deliver me from this body of death?</i>’ (Romans 7:24 NKJV) Nothing is heavier than unresolved guilt. It will: (1) <i>Drag you down</i>. (2) <i>Cause you to leave a bad taste wherever you go</i>. Even your friends will become exhausted and say, ‘Get over it.’ (3) <i>Destroy your relationships</i>. Who wants to be around someone who’s obsessed with a corpse? You’d only be using the new relationship to numb the pain of the old one. (4) <i>Destroy your health, because you aren’t built to carry resentment</i>. Cut it loose! Somebody said, ‘Everyone should have a special cemetery lot in which to bury the faults of friends and loved ones.’ Grieve if you need to—then bury it and move on! </p><h2>SoulFood: Rom 9:17–11:36, John 10:1–10, Ps 20, Prov 30:1–4</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 14 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Be full of love for others.’ Ephesians 5:2 TLB </p><p>You’ll Preserve Their Dignity and Self-Worth</p><p>Imagine how Joseph’s brothers felt when he said, ‘<i>It was not you who sent me here, but God.</i>’ (Genesis 45:8 NKVJ) Is he serious? God did it? This is a new level of forgiveness! When we recognise the hand of God in our lives we see He wants us to preserve the dignity and self-worth of others because He’s already done it for us! With full knowledge of our sinful past, He covers us with the garment of grace. And He expects us to do the same for others. As you read the genealogy of Jesus in Matthew chapter one, you might think the sin of adultery between David and Bathsheba was part of the divine strategy all along. No, sin never is, and David paid a high price. Yet the Bible records these events as though they were supposed to have happened in just that way. The Bible says, ‘<i>Be full of love for others, following the example of Christ who loved you and gave Himself to God as a sacrifice to take away your sins. And God was pleased</i>.’ (Ephesians 5:2 TLB) When you truly forgive, there’s no place for self-righteousness. You’re able to forgive because: (1) you remember what you yourself have been forgiven of; (2) you acknowledge what you’re capable of; (3) you see God’s hand at work in the bigger picture. Joseph wasn’t being condescending or patronising, nor was he thinking, ‘I’ll be admired for being so gracious.’ No, during his years in prison God had moved on his heart and changed his attitude. So when Joseph said, ‘<i>You meant evil against me; but God meant it for good</i>’ (Genesis 50:20 NKJV), he really meant it! That kind of response takes forgiveness to a whole new level!</p><h2>SoulFood: Rom 12–14, John 10:11–21, Ps 8, Prov 30:5–6 </h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 15 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘You shall be near to me…and…I will provide for you.’ Genesis 45:10–11 NKJV</p><p>You’ll Protect Them</p><p>Not only did Joseph forgive his brothers, he protected them from their worst nightmare—having to go back and tell their ageing father what they’d done twenty-two years earlier. Joseph is a step ahead of them; he tells them what to say and what not to say: ‘<i>Go up to my father, and say to him, “Thus says your son Joseph: ‘God has made me lord of all Egypt; come…You shall dwell in the land of Goshen, and you shall be near to me, you and your children…I will provide for you.’”</i>’ (Genesis 45:9–11 NKJV) You say, ‘I think they should have been forced to confess what they’d done.’ No, that would have given their father, Jacob, an even greater burden to bear—struggling with regret over his lost years with Joseph, not to mention having to fight bitterness towards his other sons. Joseph was wise. And it made his brothers respect him all the more. There’s a big difference between confessing and ‘dumping’. Irreparable damage can be done when you try to get relief by dumping the details of your guilt on somebody who can’t handle them. Sometimes confessing is the proper route, but only after talking with an experienced counsellor. After David sinned with Bathsheba he wrote, ‘<i>Against You [God], You only, have I sinned</i>.’ (Psalm 51:4 NKJV) When you consider that God knows all about your sin yet promises to keep it a closely guarded secret, it should: (1) increase your sense of humility and gratitude; (2) cause you to keep your mouth shut; (3) make you refuse to hold anybody else’s sins and shortcomings over their head. </p><h2>SoulFood: 2 Kings 5:1–27, Matt 6:19–34, Acts 5:1–11</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 16 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘He spoke very kindly to them, reassuring them.’ Genesis 50:21 TLB </p><p>You’ll Walk in Forgiveness</p><p>Seventeen years after being reunited with Joseph, his long lost son, Jacob died and Joseph’s brothers panicked. They started to think, ‘<i>Now Joseph will pay us back for all the evil we did to him.</i>’ (Genesis 50:15 TLB) So they got together, made up a story, and sent word to Joseph, saying, ‘<i>Before your father died, he instructed us to say to you: “Please forgive your brothers for the great wrong they did to you.”</i>’ (Genesis 50:16–17 NLT) Now think about it. If their father really had said this, he wouldn’t have told Joseph’s brothers, he’d have told Joseph himself, right? He wouldn’t have gone to his grave with the fear that Joseph might exact revenge. When Joseph heard that his brothers doubted his forgiveness he called them together and wept, saying, ‘<i>“Don’t be afraid…I myself will take care of you and your families.”...And he spoke very kindly to them, reassuring them.</i>’ (Genesis 50:21 TLB) True forgiveness, the kind that’s taught in Scripture, is a commitment you must practise every day of your life. People need loving the most, when they deserve it the least. No one ever said it would be easy. If Jesus had waited until His enemies repented, He’d never have prayed on the cross: ‘<i>Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they do</i>.’ (Luke 23:34 NKJV) Sure, it’s easier to forgive when others acknowledge their offence. But if that’s a prerequisite, you may never experience victory! And what you don’t forgive—you have to relive! So for your own sake forgive, take back your life, and begin walking in the blessing of the Lord.</p><h2>SoulFood: Rom 15–16, John 10:22–33, Ps 50, Prov 30:7–10</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 17 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Walk in love, as Christ also has loved us.’ Ephesians 5:2 NKJV</p><p>You’ll Ask God to Bless Them</p><p>Walking in love and forgiveness is difficult on several fronts. (1) It goes against your carnal nature. (2) There’s a chance others may never know you forgave the offence. (3) Your heart could break as you watch God bless the offender in answer to your prayers, as if they’d never sinned against you in the first place. John Calvin pointed out that praying like this ‘is exceedingly difficult’, and early Church theologian John Chrysostom called it ‘the highest summit of self-control’. The Bible says Job’s suffering ended and his prosperity was restored once he was able to pray for those who’d become a thorn in his side (Job 42:10). When you pray this way you put into practice the words of Jesus in His famous Sermon on the Mount: ‘<span lang="en-US">But I say to you, love your enemies, bless those who curse you, do good to those who hate you, and pray for those who spitefully use you and persecute you,</span> <span lang="en-US">that you may be sons of your Father in Heaven.</span>’ (Matthew 5:44–45 NKJV) That’s Christ’s standard of forgiveness, and it’s a high one. Maybe you’re wondering how anybody could possibly live that way. Look at the life and death of Stephen, the first Christian martyr. Even while his enemies were stoning him, he prayed, ‘<i>Lord, do not hold this sin against them.</i>’ (Acts 7:60 NIV) Therein lay one of the secrets of Stephen’s great effectiveness. True forgiveness is the medicine that heals the deepest emotional wounds. It closes the door on the past, and gives you grace and motivation to move forward and enjoy the life God wants you to live. </p><h2>SoulFood: Ecc 1–3, John 10:34–42, Ps 81, Prov 30:11–14</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 18 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p lang="en-AU">‘God… chose things the world considers foolish.’ 1 Corinthians 1:27 NLT</p><p lang="en-AU">Billy </p><p lang="en-AU">Writing about his time at a teen Bible camp, a counsellor tells this story: ‘Teenage boys have a tendency to pick on some unfortunate child. That summer it was 13-year-old Billy, a child who couldn’t walk or talk right. When the children from his cabin were assigned to lead devotions, they voted Billy in as the speaker. It didn’t seem to bother him. He dragged himself up to the pulpit amid sneers and snickers, and it took him a long time to stammer, “Je–sus loves…me… and…I…love Je–sus.” There was stunned silence, and when I looked around there were boys with tears streaming down their cheeks. We’d done many things to try to reach these boys, but nothing had worked. We’d even brought in famous baseball players whose batting averages had gone up since they started praying, but it had no effect. It wasn’t until a special needs child declared his love for Christ that everything changed. I travel a lot and it’s surprising how often I meet people who say, “You probably don’t remember me. I became a Christian at a camp where you were a counsellor, and do you know what the turning point was for me?” I never have to ask. I always know I’m going to hear—<i>Billy!</i>’</p><p lang="en-AU">The Bible says, ‘God chose things the world considers foolish in order to shame those who think they are wise.’ (1 Corinthians 1:27 NLT) So when you find yourself focusing on what you <i>can’t</i> do, remember His ‘power works best in [your] weakness.’(2 Corinthians 12:9 NLT) Just do what you <i>can</i>, and God will do the rest! He’ll crown your efforts with success. </p><h2>SoulFood: Ecc 4–6, John 11:1–16, Ps 76, Prov 30:15–17</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 19 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Pray…with all [manner of] prayer.’ Ephesians 6:18 AMP</p><p>Different Types of Prayer (1)</p><p>In Scripture there are many different kinds of prayer. Let’s look at some of them and see what we can learn: (1) The prayer of surrender. When Paul met Christ on the Damascus Road he prayed, ‘<i>Lord, what do You want me to do?</i>’ (Acts 9:6 NKJV) That’s like signing your name to a blank cheque and saying, ‘Here I am, Lord, do with me as You please. I hope I like what You choose, but even if I don’t, I’ll do it anyway; Your will be done, not mine.’ You’re deciding to voluntarily follow God rather than trying to get Him to follow you. As a result He will do the work that needs to be done in you, so that He can do the work He desires to do through you. (2) The prayer of commitment. The Bible says, ‘<i>Casting the whole of your care [all your anxieties, all your worries, all your concerns, once and for all] on Him</i>.’ (1 Peter 5:7 AMP) As long as you keep trying to control everything, your stress levels will keep mounting. But once you learn to hand things over to God, you’ll wonder why you spent even a single day worrying. (3) The prayer of intercession. The prophet Ezekiel writes, ‘<i>I looked for someone…who would…stand before me in the gap on behalf of the land</i>.’ (Ezekiel 22:30 NIV) ‘The gap’ is the distance between what is— and what can be. And when there’s a ‘gap’ in someone’s relationship with God due to a particular sin, as a believer you have the privilege (and responsibility) of placing yourself in that gap and praying for them. </p><h2>SoulFood: Ecc 7–9, John 11:17–27, Ps 102:1–11, Prov 30:18–20</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 20 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Pray…with all [manner of] prayer.’ Ephesians 6:18 AMP</p><p>Different Types of Prayer (2)</p><p>Here are three more types of prayer: (1) The prayer of petition. You must learn to be confident in asking God to meet your needs. Jesus promised, ‘<i lang="en-US">Therefore I say to you, whatever things you ask when you pray, believe that you receive them, and you will have them</i>.’ (Mark 11:24 NKJV) If we’d stop trying to impress God, we’d be a lot better off. Length, loudness or eloquence isn’t the issue; it’s the sincerity of our heart, the faith that’s in our heart, and the assurance that we’re praying according to God’s will that gets results. (2) The prayer of agreement. ‘<i>All these with one accord were devoting themselves to prayer...</i>’ (Acts 1:14 ESV) When you’re up against something too big to handle alone, find a prayer partner and get into agreement with them. This isn’t for people who constantly live in strife, then decide to agree because they’re desperate. God honours the prayers of those who pay the price to live together in harmony (See Psalm 133:1) (3) The prayer of thanksgiving. When your prayers outnumber your praises, it says something about your character. Self-centred people ask, but rarely appreciate. God won’t release us into the fullness of all He has planned for us until we become thankful for what we’ve already received. Petition avails much; praise avails much more! ‘<i>In every situation, by prayer and petition, with thanksgiving, present your requests to God</i>.’ (Philippians 4:6 NIV) Powerful living comes through thanksgiving. We can literally ‘<i>pray without ceasing</i>’ (1 Thessalonians 5:17 KJV) by being thankful all day long, praising God for His favour, mercy, loving kindness, grace, longsuffering and goodness.</p><h2>SoulFood: Ecc 10–12, John 11:28–37, Ps 102:12–17, Prov 30:21–23</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 21 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p lang="en-US"><span lang="en-GB">‘</span><sup> </sup>…be peaceable and considerate, and always to be gentle toward everyone.<span lang="en-GB">’ Titus 3:2 NIV</span></p><p>Remember to Say Thank You</p><p>Gratitude comes with a host of benefits. It improves your heart rhythm, reduces stress, and helps you heal physically and think more clearly under pressure. It floods your body and brain with endorphins that strengthen and rejuvenate you. And like any muscle, the more you exercise it the stronger it grows. It doesn’t have to be complicated; just take a walk and think about your blessings and it will set the tone for your day. The psalmist said, ‘<i>Praise the Lord and do not forget all His kindnesses.</i>’ (Psalm 103:2 NCV) God’s blessings operate 24 hours a day, 365 days a year. Try this: When you sit down to eat, have everyone at the table name something they’re thankful for. There’s always something. An elderly lady at a nursing home said, ‘I thank you, Lord, for two good teeth, one upper and one lower. And I thank you that they meet!’ Psychologist Martin Seligman suggests sending a letter or email of gratitude to somebody, then visiting that person and reading it to them. People who say ‘thank you’ are measurably happier and less depressed. The CEO of <i>Campbell Soup</i> wrote over sixteen thousand thank–you notes to his employees, and energised the entire company in the process. Go ahead, encourage your friends and co-workers by letting them know you appreciate what they do. The Bible says, ‘...<i lang="en-US">be peaceable and considerate</i>.’ One author observes: ‘You have it in your power to increase the sum total of the world’s happiness by giving a few words of sincere appreciation to someone who’s lonely or discouraged. Perhaps you’ll forget the kind words you say today, but the recipient may cherish them for a lifetime.’ </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 1–3, John 11:38–44, Ps 102:18–28, Prov 30:24–28</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 22 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p lang="en-US"><span lang="en-GB">‘You </span>have… encouraged those who are weak or falling<span lang="en-GB">.’</span> <span lang="en-GB">Job 4:3 TLB</span></p><p>Today, Speak Words that Encourage</p><p>The Bible says, ‘...<i>l</i><span lang="en-US">et us pursue what makes for… mutual upbuilding.</span>’ (Romans 14:19 ESV) When Job was in trouble, his friend Eliphaz reminded him how in the past Job’s words had ‘<i>encouraged those who were </i><i lang="en-US">weak or falling</i><span lang="en-US">.</span>’ Words can hurt or heal, bless or blister, destroy or deliver, tear down or build up. ‘<i>The tongue has the power of life and death</i>.’ (Proverbs 18:21 NIV) Jon Walker writes: ‘You…the one with Jesus in your heart—are capable of murder. And so am I. We have the power to speak death with our words, and… the power to speak life. Perhaps you’ve been on the receiving end of a message meant to murder. “You’re not smart enough…thin enough…fast enough…good enough…a real Christian wouldn’t think such things.” In a world where people are beaten up and put down, God gives you superhero power to punch through the negativity. You speak life when you say, “You matter to me. I like you just the way you are… Your life counts. You were created for a purpose. God loves you, and you’re incredibly valuable to Him.” You can become the voice of God’s grace in the lives of others, supporting, loving, helping and encouraging them with the words that flow from your mouth.’ God wants us to encourage each other, but that doesn’t mean flattering or buttering people up. It means speaking words that help them to stay on their feet and keep going. What you say can give fresh hope to a friend, a relative, a neighbour, or a co-worker who’s about to collapse. What a gift! </p><h2>SoulFood: Deut 9:13–29, Luke 4:1–13</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 23 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘My grace is all you need. My power works best in weakness.’ 2 Corinthians 12:9 NLT</p><p>Today, Depend on God</p><p>Hindrances, hang-ups, and hurdles are God’s gift to the self-sufficient. While He won’t let you use your weakness as a crutch or a cop-out, He’ll allow it to keep you dependent on Him. Paul wrote, ‘<i>I was given a thorn…to…keep me from becoming proud.</i>’ (2 Corinthians 12:7 NLT) Why would God keep you in touch with your limitations? To embarrass you? No, to empower you so that you can do His will. God’s intention is to increase, not decrease your need for Him. Perhaps this illustration will help you. Imagine four steel rings. The first can support eighty kg<b>, </b>the second sixty kg, the third forty kg, and the fourth twenty kg. Linked together, what’s the greatest weight the chain can support? Two hundred kg? No, a chain is <i>only as strong</i> as its weakest link, so the answer is twenty kg! And it’s the same with us; we’re only as strong as our weakest area. That’s why we sometimes try to excuse or ignore them. But that’s dangerous because relying on your own strength may win you a few victories and accolades and cause you to think you can handle everything on your own. It was because Paul was so brilliant that God permitted difficult circumstances that kept him on his knees, living in a state of forced dependence. After praying repeatedly for God to take his weakness away, Paul finally came to the place where he could say, ‘<i>I will boast all the more gladly about my weaknesses, so that Christ’s power may rest on me</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 12:9 NIV) So today, depend on God! </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 4–6, John 11:45–57, Ps 95, Prov 30:29–33</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 24 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p lang="en-US"><span lang="en-GB">‘</span>Christ means everything to me in this life, and when I die I’ll have even more<span lang="en-GB">.’</span> <span lang="en-GB">Philippians 1:21 GWT</span></p><p>A Faith Perspective</p><p>Roman prisons were terrible places. Offenders were stripped, flogged and placed in leg irons. Their blood-soaked clothing wasn’t changed even in the dead of winter. And the ‘<i>inner cell</i>’ (Acts 16:24 NIV) where Paul and Silas were imprisoned was the worst. Lack of water, cramped conditions and the stench of toilets (if that’s what you could call them) made sleep impossible. Prisoners routinely begged for death, and some even committed suicide. It was your worst nightmare! Yet ‘<i>Paul and Silas were…singing…and the other prisoners were listening.</i>’ (Acts 16:25 NIV) Paul’s attitude impressed his fellow inmates before his religious beliefs ever reached them. Let’s face it, anybody can sing in church, including hypocrites. But when you can praise God in the midst of pain, pressures, and problems—that’s something else. How did they do it? They had a faith perspective! It’s not what you have lost, but what you have left that counts! Paul didn’t just sing in prison, he wrote some of his best stuff there. Here’s his take on it: ‘...<i>through my being in prison, the Lord has given most of our brothers and sisters confidence to speak God’s word more boldly and fearlessly than ever... I will speak very boldly and honour Christ... now as always, whether I live or die. Christ means everything to me in this life, and when I die I’ll have even more</i>.’ (Philippians 1:19–21 GWT) What are you going to do with a man or woman like this? They’re beyond your threats. Their strength comes from a source that’s not diminished by outside circumstances. That’s because they have a faith perspective. And that’s what you need today too! </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 7–9, John 12:1–11, Ps 114, Prov 31:1–5</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 25 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘I am leaving you with a gift—peace of mind.’ John 14:27 NLT</p><p>‘Peace of Mind’</p><p>You can control what goes on in your mind by filling it with God’s Word. Not the Word you read casually, but the Word you process mentally, apply to each situation that arises, and stand on in times of crisis because you know it’s your right to have the peace Jesus promised. Jesus corrected His disciples because they lost their peace of mind during a storm. He didn’t lose His. He was asleep in the back of the boat. So where are you today? Resting with Jesus in the back of the boat, or panicking with the others up front? Worry overwhelms you when you forget two things: (1) What the Lord has told you. Jesus said, ‘<i>Let us go over to the other side</i>.’ (Mark 4:35 NIV) And once He spoke those words there wasn’t a wave big enough to sink them. Anytime you’re doing what God’s told you to do, you may go through storms but you won’t sink. (2) Who’s with you in the boat. The disciples thought they knew Jesus pretty well, but before the night was over they were asking, ‘<i>Who is this? Even the wind and the waves obey Him!</i>’ (Mark 4:41 NIV) Has it ever occurred to you that the storm you’re in right now has been permitted by God to show you that you don’t have a problem He can’t solve; that you’re not alone, and that through this experience you’ll come to know Him better? In the Amplified Bible the words of Jesus are translated like this: ‘<i>Do not let your hearts be…distressed, agitated</i>.’ (John 14:1 AMP) The only power worry has over you—is the power you give it. </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 10–12, John 12:12–19, Ps 118:1–9, Prov 31:6–9 </h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 26 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Children are a gift from the Lord.’ Psalm 127:3 NLT</p><p>What Your Child Deserves (1) </p><p>Your children deserve certain things, like: (1) Time. Not leftover time at the end of the day, but prioritised time. If your life is ruled by a schedule and your children aren’t on it, do something—quickly. Otherwise there’ll come a day when you’re not included in their schedule. Simply watching television together for three hours won’t cut it; you must be ‘emotionally present’. Sometimes that means letting them see your fears and insecurities, even as they witness your delight and appreciation of them. (2) Openness. There’s so much our children can teach us about themselves, about ourselves, and about who God is. Once we realise we don’t have all the answers, we become open to allowing God to speak to us through our children. That kind of receptivity strengthens their faith, helps them remain teachable, and also keeps us young at heart. (3) Structure. It’s vital, during the formative years, to establish rules and maintain boundaries. Children need guidelines and a framework to feel secure. In the early years this includes things like having an established bedtime, then moving it back as they get older. This helps them understand that age brings freedom, but not all at once, because freedom brings responsibility and they’re not as ready to handle it as they think. Don’t try to be your child’s best friend or look to them to meet your emotional needs. Their shoulders aren’t broad enough to carry that load. Be confident in God, and in who you are. Seek outside encouragement from healthy sources. In short, strive to become the firm, gentle parent your child deserves. </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 13–16, John 12:20–36, Ps 118:10–18, Prov 31:10–13</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 27 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Bring them…so I may bless them.’ Genesis 48:9 NIV </p><p>What Your Child Deserves (2)</p><p>Here are three more things your children deserve from you: (1) Forgive them, and be willing to ask for their forgiveness. By doing this you’re teaching them that: a) We must all deal with the consequences of our actions. And that when we do, we grow. b) Failing doesn’t make you a failure; it’s just part of learning and maturing. It comes with the turf. c) We should be quick to extend to others the same grace that has so often been extended to us. (2) Separate the baggage. One man became anxious and depressed as his son approached his twelfth birthday. Shortly after the boy’s birthday party, the father was thumbing through a photo album from his own childhood. That’s when it dawned on him that he was twelve when his father abandoned the family and then killed himself. Watching his son approach the same age made him afraid because it reopened old wounds—unhealed ones. A caring counsellor helped him regain his perspective and peace by helping him realise he was a very different man from his father, and he wasn’t about to abandon his family. (3) Bless them. ‘<i>“They are the sons God has given me here,” Joseph said to his father. Then Israel said, “Bring them to me so I may bless them.”</i>’ (Genesis 48:9 NIV) The principles you live by and the blessings you enjoy are meant to be passed on to your children and grandchildren. Whether it’s expressing what’s in your heart, or sending a note or email to say you’re proud of them, bless your children at every possible opportunity. </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 17–19, John 12:37–50, Ps 118:19–29, Prov 31:14–17</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 28 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘…that it may go well with you and your children...’ Deuteronomy 4:40 NIV </p><p>What Your Child Deserves (3)</p><p>Sometimes we get scared because our kids remind us so much of ourselves. We see in them the same fears and proclivities that we have struggled with. We watch them veering off life’s highway in some of the same spots where we crashed and burned and it’s difficult not to want to save them. But sometimes we can’t. They’ve grown up with their own mindset, strengths and dreams. And if the parable of the prodigal son teaches us anything, it’s that good parents can raise children who are only capable of learning the hard way. So what can you do? Pray for them—and ‘be there’ when they return. Many a successful adult was once a prodigal saved by the prayers of a parent who refused to give up on them. If what you’re doing is taking you away from prayer time for your children, your priorities are wrong. There’s nothing more valuable than the time you spend before God interceding on their behalf. You say, ‘But I don’t know how to pray.’ Try this: ‘Father, I’m concerned about the direction my children are taking. Right now they seem beyond the reach of my voice and influence. But You can reach them. You can remind them of what they’ve been taught—and initiate the circumstances that will bring them back to You. Your Word says if I obey You, things will go well for me and my children (Deuteronomy 4:40). So I stand on Your promise, believing they’ll choose to serve You and walk in Your blessing for the rest of their lives. In Christ’s name I pray. Amen.’</p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 20–23, John 13:1–17, Ps 146, Prov 31:18–21</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 29 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Encourage…and build up one another.’ 1 Thessalonians 5:11 NAS</p><p>When You Belittle, You Become Little</p><p>Here are four questions you need to be able to answer: (1) Do people feel better about themselves after spending time with you? (2) Are your expectations so high that you focus on people’s shortcomings instead of their strengths? (3) When somebody speaks well of a person you don’t particularly like, do you feel the need to inject a disparaging remark? (4) Are you so insecure and lacking in self-worth that you only feel good about yourself by putting others down? Well, how did you do on the test? If you’re not four-for-four, it’s time to spend time with God in prayer and ask Him to help you change your attitude and what comes out of your mouth. Paul says, ‘<i>Do not let any unwholesome talk come out of your mouths, but only what is helpful for building others up according to their needs, that it may benefit those who listen</i>.’ (Ephesians 4:29 NIV) Words are like hammers: they can be used to break down or build up. It all depends on the person swinging the hammer! It’s just as easy to be part of the construction crew as it is to be a member of the wrecking crew. Make a habit of encouraging your family and your friends. Let your wife know she’s the only woman in the world for you. Express appreciation for your husband’s care and sense of responsibility. Applaud your teenager for avoiding drugs and alcohol. Thank your friends for keeping your secrets! Accept people as they are, and resist the temptation to constantly ‘fix’ something about them—that’s God’s job, not yours. Remember, you only have them for a short time!</p><h2>SoulFood: Exod 17.1–7, John 4:1–42</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 30 NOVEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Come with me…to a quiet place and get some rest.’ Mark 6:31 NIV </p><p>Take Time to Rest and Sharpen</p><p>A competition was held between two men to see who could chop down the most trees in a single day. One man was older and more experienced, while the other was younger and less experienced. And that’s where the difference showed up. The younger man spent eight hours chopping down trees, and at the end of the day he had a total of twenty-five. Believing the older man lacked stamina and youth, he sat down, fully confident he would win. Meanwhile the older man, who had taken a ten-minute break each hour, ended his day by chopping down forty trees. In shock the younger man asked, ‘How is this possible, old man? I didn’t stop. You stopped every hour for ten minutes and yet you chopped down almost twice as many trees as I did.’ The older man replied, ‘Every hour I sat down for ten minutes and did two things. First, I took time to rest and recharge my batteries. Second, I took time to sharpen my axe. Yes, you were working hard but you were working with a dull axe.’ There’s an important lesson here for you. In order to succeed at what God has called you to do in life, you must always do these two things: (1) Make time for rest and renewal. You cannot always be giving out; you must also stop and take in. That’s where prayer and Bible reading come in: they restore what life depletes. (2) Stay sharp. When your axe is dull it requires more energy and produces fewer results. So take time to rest and sharpen.</p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 24:1–25:18, John 13:18–30, Ps 14, Prov 31:22–24</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 1 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘The sin we have so foolishly committed.’ Numbers 12:11 NIV</p><p>Stop Being So Critical (1)</p><p>When Miriam criticised her brother Moses because of the wife he chose, the Lord heard and she was smitten with leprosy. Maybe you grew up in a family that was forever finding fault, and now you hear the same tone in how you talk to your children. You can’t enjoy God’s blessings because you’ve been programmed to inspect, nitpick and form opinions—usually negative ones. The Bible says, ‘<i>If you want to enjoy life and see…happy days, keep your tongue from speaking evil</i>.’ (1 Peter 3:10 NLT) The definition of the word ‘criticism’ (dwelling upon the perceived faults of another with no view to their good) should cause you to pause and think. First, there’s the word perceived. Often your perceptions aren’t accurate; there are always circumstances you don’t understand. Next we come to the words dwelling upon. We’re inclined to walk through life saying, ‘That’s not right,’ or ‘I wouldn’t do it that way.’ You say, ‘I’m an analytical person, it’s how God made me.’ That’s fine, but the problem comes when you choose to dwell on your observations—when you can’t set them aside. You say, ‘But how can I help somebody if I don’t dwell on what they’re doing?’ That’s why the last part of the definition—with no view to their good—is so important. It’s not wrong to dwell upon somebody’s faults, provided you do it in a non-judgmental way with a view to helping them find a solution. Does that mean it’s ok to discuss it with a third party? Only if you can end the conversation by saying, ‘Let’s pray about it, keep it in confidence, and try to help.’ </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 25:19–27:46, John 13:31–38, Ps 65, Prov 31:25–27</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 2 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Keep your tongue from speaking evil.’ 1 Peter 3:10 NLT </p><p>Stop Being So Critical (2)</p><p>God dealt with Moses because of some of the mistakes he made. In fact, one of them kept him from entering the Promised Land. Nevertheless, God wouldn’t permit anybody else to criticise Moses—not even his sister Miriam. So what can you learn from this? (1) We’re all capable of harbouring a critical attitude. Miriam had great qualities. She saved Moses’ life as a child, and she wrote a song of praise Israel used to celebrate the crossing of the Red Sea. But she paid a high price for her critical attitude—leprosy. (2) When you’re resentful you become critical. ‘<i>Miriam…began to talk against Moses because of his Cushite wife</i>.’ (Numbers 12:1 NIV) But was that the real issue? No. ‘<i>They said, “Has the Lord indeed spoken only through Moses? Has He not spoken through us also?”</i>’ (Numbers 12:2 NKJV) Moses’ wife was just a diversion; the real issue was Moses’ success. Their beef was: ‘How come he gets all the attention?’ (3) Anytime you succeed you’ll be criticised. The Bible says, ‘<i>Moses was very humble</i>’ (Numbers 12:3 NKJV), yet even he couldn’t escape the pain inflicted by self-appointed critics. And you’re no different; as long as you’re alive somebody will find fault with what you’re doing. Brush it off and keep going. (4) If you’ve been critical, you need to repent. When Aaron acknowledged, ‘<i>We have acted foolishly…we have sinned</i>’ (Numbers 12:11 NAS), God showed mercy and healed Miriam. Most of us would rather classify criticism as a weakness, but from God’s perspective it’s a genuine, bona fide, registered sin. And there’s only one way to deal with sin—repent and stop committing it. </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 28:1–30:24, John 14:1–14, Ps 130, Prov 31:28–31</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 3 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Take delight in honouring each other.’ Romans 12:10 NLT </p><p>Stop Being So Critical (3)</p><p>Having a critical attitude may not destroy your relationship with God, but it’ll definitely hurt your capacity to experience His love, His presence and His blessing. Notice, it was God who smote Miriam with leprosy. She started out by criticising her brother Moses, and ended up feeling the consequences in her relationship with the Lord. Why? Because God pays attention to the way we treat each other! Maybe you’re wondering, ‘Why would God make such a big deal out of this?’ Because when you choose to sin, you choose to suffer. Everything God classifies as sin is hurtful to you—everything. When God says, ‘Don’t,’ what He really means is, ‘Don’t hurt yourself.’ And when He says, ‘Don’t criticise,’ He’s not trying to deprive you of satisfaction. He’s saying that having a critical attitude goes against who He made you to be, and what you’re called to do. Just as fish were made to swim and birds were made to fly, you were made to live in fellowship with God—and a critical spirit hinders that fellowship. Even people who don’t claim to be particularly religious are cognisant of the negative effects of criticism. Dr David Fink, author of Release from Nervous Tension, studied thousands of mentally and emotionally disturbed people. He worked with two groups: a stressed-out group and a stress-free one. Eventually one fact emerged: the stressed-out group was composed of habitual fault-finders and constant critics of people and things around them. On the other hand, the stress-free group was loving and accepting of others. There’s no doubt about it, the habit of criticising is a self-destructive way to live. Don’t go there. </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 30:25–31:55, John 14:15–25, Ps 2, Ecc 3:1–4</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 4 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘If I were…trying to please men.’ Galatians 1:10 TLB </p><p>Stop Being So Critical (4)</p><p>Some important observations: (1) Criticism is often ego-based. Oswald Chambers wrote, ‘Beware of anything that puts you in the place of the superior person.’ And that’s exactly what criticism does: it highlights you as the one who ‘knows’. Not only that, it gives you the satisfaction of shining the spotlight on others. People find it much harder to see your life when you’re shining the glaring light of criticism on theirs. When you live this way your attitude says, ‘If I can’t make it in this world by what I do, I’ll make it by knowing what you should do better.’ James writes, ‘<i>These things ought not so to be.</i>’ (James 3:10 KJV) And Paul writes, ‘<i>Love each other…and take delight in honouring each other.</i>’ (Romans 12:10 NLT) (2) Criticism can break hearts. Imagine how Moses felt when his brother and sister suddenly turned on him. Because the people closest to us know the details of our lives, we’re always vulnerable to their criticism. Sometimes as parents we leave our children’s lives in shambles by creating a home that’s rife with criticism. Maybe as you read these words you hear the voice of your harshest critic—a parent who constantly put you down. A parent whose words still ring in your memory: ‘You were never any good’; ‘You’ll never amount to anything.’ (3) How should you respond to criticism? Paul answers: ‘<i>If I were…trying to please men, I would not be a…servant of Christ</i>.’ (Galatians 1:10 NAS) Instead of listening to your critics, centre your attention on what God thinks of you and your life will take an upswing. In the final analysis, His is the only opinion that counts.</p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 32–34, John 14:26–15:4, Ps 147:1–11, Ecc 3:5–8</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 5 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Who are you to judge your neighbour?’ James 4:12 NIV</p><p>Stop Being So Critical (5)</p><p>Nobody wants to spend time with someone who monopolises the conversation by updating them on their top-ten-people-to-criticise list. Staying home and watching old movie reruns is more appealing than going to that kind of party! It’s a hard truth to hear, but the people you need most are the ones who’ll avoid you when you become known as a fault-finder. Sometimes criticism is inadvertent; on a better day, led by God’s Spirit and focused on what’s positive, you’d never say such things. Notice what Aaron said: ‘<i>We have acted foolishly</i>.’ (Numbers 12:11 NAS) He didn’t try to defend his position by saying, ‘Yes, Moses did marry the wrong person,’ or ‘We deserve more of the limelight.’ No, he realised his mistake, repented, and retreated from it. And you must do that too. Why? Because criticism blocks the flow of God’s blessing in your life! Oswald Chambers wrote, ‘Whenever you’re in a critical temper, it’s impossible to enter into communion with God.’ Stop and ask yourself: ‘Is the momentary relief I get from criticising others worth losing my sense of God’s presence?’ To regain that sense of His presence you need to confess and forsake your critical attitude, then replace it with a more gracious and loving one. Today, get down on your knees and pray: ‘Lord, forgive me for thinking my perspective is always right. I acknowledge that as arrogance. Give me grace in dealing with others—the same grace I’ve received from You. Help me to accept our differences and not demand that everyone see things exactly as I do. Give me victory over my critical attitude. In Jesus’ name. Amen.’ </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 35–36, John 15:5–17, Ps 147:12–20, Ecc 4:9–12</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 6 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘I come…in the name of the Lord.’ 1 Samuel 17:45 NKJV</p><p>Bringing Down Your Goliath</p><p>To bring down the ‘Goliath’ in your life, here are three things you must do: (1) You must stand up to him! Any problem you try to excuse or escape, you empower. After listening to Goliath’s threats every day, fear gripped the hearts of God’s people and they couldn’t stand up to him. (2) You must remember what God has already done for you. David recalled his victories over the lion and the bear. And you must do the same. Jeremiah said, ‘<i>This I call to mind…therefore I have hope: because of the Lord’s great love we are not consumed, for His compassions never fail. They are new every morning</i>.’ (Lamentations 3:21–23 NIV) The strength to deal with today’s struggles comes from remembering how God helped you solve yesterday’s struggles. (3) You must cut off the giant’s head. ‘<i>David…took his sword…and cut off his head…And when the Philistines saw that their champion was dead, they fled</i>.’ (1 Samuel 17:51 NKJV) You need to know your spiritual enemy, study his tactics, and be willing to fight with the same level of intensity as he does. You must take what you learn and apply it to his weak areas. And never assume he’s dead when he’s just dazed. If you do, he’ll sneak up on you another day. Go for a permanent solution, not a short–term fix: (1) fortify yourself with prayer (2) renew your mind with the Word of God (3) reach for the support that’s available to you through your spiritual family. Above all, remember your strength doesn’t lie in yourself, but in God. With Him on your side you’ll win every time. </p><h2>SoulFood: 1 Kings 17:1–7, 1 Kings 18:41–46, Mark 4:35–41</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 7 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Defend the cause of the fatherless.’ Isaiah 1:17 NIV </p><p>Be a Mentor to a Fatherless Boy</p><p>In her book Mothers and Sons, Jean Lush talks about the challenge single mothers face in raising sons. Ages four to six are especially important and difficult. A boy at that age still loves his mother, but feels the need to gravitate towards a masculine image. If he has a father in the home, he’ll want to spend more time with his dad apart from his mother and sisters. So what advice can be given to a mother who’s raising a son alone? First, she must understand he has needs that she’s not best equipped to meet. Her best option is to recruit a man who can act as a role model to her son. Of course, good mentors can be difficult to find. Single mothers should consider friends, relatives or neighbours who can offer as little as an hour or two a month. Single mothers who belong to a church should be able to find support for their boys among the male members. Scripture commands people of faith to care for children without fathers: ‘<i>Defend the cause of the fatherless, plead the case of the widow</i>.’ Jesus took boys and girls on His lap and said, ‘<i>Whoever welcomes a little child like this in My name welcomes Me</i>.’ (Matthew 18:5 NIV) If you are a man and you have been asking God to use you in His service, this could be a real ministry opportunity for you. Think of the incredible potential of one small boy, and the privilege of helping to mould him into a man of God who fulfils the purposes of God during his lifetime. What a privilege!</p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 37–39, John 15:18–27, Ps 148:1–6, Ecc 5:1–3</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 8 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Don’t sin by letting anger control you.’ Ephesians 4:26 NLT</p><p>Control Your Anger!</p><p>Uncontrolled anger is like jumping into your car, revving the engine, and discovering too late that the brakes don’t work. The Bible says, ‘<i lang="en-AU">Be angry without sinning. Don't go to bed angry. Don’t give the devil any opportunity [to work].</i>’ (Ephesians 4:26–27 GWT) Did you get that? Uncontrolled anger opens the door to Satan—and it’s all downhill from there! So before you say something you’ll regret and can’t take back, ask yourself: (1) Is the relief I’ll get from venting worth the aftermath? The Bible says, ‘<i>A gentle answer turns away wrath, but a harsh word stirs up anger</i>.’ (Proverbs 15:1 NIV) By sounding off, you run the risk of making the finest speech you’ll ever regret. By its very nature anger encourages exaggeration, and makes you say things you can’t retract. Long after you’ve moved on, harsh words maintain their power to wound and divide. (2) Is it really worth dragging other people into it? Anger inevitably affects those around you because it’s human to want to take sides, even if you’ve ‘no dog in the fight’. Involving other people is usually a way to feed your ego and justify bad behaviour. Don’t do it. (3) Is my anger appropriate? Anger over ignorance and injustice has always led to progress. But it’s easy to let small stuff like thoughtless comments and cranky kids make you overreact. For anger to have a healthy result it needs to be measured and constructive. Paul says, ‘<i>The mind governed by the Spirit is life and peace.</i>’ (Romans 8:6 NIV) It comes down to a control issue, and a controlled response is a Christlike response. It always wins. </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 40–41, John 16:1–11, Ps 148:7–14, Ecc 5:4–6</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 9 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Be doers of the word, and not hearers only.’ James 1:22 NKJV</p><p>The Cure for Spiritual Boredom</p><p>Why does the Bible say, ‘<i>Be doers of the word, and not hearers only</i>’? Because hearing without doing becomes boring—every time. You can get to the place where you’ve heard so much preaching and teaching that you say to yourself, ‘Oh no, not another sermon!’ The problem isn’t the Word; it’s that you’ve become oversaturated and spiritually numb. You’re bored because you aren’t putting it into practice and reaping the rewards of what you’ve heard. Jesus said, ‘<i>If you know these things, blessed are you if you do them</i>.’ (John 13:17 NKJV) Once you start doing what you’ve been told to do, you won’t have time to be bored. The phrase ‘hearers only’ is from the Greek noun akroates. Today we’d use it to describe students who sit in on a class just to hear the teaching, instead of taking any assessment or being graded. These folks weren’t interested in learning, passing exams, earning a degree and going out to make a difference in the world. They were there because they found it intellectually stimulating and they loved the excitement of being with the crowd. Often they followed their favourite teacher from one town to another; they loved new speakers, and when the class ended they’d get together to eat, drink, laugh and discuss what they’d heard. Mostly, they just wanted to look knowledgeable in each other’s eyes. Don’t let that happen to you. ‘<i>Remember… knowing what is right to do and… not doing it is sin</i>.’ (James 4:17 TLB) Open your heart to the truths you’ve heard preached and begin to put them to work in your life. When you do, rest assured you’ll never again suffer from spiritual boredom. </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 42–43, John 16:12–18, Ps 150, Ecc 5:10–12</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 10 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘They shared everything they had.’ Acts 4:32 NIV</p><p>Share Your Life</p><p>When you read the story of the New Testament Church, you tend to get caught up in its explosive growth and amazing miracles. But here’s a component you shouldn’t miss: ‘<i>No one claimed that any of his possessions was his own, but they shared everything they had… There were no needy persons among them…those who owned lands or houses sold them, brought the money…and it was distributed to anyone as he had need</i>.’ (Acts 4:32–35 NIV) You say, ‘If I just had more money I’d be happy.’ You might feel more secure and have fewer worries, but you wouldn’t necessarily be happier. In the Journal of Happiness Studies, researchers looked at what distinguished quite happy people from less happy people. One factor consistently separated those two groups. It’s not about how much money you have; it’s not about your health, security, attractiveness, IQ or career success. What distinguishes consistently happy people from less happy people is the presence of rich, deep, joy-producing, life-changing, meaningful relationships. Social researcher Robert Putnam writes: ‘The single most common finding from a half-century’s research on life satisfaction, not only in the U.S. but around the world, is that happiness is best predicted by the breadth and depth of one’s social connections.’ But you can know a lot of people without really being known by any of them, and end up lonely. Those folks in the New Testament Church got it right: it’s in sharing with one another spiritually, emotionally, financially and relationally that you achieve your highest level of joy.</p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 44–46, John 16:19–24, Ps 105:1–7, Ecc 5:13–16</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 11 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘After He had dismissed them, He went up on a mountainside by Himself to pray.’ Matthew 14:23 NIV </p><p>Learn to Say ‘Enough!’</p><p>Jesus dismissed a crowd of listeners and fans in order to spend time with His Father in prayer. As a result, when He returned to the crowd He was empowered to work miracles. Think about it; before an airliner takes off, the attendant tells you that if the plane gets into trouble you should secure your own oxygen mask before attempting to help others with theirs. After all, unless you’re getting enough oxygen, how can you help them? So, are your own needs being met? If not, it’s time to start taking care of yourself before you burn out. You can’t travel quietly through life hoping people will recognise when your plate is full. Speak up, or they’ll just keep pouring on more problems and responsibilities. Personal empowerment begins by taking control of your life. Overloaded people fail at marriage, ministry and management. They fail at parenting, partnership and personal endeavours. Like an airplane, if you carry too much baggage you won’t get off the ground. When you’re motivated by the need to please others or impress them, you’ll take on too much and fail to reach the heights God planned for you. Or you’ll crash because you ignored your limitations. Every situation that arises doesn’t warrant your attention! Was Jesus misunderstood when He dismissed the crowd? Probably. And you’ll have to make that same decision too. People who don’t recognise your needs and respect your goals will drain you, divert you, and keep you grounded. So what’s the answer? Give what you can, and learn when to say ‘enough!’ </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 47–49, John 16:25–33, Ps 105:8–22, Ecc 7:1–4</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 12 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘I was glad when they said to me, “Let us go into the house of the Lord.”’ Psalm 122:1 NKJV</p><p>The Benefits of Going to Church</p><p>People stay away from church for many reasons. Sometimes they feel bad because their faith isn’t working as well as they think it should. Or they’re still struggling with certain problems. Or they’re depressed because it looks like everyone else is doing well except them. Don’t let discouragement keep you away from your spiritual family. You need their love and support. You need to hear them say, ‘We made it, and by God’s grace you can too.’ The Bible says, ‘<i>Not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together, as is the manner of some</i>.’ (Hebrews 10:25 NKJV) The word ‘<i>forsaking</i>’ is taken from three Greek words which could be translated ‘out’, ‘down’, and ‘behind’. It pretty much describes someone who feels left out, spiritually and emotionally down, and far behind everyone else. The moment you feel that way the enemy whispers, ‘Just stay home from church today; you don’t need to go there with all those good people.’ If the enemy can separate you from other believers at the very time you need them most, he can rob you of what God has in store for you. Sure, you can stay at home, read your Bible and turn on Christian radio and television. But surrounded by your spiritual family you’ll get answers, experience joy and receive encouragement you can’t find anywhere else. Church is the last place the devil wants you to go when you’re feeling low. He knows if you go, you’ll be touched by the presence of the Lord and be able to crawl out of the hole you’re in. So, go to church! </p><h2>SoulFood: Gen 50, Hag 1–2, John 17:1–12, Ps 105:23–36, Ecc 7:5–8</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 13 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Like apples of gold in settings of silver is a word spoken in right circumstances.’ Proverbs 25:11 NAS</p><p>Critics, Coaches, Cheerleaders </p><p>Critics point out what’s wrong, and leave you feeling bad about yourself. Coaches show you what you did wrong, teach you how to do it right and leave you feeling better about yourself. Cheerleaders lift your spirits, offer their help, and assure you that you can succeed if you keep trying. So which of the three are you? If you tend to be one of those hard-driving, goal-oriented people, coaching someone may be a challenge for you. Perhaps you’re from the school of thought that believes a pay cheque should be encouragement enough—especially if an employee is being generously compensated. If so—beware! You’re stuck in the Stone Age and in dire need of a mindset change! If you want people to be productive, learn how to build them up. You say, ‘But it’s not my natural inclination to want to coach poor performers. I just want them out.’ Hold on there; you’re dealing with a human being, a person loved and valued by God! And with a little encouragement, some hand-holding and lots of communication, you may end up with a level of productivity and loyalty the cocky superstar isn’t capable of. Yes, if you’ve ‘a bad apple’ in the bunch you need to get rid of them before they infect the whole barrel. But before you resort to firing someone, try firing them up! Some of the people you work with just need to be presented with a clear vision, shown how they can be part of it and enlightened about the incentives and rewards that come from being part of the team that’s fulfilling a vision. </p><h2>SoulFood: 1 Kings 17:17–24, Mark 5:21–43, John 11:1–45</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 14 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Godly sorrow produces repentance leading to salvation.’ 2 Corinthians 7:10 NKJV</p><p>What It Means to Repent</p><p>The word ‘repent’ means to acknowledge your sin before God, turn from it, seek God’s forgiveness, and start living differently. It means doing an about-face turn and heading in the opposite direction. If you go 20 km down the road in the wrong direction, it requires doing a U-turn and coming 20 km back. At first this can seem discouraging. But it’s profitable, because next time you’ll think twice about where you’re headed. Repentance sometimes means making restitution to others. Zacchaeus was a tax collector who got rich by overcharging people. But after he met Jesus he said, ‘<i>If I have cheated anyone, I will pay back four times as much</i>.’ (Luke 19:8 GNT) God is more than willing to forgive you, but He may allow you to experience the painful consequences of your sin in order to motivate you towards obedience. ‘<i>No discipline is enjoyable while it is happening—it’s painful! But afterward there will be a peaceful harvest of right living for those who are trained in this way</i>.’ (Hebrews 12:11 NLT) Satan will try to tell you that you are beyond the reach of God’s grace, but you’re not. The Prodigal Son wasted his inheritance and ended up in a pigsty. But the day he decided to come back home, his father ran to meet him and restored him to full sonship in the family. And God will do that for you too. ‘<i>Let the wicked change their ways and banish the very thought of doing wrong. Let them turn to the Lord that He may have mercy on them. Yes, turn to our God, for He will forgive generously</i>.’ (Isaiah 55:7 NLT)</p><h2>SoulFood: Est 1–4, John 17:13–26, Ps 105:37–45, Ecc 7:9–12</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 15 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘This was the Lord’s doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.’ Matthew 21:42 NKJV</p><p>Seeing God’s Hand in It</p><p>Jesus said, ‘<i>The stone which the builders rejected has become the chief cornerstone. This was the Lord’s doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes</i>.’ Note the word ‘rejected’. The rejection of his brothers put Joseph on a path that led to the throne of Egypt and the saving of his family and his nation. How often has something happened in your life that you later realised was necessary? If you hadn’t experienced this or walked through that, you wouldn’t have been ready for the blessings you enjoy now. When you begin to see the hand of God in it you understand that what the enemy intended for your destruction, God used for your development. To be ‘more than a conqueror’ means you can stand up and say: ‘Here’s how I see it. It took everything I’ve been through to make me who I am and to teach me what I know. So I choose to be better, not bitter. I trust the faithfulness of God more than ever. I’ve learned that if faith doesn’t move the mountain, it’ll give me strength to endure until tomorrow. And if it is not gone by tomorrow, I’ll still believe that God is able and trust Him until He does.’ Relax, rejoice; your steps are being arranged by the Lord (Psalm 37:23). He hasn’t taken His eye or His hand off you, not even for a single moment. When you get through this trial you’ll realise that ‘the worst thing that could have happened’ was, in reality, ‘<i>the Lord’s doing</i>’, and it will become ‘<i>marvellous in your eyes</i>’.</p><h2>SoulFood: Est 5–10, John 18:1–11, Ps 18:1–29, Prov 26:24–27</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 16 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Come and drink the Water of Life.’ Revelation 22:17 TLB</p><p>Protect Your Life Source</p><p>The Babylonians encircled Jerusalem and cut off its food supply. The question was, how long could they hold out? That’s what the Babylonians kept wondering. But a month passed, then two, then an entire year, and still they held out. The secret of Jerusalem’s survival lay in a water supply from a spring outside the city walls where Hezekiah had cut a 542 m long tunnel through solid rock. From there water passed under the city walls to a reservoir inside called the Pool of Siloam. Without it God’s people would have gone down in defeat. But it’s not just another Bible story; there’s an important lesson here for you. To live victoriously you must: (1) know <i>your life’s true source</i>; (2) <i>protect it</i>; (3) <i>draw from it daily</i>. If your security, your strength, your self-worth or your strategy for living comes from any other source but God, the enemy can defeat you. Everything you need comes from God, so protect and nurture your relationship with Him, for it will always be the focal point of Satan’s attack. A day without reading God’s Word isn’t merely a slip; it’s a set-up for failure. Prayerlessness isn’t carelessness; it’s foolishness in the extreme. You say, ‘Well, I’m doing ok and I don’t pray or read the Bible very much.’ Maybe you haven’t reached your hour of testing yet. When that comes, without an established source to draw from you’ll struggle more and succeed less. Is that really how you want to live? If not, the word for you today is: ‘<i>Come and drink the Water of Life</i>.’ </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 1–4, John 18:12–24, Ps 57, Ecc 7:13–15</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 17 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Your words…[are] my joy and my heart’s delight.’ Jeremiah 15:16 NIV </p><p>The Benefits of Reading God’s Word</p><p>God promises certain things to those who take time each day to get to know Him through His Word. Let’s look at some of them: (1) Joy. ‘<i>When your words came, I ate them; they were my joy and my heart’s delight, for I bear Your name, Lord God Almighty.</i>’ (2) Strength. <i>‘Now I commit you to God and to the word of His grace, which can build you up and give you an inheritance among all those who are sanctified.</i>’ (Acts 20:32 NIV) (3) Peace. ‘<i>Great peace have those who love Your law, and nothing can make them stumble</i>.’ (Psalm 119:165 NIV) ‘<i>If only you had paid attention to My commands, your peace would have been like a river</i>.’ (Isaiah 48:18 NIV) (4) Stability. ‘<i>I have set the Lord always before me. Because He is at my right hand, I will not be shaken. Therefore my heart is glad and my tongue rejoices; my body also will rest secure</i>.’ (Psalm 16:8–9 NIV) (5) Success. ‘<i>Do not let this Book of the Law depart from your mouth; meditate on it day and night, so that you may be careful to do everything written in it. Then you will be prosperous and successful</i>.’ (Joshua 1:8 NIV) (6) Answered prayer. ‘<i>If you remain in Me and My words remain in you, ask whatever you wish, and it will be done for you</i>.’ (John 15:7 NIV) Joy, strength, peace, stability, success, and answered prayer—these are the things everybody wants. Don’t you? Well, look no further. God has promised them to you when you spend time with Him in His Word each day.</p><h2>SoulFood: Job 5–7, John 18:25–32, Ps 67, Ecc 7:19–22</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 18 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘If a [shepherd] has a hundred sheep, and one…is lost… Won’t he… search for the lost one?’ Matthew 18:12 TLB</p><p>Pastor, How Are You Doing? (1)</p><p>When a traveller was robbed and left to die on the Jericho Road, Jesus said, ‘<i>A… priest…Likewise a Levite…passed by on the other side</i>.’ (Luke 10:31–32 NKJV) That sounds cold, doesn’t it? But what if they overlooked the man not because they lacked compassion, but because they were late for a Bible study or a board meeting? Would they have been justified? James MacDonald writes: ‘This parable didn’t register until I’d been in the ministry for years. I’d walked past so many people who could’ve used my help, but because I was too distracted by church programmes, broken lives by the roadside rarely fitted into my agenda. Love isn’t efficient; it can’t be scheduled. This hurting man couldn’t have waited three weeks for an appointment, or for the Samaritan to launch a ministry of care to similar victims.’ Life’s most rewarding experiences rarely come in neat little packages. They’re found in unexpected encounters and at critical times in the lives of people. In fact, some people who can’t remember your last sermon can tell you in detail what you said to them in the hospital or over coffee last year, because it touched them so personally. Nothing in ministry is more seductive than thinking your work on behalf of the multitudes justifies ignoring those who can only be reached individually. Jesus said, ‘<i>If a [shepherd] has a hundred sheep, and one…is lost…Won’t he…go…search for the lost one?</i>’ When Peter said, ‘<i>Lord…I love You</i>,’ Jesus said, ‘<i>Take care of My sheep</i>.’ (John 21:16 NIV) And today He’s saying that to you, Pastor! </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 8–10, John 18:33–40, Ps 12, Ecc 9:10–12</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 19 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘The good shepherd lays down his life for the sheep.’ John 10:11 NIV</p><p>Pastor, How Are You Doing? (2)</p><p>Sometimes pastors hide behind their busy schedules to avoid having to say ‘no’ to people. Jesus knew when to get involved, and when not to. Learn from Him. You’ll never be able to respond effectively if you feel obligated to meet every need all the time. And God’s not asking you to. He only expects you to respond to what He sends your way. James MacDonald says: ‘I’ll never forget my guidance counsellor’s face when she heard I was going into the ministry. “But you don’t even like people!” she exclaimed. I remember thinking, “So what? Ministry’s about preaching and leading a congregation to greater heights. I don’t have to worry about individuals.” But that’s a myth. We dare not become so programme-focused that we flee from the next person God sends our way. I’m amazed how far bureaucracies will go to make systemic change, rather than making an exception that would easily fix the problem. Personal needs are too significant to commit to the rigidity of any programme. Some of us think the problem with handling needs personally is that they can multiply like rabbits. Plus, programmes exist to prevent you from becoming overwhelmed, right? Wrong! The “ministry myth” that says, “What you do for one you must do for all,” is a recipe for burnout.’ Jesus spent much of His time ministering to individual needs. And He said, ‘<i>The good shepherd lays down his life for the sheep</i>.’ But in order to do that you must make room in your life for the unexpected. </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 11–14, John 19:1–7, Ps 47, Ecc 10:1–4</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 20 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Only in returning to Me and resting in Me will you be saved.’ Isaiah 30:15 NLT</p><p>Pastor, How Are You Doing? (3)</p><p>God said, ‘<i>Only in returning to Me and resting in Me will you be saved. In quietness and confidence is your strength. But you would have none of it.</i>’ When you’re emotionally and spiritually drained by people’s expectations, it’s easy to grow numb to the full range of human emotions. And while it may seem like a relief to be free from negative emotions, the positive ones also become elusive because you don’t feel much of anything—good or bad. When that happens you’re likely to end up being directed by things like: (1) over-scheduling; (2) poor time management; (3) performance anxiety; (4) having few boundaries; (5) tolerating toxic relationships and bad habits; (6) unresolved grief or pain; (7) wrong goals. So what’s the answer? ‘<i>Only in returning to Me and resting in Me will you be saved</i>.’ Instead of pushing on and struggling to keep going, stop and talk to God about what’s happening in your life. Rather than feeling isolated and weighed down by the impossibility of your situation, include Him in the equation by praying: ‘Lord, help me to keep my mind stayed on You. During this time of busyness and stress help me to reorder my priorities according to Your will, to think Your thoughts, and to let the mind of Christ have its rightful authority in my life. Your Word says You’ve ordained peace for me. Because You are my fortress and my deliverer, I will not allow myself to be troubled or afraid. Thank You for keeping my heart and mind at rest through Christ Jesus. Amen.’</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 27:30–33, Num 31:48–54, 1 Cor 16:1–3</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 21 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Come aside by yourselves…and rest a while.’ Mark 6:31 NKJV</p><p>Pastor, How Are You Doing? (4)</p><p>There are two kinds of ‘tired’. And the dissimilarity is like the difference between puffy spring rain clouds and the clouds that precede a tornado. One is temporary and normal. It comes from a job well done, and after a period of rest you bounce back. The other is a chronic inner fatigue that accumulates over months, and doesn’t always manifest itself in physical exhaustion. In fact, it’s often masked by frenetic activity and impulsive behaviours such as: (1) You can’t relax over a meal or coffee. (2) You keep checking and rechecking your voice messages and emails. (3) Your bedside table is piled high with publications designed to keep you ‘ahead of the game’. (4) Taking a day off seems impossible. (5) You don’t take breaks and you work every holiday. (6) You can’t sleep. (7) Any free time you have is spent in ‘escapist’ behaviour like eating, drinking, spending and mindlessly watching TV. When we don’t rest, we lose direction. We’re lured away from God by the mistaken belief that determination and effort will allow us to achieve our dreams. </p><p>So, the truth is: while you’re busy working hard and looking important, you can lose your ability to hear the voice of the One who called you to your position initially. Yes, God expects you to work hard, but not by endangering your health, your family or your time with Him. If that’s the shape you’re in right now, Jesus is saying, ‘<i>Come aside…and rest a while.</i>’ If you’re wise and you want to go the distance—you’ll pay attention and do what He says.</p><h2>SoulFood: Job 15–17, John 19:8–16, Ps 128, Ecc 10:5–9</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 22 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘He will direct his children.’ Genesis 18:19 NIV </p><p>Godly Parents, Godly Children</p><p>Speaking about Abraham, God said, ‘<i>He will direct his children… to keep the way of the Lord.</i>’ Can God say that about you? When you get serious about raising godly children, God puts the focus where it belongs—on you! If you want to see important truths sail right over your children’s heads, try teaching them something you’re not personally committed to. Do you think your children are just being difficult? No, they’re watching you like a hawk! If your actions demonstrate that what you’re teaching them isn’t important to you, it’ll never be important to them either. And can you blame them? If you’re devoted to chasing material things, they will be too. But if you devote yourself to serving the Lord, they’ll be drawn to Him as well. Do you want to enjoy a long, happy life? Pass God’s teaching on to your children, and to their children after them (See Deuteronomy 6:2). Notice, your love for the Lord comes first: ‘<i>You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart</i>.’ (Deuteronomy 6:5 NKJV) Surprised? You shouldn’t be. When your lifestyle demonstrates your love for Christ, He’ll attract your children like nothing else on earth. Do your children see you reading the Bible? Do you discuss its truths with them in an engaging way? When behaviours and values come into question, do you lead them to the Scripture for answers? Why is this so important? Because the Bible says, ‘<i>Another generation arose after them who did not know the Lord.</i>’ (Judges 2:10 NKJV) In order to raise godly children you must teach them God’s principles, and practise them yourself. </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 18–20, John 19:17–30, Ps 113, Ecc 10:10–14</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 23 DECEMBER 2015</p><p lang="en-US"><span lang="en-GB">‘</span>God was kind! He made me what I am, and His wonderful kindness wasn’t wasted<span lang="en-GB">.’</span> <span lang="en-GB">1 Corinthians 15:10 CEV</span></p><p>Don’t Boast</p><p>If you’ve been blessed with success, read these words from Paul and take them to heart: ‘<i lang="en-US">God was kind! He made me what I am, and His wonderful kindness wasn’t wasted</i><i>.</i>’ Every good thing you have right now, plus every good thing you’ll enjoy in the future, comes from God. Try never to forget that! You say, ‘Wait a minute, I worked hard for this. Don’t I deserve a little credit?’ Yes, you do; the Bible says, ‘<i>Give honour and respect to all those to whom it is due</i>.’ (Romans 13:7 TLB) But praise by its very nature can be intoxicating. The human body is a remarkable piece of chemistry; pat a man or woman on the back—and their head starts to swell! Someone said ‘Praise is like perfume; if you consume it, it’ll kill you!’ That’s why Paul gives us this timely reminder: ‘<i>W</i><i lang="en-US">hat are you so puffed up about? …if all you have is from God, why act as though you are so great?</i>’ (1 Corinthians 4:7 TLB) One day King Nebuchadnezzar’s head got too big for his hat, and he boasted, ‘<i>Look at this great city of Babylon! By my own mighty power, I have built...</i>’ (Daniel 4:30 NLT) But God interrupted his proud moment and stripped him of his kingdom, and he ended up losing his mind and living like a wild beast. Only when he repented and acknowledged that God was the ruler over everything, did God restore his sanity and his kingdom. Corrected, humbled and enlightened, he knelt down and prayed, ‘<i>I, Nebuchadnezzar, raised my eyes towards Heaven, and my sanity was restored</i>.’ (Daniel 4:34 NIV) Boasting is a form of insanity—don’t do it!</p><h2>SoulFood: Job 21–23, John 19:31–42, Ps 117, Ecc 10:15–19</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 24 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘They saw the child…and worshipped Him.’ Matthew 2:11 NIV</p><p>This Christmas, Look for Jesus</p><p>The Wise Men couldn’t have imagined humbler circumstances than those surrounding the birth of Jesus. Max Lucado paints the picture: ‘The ground is hard, the hay scarce. Cobwebs cling to the ceiling… Mary looks into the face of her Son. Her Lord. His Majesty. At this point the human being who best understands who God is and what He’s doing is a teenage girl… She remembers the angel’s words, “His Kingdom will never end.” Majesty in the midst of the mundane. Honour in the filth of manure and sweat. Divinity entering the world on the floor of a stable. This baby had once overlooked the universe. His robes of eternity were exchanged for the rags keeping Him warm. His golden throne room abandoned in favour of a dirty sheep pen. Worshipping angels replaced with shepherds. Meanwhile the city hums, unaware that God has visited their planet. The innkeeper would never believe he’d just sent God out into the cold. And people would scoff at anyone who told them the Messiah lay in the arms of a teenager on the outskirts of their village. They were all too busy to consider the possibility. But those who missed His Majesty’s arrival that night missed it not because of acts of evil or malice. No, they missed it because they weren’t looking for Him!’ This Christmas, in the midst of the toys, the tinsel, and the tumult, stop and look for Jesus. If you know Him as your Lord and Saviour, take time to worship Him. And if you don’t, make Him your Lord and Saviour. If you do, it’ll be the best Christmas you’ve ever had. </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 24–28, John 20:1–9, Ps 97, Ecc 10:20–11:3</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 25 DECEMBER 2015</p><p lang="en-AU">Quite a Story, Isn’t It?</p><p lang="en-AU">‘…they presented gifts to Him...’ Matthew 2:11 NKJV</p><p lang="en-AU">In the Christmas story we learn that: </p><p lang="en-AU">(1)<i> God will use people you don’t know to bless you.</i> The wise men weren’t devout Jews or committed Christians, but Persian stargazers. Don’t be selective; you’ll tie God’s hands. Open your heart and you’ll start seeing Him reaching out to you through the most interesting people. </p><p lang="en-AU">(2)<i> God will take care of your tomorrows.</i> Joseph and Mary would have to leave home and flee to Egypt. What would they live on? Gold, frankincense and myrrh; gifts only the rich can give. When you’re in the will of God He will provide for you. He may do it through your job or the generosity of others, but He will do it. You don’t have to stay up all night worrying, trying to figure out how to make ends meet. The Psalmist said, ‘I have been young, and now am old; yet I have not seen the righteous forsaken, nor his descendents begging bread.’ (Psalm 37:25 NKJV) </p><p lang="en-AU">(3)<i> God will override the system and get you the help you need.</i> ‘The star guided them to where the young child should be born.’ In the history of the solar system there’s never been anything like it. God moved a star like we move a pawn in a chess game, that’s because He ‘works all things according to the counsel of His will.’ (Ephesians 1:11 NKJV) The story reads: ‘When they had come into the house, they saw the young Child with Mary His mother, and fell down and worshipped Him. And when they had opened their treasures, they presented gifts to Him: gold, frankincense, and myrrh.’ </p><p lang="en-AU">Quite a story, isn’t it?</p><h2>SoulFood: Is 7:14, Luke 2:1–20, Mic 5:2–5a, Is 9:6–7</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 26 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Jesus asked him, “What is your name?”’ Luke 8:30 NAS</p><p>Stop Putting Yourself Down</p><p>Remember the man in Scripture who was possessed by demons? ‘<i>Jesus asked him, “What is your name?” And he said, “Legion,” because many devils had entered him</i>.’ (A legion in the Roman army comprised some six thousand troops.) ‘Legion’ wasn’t this man’s real name; it represented his demonic oppression. He’d suffered with this oppression so long that perhaps he'd come to accept it as the new norm. Perhaps you’re struggling along a similar vein, naming yourself ‘Fatso’ because you’ve battled weight for so long with no apparent victory in sight. Or you define yourself as a ‘victim’ because you were abused or taken advantage of by others. Maybe you see yourself as a ‘failure’ because you’re divorced, or your kids have gone off the tracks. If so, it’s time to lose the negative labels and start seeing yourself the way God sees you. Jesus set this tormented man free, gave him his right-mind back, and restored him to his family. And He wants to do the same for you! Satan will take you from one extreme to the other. He’ll make you either boastful or bashful; make you think you’re ‘hot stuff’, or convince you that you’re worthless. Don’t buy it! Self-deprecation is often disguised as humility, when in reality it’s a rejection of God’s Word, which assures you that you ‘<i>can do all things through Christ who strengthens [you].</i>’ (Philippians 4:13 NKJV) What others call you doesn’t matter; what you call yourself does! The bottom line is: ‘<i>God is able to make all grace abound to </i>you<i>, so that in all things, at all times, having all that </i>you<i> need, </i>you<i> will abound in every good work</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 9:8 NIV) </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 29–31, John 20:10–18, Ps 139:1–12, Ecc 11:4–6</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 27 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘I must work the works of Him who sent Me.’ John 9:4 NKJV</p><p>Seeing Your Work as God’s Will (1)</p><p>You’ll experience a new level of fulfilment when you begin to see what you do for a living as an important part of God’s will for your life. Jesus preached and healed, but He saw it all as ‘<i>work</i>’ given to Him by His Father. You must too. Instead of seeing church as a place where you meet with God on Sunday morning, see it as a place where you’re fed and strengthened so that you can carry the presence of God with you into the workplace. ‘<i>Whatever you do, whether in word or deed, do it all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks to God the Father through Him</i>.’ (Colossians 3:17 NIV) Notice two words here: (1)<i> ‘Word.’</i> That covers skills of communication and information. (2)<i> ‘Deed.’</i> That covers skills such as creativity and building. Whatever you do, you’re supposed to do it with a thankful heart, as though the Lord were your boss—because He is. When you work with that attitude, you come alive. One person comes alive when they pick up a musical instrument, another when they lead a team, another when they counsel someone who’s hurting, and another when they’re looking at a financial spreadsheet. When each of us is doing what God designed and called us to do, the world around us is enriched. All skill is God-given, and we’re invited to live in conscious interaction with the Holy Spirit as we work, so that we can develop the skills He gives us. Work is a form of love. We cannot be fully human without creating value. </p><h2>SoulFood: Ps 103:8–18, John 3:16–18, Acts 2:38–41</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 28 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Do it all in the name of the Lord Jesus.’ Colossians 3:17 NIV </p><p>Seeing Your Work as God’s Will (2)</p><p>Research shows that the best moments of our lives don’t come from leisure or pleasure. They come when you’re immersed in a significant task that’s challenging, yet matches up well to your highest abilities. In those moments, you’re so caught up in an activity that time somehow seems to be altered; your attention is fully focused without your having to work at it. You’re deeply aware, without being self-conscious; you’re being stretched and challenged, but without a sense of stress or worry. You have a sense of engagement or oneness with what you are doing. This condition is called ‘flow’, because people experiencing it often use the metaphor of feeling swept up by something outside themselves. Studies have been done over the past thirty years with hundreds of thousands of subjects to explore this phenomenon of flow. Ironically, you experience it more in your work than you do in your leisure time. In fact, your flow is at its lowest ebb when you’ve nothing to do. Sitting around doesn’t produce flow. This picture of flow is actually a description of what the exercise of dominion was intended to look like. God says in Genesis that we’re to ‘<i>rule</i>’ over the earth, or exercise ‘<i>dominion</i>’ (See Genesis 1:26, 28). We often think of these words in terms of ‘dominating’ or ‘bossing around’. But the true idea behind them is that you’re to invest your abilities to create value on the earth, to plant and build and write and organise and heal and invent ways that bless people and cause God’s Kingdom on earth to flourish. </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 32–34, John 20:19–31, Ps 139:13–24, Ecc 11:7–10</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 29 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labour in vain.’ Psalm 127:1 NRS </p><p>Seeing Your Work as God’s Will (3)</p><p>When your skill level is high but the challenge of the task is too low, you experience boredom. When your skill level is low and the challenge of the task is too high, you experience frustration and anxiety. But when the level of the challenge matches the level of your skills—then you’re ‘in the flow’. We don’t work mainly for money, recognition, promotion, applause or fame. We work for the flow that comes from a partnership with God. We hunger for flow, and when it’s present, something happens in our spirit as we connect with a reality beyond ourselves and become a co-worker with God. This is why the psalmist says, ‘<i>Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it labour in vain.</i>’ Flow is part of what we experience in that partnership and, in that, God in turn uses flow to shape us. Bezalel experienced flow when he carved wood, David when he played the harp, Samson when he used his strength, Paul when he wrote a brilliant letter, Daniel when he ran a government, and Adam when he gardened. If other people report to you, one of the great spiritual acts of service you can perform is to ask whether they’re experiencing flow in their work, and help them experience it even more. When you’re working in the flow of service to God, when you’re experiencing flow in activities that enhance and bless the lives of others—you’re working ‘<i>in the Spirit</i>’. Paul was in the flow when he described himself as ‘<i>poor, yet making many rich; having nothing, and yet possessing everything.</i>’ (2 Corinthians 6:10 NIV) </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 35–37, John 21:1–6, Ps 116, Ecc 12:1</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 30 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘In everything give thanks; for this is the will of God…for you.’ 1 Thessalonians 5:18 NKJV</p><p>Be Grateful for What You Have</p><p>Theoretical physicist Stephen Hawking has a brilliant mind. He has been compared by some to Albert Einstein. But he has a rare degenerative disease called amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS syndrome or motor neurone disease). And it has left him virtually paralysed. He learned to use a computer with the tips of his fingers and was able to communicate his calculations and thoughts. Before he became ill, he described his life as a ‘pointless existence’. He drank too much and did very little work. But after discovering that he perhaps had only a few years to live, life suddenly took on an urgency and a new meaning. And he was actually happier than he was before. He explained the paradox this way: ‘When one’s expectations are reduced to zero, one really appreciates everything that one does have.’ When you’re told that you only have a limited time left to live, it transforms your whole perspective on living. Things you overlook suddenly become meaningful: the laughter of children, a sunrise or sunset, the love of friends and family, or just a walk in the park. The most miserable people in the world are those who believe that life ‘owes them’. They’re never happy, because they never believe they get what they deserve. The apostle Paul was in prison with no hope of getting out when he wrote, ‘<i>In everything give thanks; for this is the will of God in Christ Jesus for you</i>.’ What was he saying? Simply this: Instead of competing, comparing and complaining, focus on the good things God has given you, enjoy them and develop an attitude of gratitude (Philippians 4:8).</p><h2>SoulFood: Job 38–39, John 21:7–14, Ps 23, Ecc 12:13–14</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 31 DECEMBER 2015</p><p>‘Remember Lot’s wife.’ Luke 17:32 KJV</p><p>Don’t Look Back</p><p>Before God destroyed the city of Sodom, He sent two angels to rescue Lot and his family from it. Their instructions were clear: ‘<i>Do not look behind you nor stay anywhere in the plain. Escape to the mountains, lest you be destroyed</i>…’ (Genesis 19:17 NKJV) But: ‘...<i>his wife looked back behind him, and she became a pillar of salt</i>.’ (Genesis 19:26 NKJV) Jesus recalled this story in a simple statement: ‘<i>Remember Lot’s wife</i>.’ Here are two lessons you should learn and remember: (1) Don’t look back with longing to your old sinful pleasures and pursuits. The promise sin made was false then, and it’s still false now. ‘<i>Each one is tempted when he is drawn away by his own desires and enticed. Then, when desire has conceived, it gives birth to sin; and sin, when it is full-grown, brings forth death. Do not be deceived, my beloved brethren</i>.’ (James 1:14–16 NKJV) (2) Don’t look back with regret on the mistakes you’ve made. Lot’s two sons-in-law wouldn’t heed the message of the angels or the pleading of their father-in-law, so they stayed behind. Perhaps that’s why his wife looked back. But it was fatal then, and it’s fatal now. Don’t wallow in the regrets of your past. Stop dwelling on the injuries inflicted on you by others. Get your eyes off the rear-view mirror and onto the road ahead. God has great things in store for you; that’s what the battle in your life is about. Jesus referred to Satan as a ‘<i>thief</i>’ (See John 10:10). He has already stolen too much from you; don’t let him steal any more. Today commit your life to Christ, and watch His blessing begin. </p><h2>SoulFood: Job 40–42, John 21:15–25, Ps 77:11–20, Pr 9:10–12</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 1 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘I know the plans I have for you.’ Jeremiah 29:11 NIV </p><p>This Year Ask God for His Plan!</p><p>God says, ‘<i>I know the plans I have for you…plans to prosper you…plans to give you hope and a future…pray to Me, and I will listen to you</i>.’ (Jeremiah 29:11–12 NIV) This year ask God for His plan. It’s miserable playing a part for which you’re ill–suited. It’s like walking in shoes that don’t fit. So… what are you good at? What do you enjoy doing most? What accomplishments make you feel best? List five moments in your life when you were acutely aware of this feeling of fulfilment. Does this reveal anything about your purpose? If money wasn’t a consideration, how would you fill your days? How does this compare with where you are now? What one small step can you take right now—one phone call made, one letter written, one email sent—to move you towards your true calling? What have you learned about your purpose through failure? Are some areas clearly not a part of your calling at all? Who do you admire for the way they’ve applied their talents? Why are you like them? What can you learn from them? How would you describe your vision for your life this year? Or five years from now? Or ten? Who are the people in your life who really get who you are? Have you asked them what they think your purpose might be? Have they given any indication of how they think you should use your talents? If you could write your own obituary, what would you want it to say? What would you like to be remembered for? As you begin the New Year, ask God for His plan.</p><h2>SoulFood (New Year’s Day): Rom 13:12–14:19, John 1:1–14</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 2 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Where there is no vision, the people perish.’ Proverbs 29:18 KJV</p><p>What’s Your Vision for This Year?</p><p>What are you planning to do with this New Year? What you set your heart on will determine how you spend your time and energy. And it takes as much effort to live an unfulfilled life as a richly rewarding one. Some scientists have recently estimated that the human brain has between 10 and 100 terabytes of capacity, which means we all have lots of room for growth. One of the most rewarding things you can do this year is work to develop your mind. ‘<i>Where there is no vision [sense of direction], the people perish</i>.’ Dissatisfaction doesn’t come from the absence of things, but the absence of direction. Too many of us merely exist because we’ve settled for less than God intended. The quality of your life will be determined by your vision and the effort you’re willing to put into fulfilling it. So stop and make a written list of the areas where you’d like to grow this year, then tackle the three or four most important ones. Don’t get discouraged if the one you’re working on doesn’t want to co-operate; nothing great is ever created suddenly. Paul said of his faith, ‘<i>I press on toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God in Christ Jesus.</i>’ (Philippians 3:14 ESV) It’s a process; you have to keep plugging away. Some days it’ll feel like two steps forward and three steps backward. But don’t give up. It’s better to die for something than to live for nothing! And unless you try something beyond what you’ve already mastered, you won’t grow. So what are you waiting for? Life? It’s waiting for you—so get going!</p><h2>SoulFood: 2 Th 1–3, Luke 1:1–10, Ps 90, Prov 1:1–7</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 3 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘They looked the other way.’ Genesis 9:23 NLT</p><p>Dealing with Other People’s Failures</p><p>The Bible says: ‘<i>After the flood, Noah began to cultivate the ground, and he planted a vineyard. One day he drank some wine… and became drunk and lay naked inside his tent. Ham… saw that his father was naked and went outside and told his brothers. Then Shem and Japheth took a robe, held it over their shoulders, and backed into the tent to cover their father. As they did this, they looked the other way so they would not see him naked. When Noah woke up from his stupor, he learned what Ham, his youngest son, had done. Then he cursed Canaan, the son of Ham</i>.’ (Genesis 9:20–25 NLT) Have you ever uncovered something about a person in a position of respect, and you just couldn’t refrain from telling other people? If you have, think about this: if God trusted you enough to reveal someone’s nakedness or sin, maybe you weren’t meant to ‘see’ and ‘tell’, but to ‘cover’ that person’s nakedness with discretion, compassion and prayer. The Bible says, ‘<i>Discretion will protect you, and understanding will guard you</i>.’ (Proverbs 2:11 NIV) The fact is that Ham ended up being condemned, while his father Noah ended up in Hebrews chapter eleven being given honourable mention with the great heroes of Scripture. You say, ‘But I’m free to say whatever I like!’ Not true! The Bible says, ‘<i>A talebearer reveals secrets, but he who is of a faithful spirit conceals a matter</i>.’ (Proverbs 11:13 NKJV) What if God decided to show someone else your nakedness? Remember, what you sow, you reap! How you handle someone else’s area of vulnerability determines how God handles yours (Galatians 6:7). </p><h2>SoulFood: 2 Chron 7:12–16, Matt 6:5–15, Luke 18:1–8</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 4 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘He who invokes a blessing on himself…shall do so by saying, May the God of truth and fidelity [the Amen] bless me.’ Isaiah 65:16 AMP </p><p>Invoke God’s Blessing upon Your Life </p><p>The word ‘invoke’ implies these two things: (1) <i>to make an earnest request for, or to solicit</i>; (2) <i>to put into effect or operation, or to implement</i>. With that in mind, read this Scripture: <i>‘[It shall be] that he who invokes a blessing on himself in the land shall do so by saying, May the God of truth and fidelity [the Amen] bless me; and he who takes an oath in the land shall swear by the God of truth and faithfulness to His promises [the Amen], because the former troubles are forgotten</i>.’ That’s a powerful promise! God, our Father, spoke the world into existence, and we need to stand on His Word to frame the world we will live in. When you speak the blessings and promises of God over your life, you ‘make an earnest request and solicit it’. And by applying it ‘put it into effect or operation, and implement it’. This is why God told Moses to bless the Israelites with these words: ‘<i>The Lord bless you and keep you; the Lord make His face shine upon you, and be gracious to you; the Lord lift up His countenance upon you, and give you peace</i>.’ (Numbers 6:24–26 NKJV) Then God added, ‘<i>And I will bless them</i>.’ (Numbers 6:27 NKJV) Understand that what we speak to ourselves and to others can lead us down either a right path or one of destruction (James 3:2–10). God’s Word, rightly understood and applied will change things for the better, but remember, ‘<i>Death and life are in the power of the tongue</i>.’ (Proverbs 18:21 NKJV) So the word for you today is—invoke God’s blessing upon your life!</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 1–4, Luke 1:11–25, Ps 10:1–11, Prov 1:8–16</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 5 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘He who began a good work in you will carry it on to completion.’ Philippians 1:6 NIV</p><p>Don’t Let Fear Stop You (1)</p><p>Has God called you to do something you don’t feel capable of doing? Could you think of a dozen others better suited for the job? It doesn’t matter what you think, God didn’t choose somebody else! He chose you in spite of your limitations and insecurities. Your inadequacies don’t surprise Him. In fact, His ‘<i>power works best in weakness</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 12:9 NLT) Jon Walker says: ‘You may…hide your weaknesses from others, but you can’t hide them from God. He created you (do you think He made a mistake?) He created you with weaknesses to keep you on your knees… without them to push you back to God you’ll get prideful… and He won’t allow you to use them as an excuse for avoiding your mission or ignoring your purpose. If God is calling you to a monumental task, He will equip you to complete it—and that includes the Holy Spirit working from inside you. So focus on His strength, not yours. Don’t think about how incapable you are for the task. Remember, God is bigger than anything you face, no matter how overwhelming it may appear.’ The Bible says we were ‘<i>created in Christ…to do good works, which God prepared in advance for us to do</i>.’ (Ephesians 2:10 NIV) God’s plans are never an afterthought. He designed you for a specific purpose, and the One who ‘<i>began a good work in you will carry it on to completion.</i>’ So instead of letting fear stop you, let it motivate you to get up and get going! </p><p lang="en-US">SoulFood: Lev 5–7, Luke 1:26–38, Ps 10:12–18, Prov 1:17–19</p><p>WEDNESDAY 6 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘…Matthew got up and followed Him.’ Matthew 9:9 NIV </p><p>Don’t Let Fear Stop You (2)</p><p>Collecting taxes for the Romans was a lucrative job. But for a Jew like Matthew it meant betraying your own people. As a result he was despised and excluded from religious worship. But that didn’t stop Jesus from calling him to be a disciple. And when He did, Matthew didn’t hesitate; he ‘<i>got up and followed Him</i>.’ Here’s a man most of his fellow citizens would have considered a traitor. Jesus saw latent loyalty in Matthew, the hidden promise, the waiting potential. Others might have seen a loser but Jesus saw the man who would record His words and deeds and write a Gospel to bless future billions. It doesn’t matter who we are or what we’ve done, Jesus has a plan for us. And He wants each and every one of us to fulfil our God-given, divine purpose. It’s natural to be apprehensive when you’re facing change and uncertainty, but God says, ‘<i>Take courage!…Don’t be afraid</i>.’ (Matthew 14:27 NIV) Jon Walker writes: ‘God knows it involves a challenging stretch… He knows our abilities and resources aren’t what strengthen us for the journey (Philippians 4:13). When we fear we can’t do the things God calls us to do…that He won’t protect and provide…we embrace the lie that our circumstances are bigger than God, and our faith gets placed on the altar of our own perceptions. If you’re like me you often fear what’s behind the curtain of God’s call, and—frustratingly—He won’t let me peek… He keeps the curtain of our future drawn so we’ll learn to live by faith and not by sight, so we’ll become certain of what we hope for, and become sure of God even when we can’t see how He’s working in our current circumstances.’</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 8–10, Luke 1:39–56, Ps 42:1–5, Prov 1:20–23 </h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 7 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘This is My beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.’ Matthew 3:17 NKJV</p><p>Step into the Water</p><p>When Jesus was baptised, ‘<i>the heavens were opened to Him…And suddenly a voice came from Heaven, saying, “This is My beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.”</i>’ (Matthew 3:16–17 NKJV) That day when Jesus stepped into the River Jordan, He was stepping into the fullness of God’s purpose for His life. Those waters were teeming with the sins of mankind. John had baptised multitudes of converts there; their sins figuratively passing from them into the sea of God’s forgetfulness, just like the waters of the River Jordan end up in the Dead Sea. Maybe you’re appalled at the idea of Jesus wading into sin. But He was doing it to fulfil the purpose of God: redemption for you. Jesus was exactly where God wanted Him to be, doing exactly what God wanted Him to do. That’s why His Father announced, ‘<i>This is My beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased</i>.’ There’s a lesson here for you. Doing God’s will sometimes means stepping into messy situations and troubled waters. But when you obey God and do what He says, you won’t have to speak up for yourself or fight for yourself. God will command whatever forces are involved to yield to you, honour you, listen to you and even bless you. You won’t have to flounder around for the right answer, or wonder if something is right for you. God will give you the ability and resources you need because you’re where He wants you to be, doing what He wants you to do. So the word for you today is ‘step into the water’.</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 11:1–13:37, Luke 1:57–66, Ps 42:6–11, Prov 1:24–28</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 8 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Is anyone among you afflicted (ill-treated, suffering evil)? He should pray.’ James 5:13 AMP</p><p>Pray About It</p><p>It’s amazing how long we put up with things before we decide to pray about them. The hymn writer says, ‘O what peace we often forfeit; O what needless pain we bear. All because we do not carry everything to God in prayer.’ We complain to our friends. We wonder why God doesn’t do something. We wrestle with the situation in our minds, yet we fail to take advantage of the simplest solution there is—prayer. Charles Spurgeon wrote, ‘The desire to commune with God is intensified by the failure of all other sources of consolation.’ We’re all guilty of treating prayer as a last-ditch effort. When you say things like, ‘Nothing else is working. Maybe I should pray about it,’ do you realise what that says about you? That you really don’t understand or believe in the power of prayer as you should. You’re carrying burdens you don’t need to carry, and life is harder than it has to be because you don’t realise how powerful prayer is. If you did, you’d pray about everything—not as a last resort but as a first response. The Bible says, ‘<i>Is anyone among you afflicted (ill-treated, suffering evil)? He should pray</i>.’ When you’ve a problem: pray. When someone hurts you: pray. When you’re sick: pray. When you feel like giving up: pray. When someone you love is suffering: pray. When you’re discouraged: pray. When you don’t know what to do: pray. Jesus, who prayed early in the morning and late at night, said, ‘<i>Whatever things you ask when you pray, believe that you receive them, and you will have them</i>.’ (Mark 11:24 NKJV) So pray about it.</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 13:38–14:57, Luke 1:67–80, Ps 3, Prov 1:29–31</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 9 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘God…will not forget your work and the love you have shown.’ Hebrews 6:10 NIV </p><p>God Values What You Do</p><p>Satan will try to convince you that you don’t count for much in God’s Kingdom because you don’t have a high-profile gift like preaching, teaching or leading in public. Nothing could be further from the truth: ‘<i>God…will not forget your work and the love you have shown…as you…helped His people</i>.’ God sees you working behind the scenes day in and day out, caring for ageing loved ones, raising your children, encouraging others and contributing where you can. Will Rogers said, ‘We can’t all be heroes. Somebody has to sit on the kerb and clap as they go by.’ So when you think you’re too small to do big things, try doing small things with a big heart of love. You never know what you can do until you try! James Sizoo said: ‘Glamour isn’t greatness, applause isn’t fame, and prominence isn’t eminence. The man of the hour isn’t apt to be the man of the ages. A stone may sparkle but that doesn’t make it a diamond. People may have money but that doesn’t make them a success. It’s the seemingly unimportant people who determine the course of history. The greatest forces in the universe are never spectacular. Summer showers do more good than hurricanes, but they don’t get a lot of publicity. The world would soon die but for the fidelity, loyalty, creativity, and commitment of those whose names are unhonoured and unsung.’ Today God values what you do. ‘<i>Don’t get discouraged and give up, for [you] will reap a harvest of blessing at the appropriate time</i>’ (See Galatians 6:9).</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 15–17, Luke 2:1–15, Ps 46, Prov 1:32–33</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 10 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Whoever can be trusted with very little can also be trusted with much.’ Luke 16:10 NIV </p><p>Be Trustworthy in Little Things!</p><p>Jesus said: ‘<i>Whoever can be trusted with very little can also be trusted with much, and whoever is dishonest with very little will also be dishonest with much. So if you have not been trustworthy in handling worldly wealth, who will trust you with true riches? And if you have not been trustworthy with someone else’s property, who will give you property of your own?</i>’ (Luke 16:10–12 NIV) God won’t promote you beyond your current level of competence and commitment. Indeed, He’ll keep bringing you back to these two things until you get them right. As you walk with Him, He’ll increase your faith by testing you in settings that require only a little faith. And if you pass, He’ll expose you to circumstances that require more faith. Each time you prove your willingness to trust Him at a higher level, He will reveal a little more of Himself and entrust to you a greater measure of blessing. That’s how it works. Every small step of faith leads to a deeper, richer and more rewarding relationship with Him. When Michelangelo was painting the frescoes in the Sistine Chapel he spent endless hours lying on the scaffolding perfecting the details. It was a miserable job. A student, curious about why the renowned sculptor took such pains with details that could only be seen from a distance, asked, ‘Who will know whether or not it’s perfect?’ The master artist replied, ‘I will!’ And so will your Master—Jesus! What you’re doing today matters. It’s the determining factor in what God will call you to do tomorrow. So be trustworthy in little things. </p><h2>SoulFood: 1 Sam 3:1–11, Act 9:1–9</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 11 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘I shall not die, but live, and declare the works of the Lord.’ Psalm 118:17 NKJV</p><p>Growing Older, and Better</p><p>Today people are living longer and enjoying better health. Given that fact, it would be wise to glean from their wisdom and value their talent. You may have noticed that television advertisers are targeting younger and younger people. Why? After all, isn’t a tube of toothpaste sold to an eighty-year-old just as profitable as one pitched to a kid? The idea that life should be winding down at sixty or seventy makes no sense. Immanuel Kant wrote one of his best philosophical works at the age of seventy-four. Verdi penned his classic ‘<i>Ave Maria</i>’ at eighty-five. Alfred Lord Tennyson was eighty when he wrote ‘<i>Crossing the Bar</i>’. Michelangelo was eighty-seven when he completed the Pietá, his greatest work of art. Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes set down some of his most brilliant opinions at the age of ninety. Titian painted his famous Allegory of the Battle of Lepanto at the age of ninety-eight. President Ronald Reagan was one of the most powerful men in the world at seventy-five. Noah was over six hundred years old when he came out of the ark and helped to start the world all over again. David the psalmist wrote two things worth noting about getting older: (1) ‘<i>They shall still bear fruit in old age</i>’ (Psalm 92:14 NKJV); (2) ‘<i>I shall not die, but live, and declare the works of the Lord.</i>’ When the spotlight moves from you to the younger generation, don’t be discouraged. Just serve faithfully in the shadows, knowing that one day God will reward you openly for all you have done.</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 18–20, Luke 2:16–32, Ps 71:1–16, Prov 2:1–2</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 12 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Now to Him who is able to do exceedingly abundantly above all that we ask or think.’ Ephesians 3:20 NKJV</p><p>Give God Your All</p><p>If you only have a thimble-worth of capacity and you’re standing on the edge of a vast ocean, you have access to a lot of water but you won’t get much of it because your capacity is so small. If you have the capacity of a bucket you’ll get more than a thimble, but once the bucket is full the ocean can do you no more good. If you have a barrel you’ll get more than a bucket, but once the barrel is full you will still only have taken advantage of a miniscule part of the ocean. The idea is to offer God the biggest container possible. Offer Him all of you so that He can accomplish what He wants to do in your life. And no matter how successful you may be, you still haven’t maximised all that God wants to do in you and through you. Paul puts it this way: ‘<i>Now to Him who is able to do exceedingly abundantly above all that we ask or think, </i>according to the power that works in us.’ When you give your life to Christ, the Holy Spirit takes up residence within you. That means if your life has been a failure thus far, He can turn it into a success. And if your life has been successful thus far, He can take you to a higher level of success. That’s why you should begin each morning by praying: ‘Lord, I make myself totally available to You this day; work through me to accomplish Your will.’ That’s a prayer God will answer.</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 21:1–23:25, Luke 2:33–40, Ps 71:17–24, Prov 2:3–5</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 13 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘There is…a time to be silent and a time to speak.’ Ecclesiastes 3:1; 7 NIV </p><p>Speak Up!</p><p>The Bible has a lot to say about not criticising and passing judgment. But there are times when silence isn’t ‘golden’, it’s deadly. For example: (1) Silence is deadly when you use it as a passive, retaliatory means of expressing your anger or displeasure. That’s called ‘emotional manipulation’. Jesus said, ‘<i>If your brother sins against you, </i>go and tell him<i> his fault between you and him alone. If he hears you, you have gained your brother</i>.’ (Matthew 18:15 NKJV) Jesus is recommending pretty assertive behaviour by commanding us to take the initiative in addressing the ‘trespass’. Trespassing is the unauthorised crossing of a boundary, and many times we feel like we’ve been trespassed against or wronged. However, rather than addressing the issue directly with the offender, we resort to sulking and pouting. Jesus says, ‘Don’t do that!’ Your lack of communication can leave the wrongdoer unaware of their behaviour and make them more likely to repeat it. (2) Silence is deadly when you fail to defend someone against unwarranted criticism or vicious rumours. Don’t let fear of alienation and rejection cause you to let slander and character assassination go unchallenged, especially when you’re aware of facts to the contrary. (3) Silence is deadly when it results in your making an undesirable decision by default. The fact is, silence can indicate consent. Prayer was taken out of public schools in the United States because the majority stayed silent instead of speaking up. The Scripture says, ‘<i>There is…a time to be silent and a time to speak</i>.’ So have the courage of your convictions and speak up!</p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 23:26–25:55, Luke 2:41–52, Ps 74:1–11, Prov 2:6</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 14 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Stop being perpetually uneasy (anxious and worried) about your life.’ Matthew 6:25 AMP</p><p>How to Overcome Anxiety (1)</p><p>Here are some steps to overcoming your anxiety: (1) Talk to God. Don’t bemoan the collapse of an investment; ask God to help you. Don’t pace the floor of the hospital waiting room; pray for a successful surgery. ‘<i>Casting the whole of your care [all your anxieties, all your worries, all your concerns, once and for all] on Him</i>.’ (1 Peter 5:7 AMP) (2) Slow down. ‘<i>Rest in the Lord, and wait patiently for Him</i>.’ (Psalm 37:7 KJV) Jesus’ first miracle took place at a wedding. They had run out of wine, which was a social disaster in those days. Mary could’ve blamed the host for poor planning, or the guests for overdrinking, but instead she took the shortage to Jesus and He solved her problem. You can do the same. Assess the problem, and then take it to the Lord in prayer. (3) Don’t let your anxieties get the best of you. When a mosquito lands on you, you don’t say, ‘I’ll take care of it in a minute.’ No, you kill it before it can bite you. Be equally decisive with your worries. The moment they surface, deal with them. Before you rush to diagnose that mole as a cancer, have it examined. Instead of assuming you’ll never get out of debt, consult a financial expert. Be a doer, not a stewer. Horace Bushnell said, ‘Anxiety is a word of unbelief or unreasoning dread. We have no right to allow it. Full faith in God puts it to rest.’ The crosses we bear over anxiety concerning the future aren’t crosses that come from God. So give your anxiety to God, and leave it with Him! </p><h2>SoulFood: Lev 26–27, Luke 3:1–10, Ps 74:12–23, Prov 2:7–8</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 15 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘And the peace of God…will guard your hearts.’ Philippians 4:7 NIV </p><p>How to Overcome Anxiety (2)</p><p>Here are three more steps you can take to overcome anxiety: (1) List your worries. For one week, make a list of the things you worry about most. Children? Health? Money? Marriage? Job? These aren’t one-time worries that come and go quickly. They’re things that make you ‘<i>perpetually uneasy</i>’ (Matthew 6:25 AMP), so begin to review them. Ask yourself how many of them have actually turned into reality? Charles Spurgeon said, ‘Our worst misfortunes never happen…most of our miseries lie in anticipation.’ (2) Analyse them. You’ll detect recurring areas of preoccupation that may become obsessions: what people think of you; the fact that heart disease, cancer, and Alzheimer’s run in your family; the fear that you won’t have enough to live on when you get old. Identify each fear and pray specifically about it. (3) Live in today. God has promised to meet your needs daily, not weekly or annually. He’ll give you what you need—when you need it! ‘<i>Let us therefore come boldly to the throne of grace, that we may obtain mercy and find grace to help in time of need</i>.’ (Hebrews 4:16 NKJV) The old hymn goes: ‘Not so in haste my heart! Have faith in God, and wait; although He lingers long, He never comes too late.’ When the word ‘<i>worry</i>’ is mentioned in the Bible, it’s almost always following the words ‘<i>do not</i>’. If ‘<i>worry</i>’ features in your vocabulary, it should be as part of God’s words to you: ‘<i>do not worry</i>’. Philippians 4:6–7 NIV says to you, ‘<i>Do not be anxious about anything, but in every situation, by prayer… present your requests to God. And the peace of God… will guard your hearts.</i>’</p><h2>SoulFood: Phil 1–4, Luke 3:11–20, Ps 79, Prov 2:9–10</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 16 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Your heavenly Father already knows all your needs.’ Matthew 6:32 NLT</p><p>How to Overcome Anxiety (3)</p><p>Here are two more steps to overcoming anxiety: (1) Ask for help. Paul wrote, ‘<i>Outside were conflicts, inside were fears. Nevertheless God, who comforts the downcast, comforted us by the coming of Titus</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 7:5–6 NKJV) You’re not unique; others are facing the same fears too. By ‘telling’ on your anxieties, they begin to lose their power. Remember: ‘<i>Two are better than one…If one falls down, his friend can help him up. But pity the man who falls and has no one to help him up!</i>’ (Ecclesiastes 4:9–10 NIV) Share your feelings with someone you trust, and ask them to pray with you. People are more willing to help than you might imagine. Less worry on your part often means more happiness on theirs. (2) Focus on God, not yourself. Jesus concludes His call to calmness with this challenge: ‘<i>Your heavenly Father already knows all your needs. Seek the Kingdom of God above all else, and live righteously, and He will give you everything you need</i>.’ (Matthew 6:32–33 NLT) If you seek wealth, you’ll worry about every dollar. If you seek health, you’ll fear every blemish and bump. If you seek popularity, you’ll obsess over every conflict. If you seek safety, you’ll jump at every crack of the twig. But if you focus each day on God’s Kingdom, ‘<i>He will give you everything you need</i>.’ Elizabeth Cheney wrote: ‘Said the robin to the sparrow, “I should really like to know, why these anxious human beings rush around and worry so.” Said the sparrow to the robin, “Friend, I think that it must be, that they have no Heavenly Father such as cares for you and me.”’</p><h2>SoulFood: Dan 1–2, Luke 3:21–38, Ps 81, Prov 2:11–15</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 17 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘You have taught me from my youth.’ Psalm 71:17 NKJV</p><p>Claim Your Children for Christ</p><p>When a child is raised by praying parents who walk according to God’s Word, 85% of the time they’ll develop a strong faith before age thirteen. But what if your kids are already grown? One of God’s titles is ‘<i>Redeemer</i>’, which means He can give you another chance. Commit your life to Christ; that’s how generational cycles of failure are broken. Or what if you’re concerned about bringing a child into an evil world? The Bible says it’s the children of the light who push back the darkness (Matthew 5:14–16). God promised, ‘<i>My spirit and My words that I give you will never leave you or your children or your grandchildren, now and forever</i>.’ (Isaiah 59:21 NCV) You ask, ‘How can I compete with the negative influences around me?’ Every study confirms that a parent has the greatest influence—greater than friends, school, or the media—in determining the character and direction of a child. Think of it as a relay race. Success isn’t just based on how well you run, but on how well you pass the baton. Only when the story of future generations is told will you know whether you won or lost. The psalmist writes, ‘<i>You have taught me from my youth… Now also when I am old…do not forsake me, until I declare Your strength to this generation, Your power to everyone who is to come</i>.’ (Psalm 71:17–18 NKJV) Don’t drop the baton! Make it your goal to raise children who’ll pick up your legacy of faith and carry it further than you did. When you commit to doing that, God will work with you and through you. </p><h2>SoulFood: Judges 16:23–31, 2 Cor 12:3–11</h2></body><body><p>MONDAY 18 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Love each other with genuine affection, and take delight in honouring each other.’ Romans 12:10 NLT</p><p>Don’t Resort to Manipulation</p><p>Deep within each of us is a desire to run our own lives and, in some cases, other people’s lives too. As a result we become experts at manipulating one another. This desire for control brings about different behaviours. Here are six of them you must be aware of and avoid if you want good relationships: (1) Emotional blackmail. ‘Do what I want or I’ll get angry and go to pieces.’ (2) The guilt trip. ‘How could you do this to me after I’ve done so much for you?’ (3) The eternal illness. ‘Don’t upset me. Can’t you see I’m not well?’ (4) Help from beyond the grave. ‘Your dear father would have agreed with me.’ (5) Divine revelation. ‘God told me you should do what I want.’ (6) Humiliation. ‘Do what I want or I’ll embarrass you in front of others.’ These are powerful tools we use to get others to do what we want. And not only are adults good at using them, teenagers can be masters of manipulation too, especially if they’re not thinking straight. ‘I want this thing so badly I’ll go and do something stupid (even if it hurts myself) if I don’t get it.’ An argument that becomes a dangerous cry for help is the worst nightmare of many parents of teenagers. Manipulation is a game any number can play—right in the privacy of our own home. But those who engage in it pay a high price in conflict, hostility, and resentment. What’s the answer? The Bible gives it to us: ‘<i>Love each other with genuine affection, and take delight in honouring each other</i>.’</p><h2>SoulFood: Dan 3–4, Luke 4:1–13, Ps 84, Prov 2:16–19</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 19 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Love <span lang="en-US">suffers long and is kind…</span>’ 1 Corinthians 13:4 NKJV</p><p>Give Each Other Space</p><p>To be happy in a relationship, you must give each other space. And you have to be secure to do that. Someone said, ‘If you love something, set it free. If it comes back to you, it’s yours for life. If it doesn’t, it was never yours in the first place.’ When you constantly crave someone’s affection and try to cling to them, you create the very thing you dread—distance. By overreaching, you drive them away. Just as a drowning person grabs anything that floats, including their rescuer, a panic-stricken lover tries to hold on to the one who’s attempting to escape. That makes them even more frantic to get away. The story’s told of a guy who wanted to date a beautiful girl but she turned him down. He decided that the way to her heart was through the mail, so he began writing her a love letter every day. When she didn’t respond, he increased it to three letters a day. In all, he wrote more than seven hundred letters in a single summer. Not only did his plan not work—she married the postman! Appearing too anxious and available will drive the other person away rather than attracting them to you. Love is like a plant; when you smother it, it dies, but when you give it air, it thrives. There’s only one person who can ‘fix’ you, and that’s God. As you become more spiritually healthy you’ll become more emotionally healthy, and when that happens you’re more apt to find your needs being met. Paul bottom-lines it: ‘<i>Love </i><span lang="en-US">suffers long and is kind; love does not envy; love does not parade itself</span><i>.</i>’</p><h2>SoulFood: Dan 5–7, Luke 4:14–30, Ps 89:1–14, Prov 2:20</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 20 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘...I have learned the secret of facing plenty and hunger, abundance and need. I can do all things through Him [Christ] who strengthens me.’ Philippians 4:12–13 ESV</p><p>Be Confident in Christ</p><p>The Bible says, ‘<i>Blessed is the one who trusts in the Lord, whose confidence is in Him.</i>’ (Jeremiah 17:7 NIV) To succeed at whatever God calls you to do, you must learn to be confident—not self-confident, but confident in Christ. Paul was brilliant, but he said, <i>‘I can do all things through Him [Christ] who strengthens me.’</i> Jesus said, ‘…<i>without Me you can do nothing.</i>’ (John 15:5 NKJV) It seems to take forever to learn this truth. Much of our frustration comes from misplaced confidence. Paul says, ‘<i>Put no confidence in the flesh</i>.’ (Philippians 3:3 NIV) Now, he wasn’t saying you aren’t supposed to trust anyone. He was saying if you give others or yourself the trust that belongs to God alone, you won’t succeed. He won’t let you! To succeed at anything you must have confidence, but it must be confidence in God. You must believe that He wants you to succeed. You may fail on your way to success, but if you trust God, He will take your mistakes and cause them to work out for your good (See Romans 8:28). Sometimes our confidence is shaken when trials come, especially if they’re lengthy. When this happens you must do what David did: He ‘<i>encouraged and strengthened himself in the Lord</i>.’ (1 Samuel 30:6 AMP) When David had no one else to believe in him, when his men were so disappointed in his leadership they talked about killing him, he still believed in God’s ability to work through him. As a result, he got everything back that he’d lost. Nothing was missing. In fact, he received back more than he’d lost. Think about it. </p><h2>SoulFood: Dan 8–10, Luke 4:31–44, Ps 89:15–37, Prov 2:21–22</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 21 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘When the Almighty was yet with me, when my children were around me.’ Job 29:5 NKJV</p><p>Take Your Family with You</p><p>Vince Foster served as deputy counsel to President Bill Clinton. He allegedly committed suicide in a Washington DC park. A few months before his death, Foster was asked to speak to the graduating class of the University of Arkansas School of Law. This is what he told the students: ‘A word about family. You have amply demonstrated that you are achievers willing to work hard, long hours and set aside your personal lives. But it reminds me of the observation that no one was ever heard to say on a deathbed: “I wish I had spent more time at the office.” Balance wisely your professional and your family life. If you are fortunate to have children, your parents will warn you that your children will grow up and be gone before you know it. I can testify that it is true. God only allows us so many opportunities with our children to read a story, go fishing, play catch, and say our prayers together. Try not to miss one of them.’ Job’s seven sons and three daughters died tragically in a single day. Looking back on it, he said, ‘<i>Oh, that I were as in months past, as in the days when God watched over me…when the Almighty was yet with me, when my children were around me.</i>’ (Job 29: 2; 5 NKJV) If you sacrifice your children for your career, or for material things, you’ll live to regret it. Don’t let that happen to you. On your journey to success, be sure to take your family with you.</p><h2>SoulFood: Dan 11–12, Luke 5:1–11, Ps 89:38–52, Prov 3:1–2</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 22 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Blessed be the Lord, who daily loads us with benefits.’ Psalm 68:19 NKJV</p><p>Look for Things to be Grateful For</p><p>The story is told of a twelve-year-old boy who had never spoken a word in his life. As a result, his parents thought he couldn’t speak. Then one day his mother placed a bowl of soup in front of him and he took a spoonful. He pushed it away and said, ‘This is awful; I won’t eat it!’ The family was ecstatic. His father said, ‘Why haven’t you ever talked to us before?’ The boy replied, ‘Because up until now everything’s been ok.’ The only time some of us speak is to complain! You say, ‘But I’ve got nothing to be grateful for.’ Really? If you slept eight hours last night, there are millions of insomniacs who would gladly switch places with you. If you have a job, a roof over your head, and three square meals a day, there are millions of unemployed people who would like to have your problem. If you were able to get out of bed this morning and move through the day pain free, you’re blessed with the gift of health. Without it you would truly have something to complain about! And what about your salvation? What price would you put on that? Your sins have been forgiven, you have peace with God, and when you die you have a home in Heaven. Sure, we all have trials and tough days. But don’t insult God and belittle His blessings by saying you don’t have anything to be grateful for. It’s time you started talking to yourself, as David the psalmist did: ‘<i>Bless the Lord, O my soul, and forget not all His benefits</i>.’ (Psalm 103:2 KJV)</p><h2>SoulFood: Jas 1–2, Luke 5:12–26, Ps 91, Prov 3:3–4</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 23 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘I myself always strive to have a conscience without offence toward God and men.’ Acts 24:16 NKJV</p><p>Conscience, Your Sin Detector</p><p>When you go through a metal detector in an airport you are required by law to take everything out of your pockets. If you don’t, you set off a beeper. And if you try to hide a gun or a knife, you will probably end up in prison. Your conscience works the same way. When you knowingly do wrong, the Holy Spirit who lives within you will trigger your conscience and an alarm will go off inside you. If you’re wise, you’ll repent of your sin and make things right. Why? Because your alternatives aren’t good! ‘<i>Having faith and a good conscience, which some have rejected, concerning the faith have suffered shipwreck</i>.’ (1 Timothy 1:19 NKJV) Think of the word ‘shipwreck’, then picture the word ‘Titanic’. Getting the picture? When God says no, He’s not trying to be hard to get along with; He’s trying to protect you from the iceberg you’re sailing towards. Many of us have security systems in our homes. When we open the door we have thirty seconds before the alarm goes off and the police are called. God has given you an alarm system that works the same way; it’s called your conscience. And there are three things you can do with it: (1) <i>Turn it off</i>. (2) <i>Tune it out</i>. (3) <i>Allow it to guide you and walk in the blessing of God</i>. The writer to the Hebrews said, ‘<i>Pray for us, for our conscience is clear and we want to live honourably in everything we do</i>.’ (Hebrews 13:18 NLT) That should be your prayer today, and every day!</p><h2>SoulFood: Jas 3–5, Luke 5:27–39, Ps 96, Prov 3:5–6</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 24 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘I have betrothed you to…Christ.’ 2 Corinthians 11:2 NKJV</p><p>You Belong to Christ</p><p>In Bible days betrothal meant much more than engagement: it was part of the marriage ritual. As soon as a couple was betrothed, they were considered to be one. But the marriage wasn’t consummated for a year or more. During that time the groom would build their new home, continue courting his bride, getting to know her and allowing her to know him. And the bride would prepare herself by learning everything she could about her future husband so that she could please him in all respects. Finally the groom brought his bride to their new home and they began to live as husband and wife. So what’s the point of this illustration? Simply this: the Church is the bride of Christ, and we should be longing for the time when our union with Him will be consummated and we’ll partake of the marriage supper of the Lamb in Heaven (See Revelation 19:7). Until then Jesus is fulfilling His part by preparing a place for us, praying and interceding on our behalf, continuing to woo us, to lavish His love upon us, and to bring us into ‘<i>the knowledge of [Him].</i>’ (Ephesians 4:13 KJV) And what’s our part? Remembering that how we live our lives reflects on Him. No man wants his wife running around writing bad cheques, engaging in lewd conversation, getting drunk in public or flirting with other men. He wants her to refrain from those behaviours because he loves her and wants her reputation to be good. He wants his wife to be a good reflection on him and their family. In other words, your betrothal to Christ demands that you no longer live for yourself—but for Him! </p><h2>SoulFood: Ezek 47:1–12, Rev 21:22–22:5</h2></body><body><h2>MONDAY 25 JANUARY 2016</h2></body><body><p>‘Your face, Lord, I will seek.’ Psalm 27:8 NKJV</p><p>Seeking God’s Face in Prayer (1)</p><p>We get a remarkable picture of what can happen in prayer when we watch a parent and a little child. Imagine a one-year-old who looks at you and holds his gaze. You’re charmed. He looks shyly at first, tilting his head away and looking out of the corner of his eye. You do the same. It’s fun. He turns his face to look directly at you. You mirror the turn. Then there’s a sudden noise behind him, and he looks startled—you mirror his surprised look. He’s so startled that he’s getting ready to cry, so you shift to a smile. He does the same, and he’s soon gurgling with joy. When a child makes eye contact like this, when someone lets him know that they understand what he’s feeling, his brain and nervous system make crucial connections inside his body. He is experiencing what’s called ‘neural integration’. By playing the face game, you’re literally giving the child peace. It heals him. He finds delight in your presence. And prayer works like that too. In the Old Testament God instructed Moses to give the Israelites the following blessing: ‘<i>The Lord bless you and keep you; the Lord make His face shine on you and be gracious to you; the Lord turn His face towards you and give you peace</i>.’ (Numbers 6:24–26) In prayer we speak about ‘seeking God’s face’. That means sometimes prayer is about speaking, other times it’s about listening. But there’s a third ingredient. It’s the security that comes from sensing God’s smile of love and approval. </p><h2>SoulFood: Num 1–2, Luke 6:1–16, Ps 100, Prov 3:7–8</h2></body><body><p>TUESDAY 26 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘The Lord make His face shine on you.’ Numbers 6:25 NIV </p><p>Seeking God’s Face in Prayer (2)</p><p>When you study the life of Christ you realise that for Him prayer wasn’t an energy drainer, but an energy giver. And it can be the same for you when you come to see God’s face shining upon you as you talk with Him in prayer. When you’re with a critic who wants to argue, you lose energy. But when you meet with your best friend, you gain energy, and Jesus said, ‘<i>I have called you friends</i>.’ (John 15:15 NIV) Have you ever noticed how people in love sometimes speak to each other in baby talk? It’s immensely intimate and private—and it’s off-putting to a third party. But we do it because it is the most tender language we know. Jesus’ prayer life demonstrated this intimacy. He called God ‘Abba’, an Aramaic word much like ‘dada’ or ‘mama’. (Jesus spoke in Aramaic, and some portions of the New Testament are written in Aramaic rather than Greek.) ‘Abba’ was a Jewish child’s first word, because it was so easy to say. Somehow when Jesus was with God, the tender love that an adult offers to a child to give him strength is what He received from His Father. And you can have that same experience. It’s why Paul wrote: ‘<i>You have not received a spirit that makes you fearful slaves. Instead, you received God’s Spirit when He adopted you as His own children. Now we call Him, “Abba, Father.” For His Spirit joins with our spirit to affirm that we are God’s children. And since we are His children, we are His heirs</i>.’ (Romans 8:15–17 NLT) Your highest goal in prayer should be intimacy with God. </p><h2>SoulFood: Num 3:1–4:33, Luke 6:17–26, Ps 104:1–23, Prov 3:9–10</h2></body><body><p>WEDNESDAY 27 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Teach us to realise the brevity of life, so that we may grow in wisdom.’ Psalm 90:12 NLT</p><p>Make Every Day Count</p><p>The story’s told of a guy who went to Heaven and met St Peter. Peter said, ‘Tell me what good things you did in your lifetime.’ The guy replied, ‘Well, a gang of Hell’s Angels was beating up an old lady and stealing her purse, so I rushed in and saved her.’ Peter said, ‘When did this happen?’ The guy answered, ‘About one minute ago.’ Seriously, unless Jesus comes back, you are going to die. The psalmist wrote, ‘<i>Seventy years are given to us! Some even live to eighty</i>.’ (Psalm 90:10 NLT) Let’s say you’re sixty, and you live to be eighty. That’s two hundred and forty months! When you begin to think that way, time becomes a precious commodity and a limited resource, and you get serious about making every day count. Each time you say, ‘I’ll take care of that tomorrow,’ you’ve lost another day you can never get back. Here are some questions you need to think about. Have you discovered God’s will for your life and devoted yourself to fulfilling it? If not, why not? Understand these three things: (1)<i> God scheduled the date of your arrival on earth.</i> ‘<i>You saw me before I was born. Every day of my life was recorded in your book. Every moment was laid out before a single day had passed</i>.’ (Psalm 139:16 NLT) (2)<i> God has laid out a track for you to run on.</i> ‘<i>Let us run with endurance the race God has set before us.</i>’ (Hebrews 12:1 NLT) (3)<i> God will reward you for how you’ve lived</i> (See 1 Corinthians 3:11–15). So make every day count!</p><h2>SoulFood: Num 4:34–6:27, Luke 6:27–42, Ps 104:24–35, Prov 3:11–12</h2></body><body><p>THURSDAY 28 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Let us run…the race that is set before us, looking unto Jesus.’ Hebrews 12:1–2 NKJV</p><p>Keep Your Eyes on Jesus</p><p>At the Good Will Games in Edmonton, Canada, the Jamaican team was participating in the 4 x 100-metre relay. Those in the third leg of the race had a friend competing in another event nearby. While the sprinter was waiting for the baton, he looked up for a moment to try and see how their friend was doing in his event. Big mistake! In the next moment, the guy running the second leg of the race came up to him with the baton—and crashed into him. Needless to say, the Jamaicans lost because one of their runners was looking at the wrong thing. Instead of focusing on his own race, he was looking at someone else’s. </p><p>Who are you looking at—Christ, or other Christians? The Church is like a spiritual hospital: its members are in various stages of treatment, with the aim of becoming whole. So when you look to Christians you’ll sometimes be disappointed—but not when you look to Christ. One day Jesus told Peter what type of death He would suffer, and Peter questioned Him about what sort of death John would face. ‘<i>Lord, what about this man?</i>’<i> Jesus said to him, </i>‘<i>…what is that to you? You follow Me.</i>’ (John 21:21–22 NKJV) Have you ever watched a team rowing in the Olympic Games? They can’t see the finish line because their backs are towards it, so they keep their eyes on the captain. He guides them. He motivates them. He shouts, ‘Row, row, row!’ He gives them a cadence and keeps them on track. So the word for you today is—keep your eyes on Jesus.</p><h2>SoulFood: Num 7, Luke 6:43–7:10, Ps 107:1–9, Prov 3:13–18</h2></body><body><p>FRIDAY 29 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘His father…filled with love…ran to his son.’ Luke 15:20 NLT</p><p>Dad, Show Your Children You Love Them</p><p>Canoeing specialist Bill Havens was almost guaranteed to win a gold medal in the 1924 Olympics in Paris. But a few months before the games he learned that his wife would likely give birth to their first child while he was away. She told him that she could make it on her own, but this was a milestone Bill didn’t want to miss. So he surprised everyone and stayed home. He greeted his infant son, Frank, into the world on 1 August 1924. Though he always wondered what might have been, he said he never regretted his decision. He poured his life into that little lad, and shared with him a love for the rapids. Twenty-four years passed, and the Olympic Games were held in Finland. This time his son Frank was chosen to compete in the canoeing event. The day after the competition, Bill received a telegram from Frank that read: ‘Dear Dad, thanks for waiting around for me to be born. I’m coming home with the gold medal that you should have won.’ It was signed ‘Your loving son, Frank.’ Bill Havens wanted his family to know they always came first, no matter what. And that made him a hero to a little boy named Frank. Bill understood that medals tarnish, records are broken, and achievements are soon forgotten. These things don’t satisfy. What does? The love you have for your children, and the love they have for you. Jesus pointed out that even when a child is wayward, a parent’s love can restore them. Are you neglecting your family today? If so, take action immediately!</p><h2>SoulFood: Num 8–10, Luke 7:11–23, Ps 107:10–16, Prov 3:19–20</h2></body><body><p>SATURDAY 30 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘God’s law was given so that all people could see how sinful they were.’ Romans 5:20 NLT</p><p>Victory Through Rule-Keeping or Through Grace?</p><p>Why did God establish a new covenant with His people through Jesus instead of continuing with the covenant He’d given to Moses? Because while the law had the power to let people know how far short they fell, it didn’t have the power to make them want to obey it. Let’s suppose you have a tendency to eat too much chocolate. You want to be free from the habit, so you make a law for yourself: ‘I must not eat chocolate. I cannot eat chocolate. I will never eat chocolate again.’ You even convince yourself that for you it’s a sin to eat chocolate. But this self-made law doesn’t set you free from the desire for chocolate; it actually seems to increase your problem! Now all you can think about is chocolate; it’s on your mind day and night. Eventually you find yourself sneaking around to eat chocolate because you told everybody you were never going to eat it again. You can’t eat chocolate in front of people so you hide when you eat it, and end up feeling really guilty because now you’ve become a ‘sneaky’ sinner. Now you understand the pain that comes from being ‘under the law’ instead of free in Christ. New believers often focus their attention on God’s laws in order to control their passions, but it doesn’t work. As they mature, however, they learn to direct their attention to the leadership of the Holy Spirit, and discover that He can set you free from the desire to sin. The law requires living in perfect obedience, which we cannot fulfil; living by grace is relying on Christ and His perfect life of obedience, drawing each day on the power of God’s Spirit. </p><h2>SoulFood: Num 11–13, Luke 7:24–35, Ps 107:17–22, Prov 3:21–24</h2></body><body><p>SUNDAY 31 JANUARY 2016</p><p>‘Who am I…that you have brought me this far?’ 2 Samuel 7:18 NIV </p><p>Always Be Humble</p><p>A member of parliament took his little daughter to visit Westminster Abbey. As she stood looking up at its magnificent columns, her father asked, ‘What do you think, sweetheart?’ With childlike candour she replied, ‘I was thinking how big you look at home, Daddy, and how small you look in here.’ God’s presence has a way of humbling us. In the Old Testament, King David went in and sat before the Lord and said, ‘Who am I, O Sovereign Lord, and what is my family, that you have brought me this far?’ The Bible’s filled with examples of people who humbled themselves before God. In Matthew’s Gospel he mentions his own name only twice, and both times he calls himself a tax collector. And John doesn’t even mention his own name in his Gospel. The name ‘John’ that appears throughout his Gospel refers to John the Baptist. John simply calls himself ‘the other disciple’, or ‘the disciple whom Jesus loved’. Luke wrote two of the most important books in the Bible without ever once mentioning his own name. And Paul, the Bible’s most prolific author, referred to himself as ‘<i>a fool</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 12:11 NIV) He described himself as ‘<i>the least of the apostles</i>’ (1 Corinthians 15:9 NIV), and later claimed to be ‘<i>less than the least of all saints</i>.’ (Ephesians 3:8 KJV) In fact, as Paul grew older his ego grew smaller, and in one of his final Epistles he referred to himself as ‘<i>the chief of sinners</i>’ (1 Timothy 1:15). King David wrote no psalm celebrating his victory over Goliath, but he wrote a psalm of penitence confessing his sin with Bathsheba (Psalm 51). So, always be humble!</p><h2>SoulFood: Exod 16:1–35, John 6:30–40</h2></body></html>