<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" lang="en-US">
<head>
<title>???</title>
<meta content="Ben Poole" name="author"/>
<meta content="2015-09-28T01:45:00Z" name="dcterms.created"/>
<meta content="2015-09-28T01:45:00Z" name="dcterms.modified"/>
<meta content="UCB" name="dcterms.publisher"/>
<meta content="XMLmind Word To XML Professional Edition 1.0.0-beta04" name="generator"/>
</head>
<body>
<p>Sunday 1 November</p>
<p>‘Instruct the wise and they will be wiser still; teach the righteous and they will add to their learning.’ Proverbs 9:9 NIV</p>
<p>Feel the Yearn</p>
<p>Rightio then, grab a Bible(app), and keep it in hand. You’ll need it for the next few minutes. Have a read of Proverbs chapter 9. There’s a nice little spiritual sandwich: a layer of wisdom, buttered with a warning against folly, filled with some meaty slices about attitudes and consequences. The character called ‘Wisdom’ is pretty switched on: she’s organised, enthusiastic and inviting. Which is more than can be said for the character of ‘Folly’ (have a look at Proverbs 9:13–18). ‘Folly’ is everything ‘Wisdom’ is not. She’s reckless, foolish and lazy. But here’s the deal: they’re both inviting people to feast with them. (Proverbs 9:3–6 and Proverbs 9:16). The difference between them is that ‘Wisdom’ sends out her servants, whereas ‘Folly’ waits for people to come to her. The outcome? Those who have dinner with ‘Wisdom’ extend their lives but those who dine with ‘Folly’ experience the tragedy described in Proverbs 9:18. Now, you’re probably wise enough yourself to figure out that there’s a difference between ‘Fun’ and ‘Folly’, but we’re going to state the obvious anyway: you can be a fun person but still take your faith seriously. Take a look at ‘Wisdom’. She’s having a great time, but she’s all about setting people on the straight and narrow. Why? Because ‘Wisdom’ is all about respecting God. Have a look at Proverbs 9:10—wisdom comes into our lives when we yearn for the real and living God.<br></br>
Pray that God would help you to understand a little more about Him today and grow in wisdom as a result.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Heb 11:4–12:3, 1 Chron 17:1–20, Ps 18:20–29</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 2 November</p>
<p>‘Even to your old age…I am He who will sustain you.’ Isaiah 46:4 NIV</p>
<p>Alive and Kicking</p>
<p>The odds are high that you’re aware of the sorts of things that can become idols: money, popularity; in fact, anything that we spend more time, effort and devotional thoughts on instead of with God. Oops. So it does cover a whole plethora of stuff then. In Isaiah 45 and 46 the exiled Israelites are given a clear–cut choice: stick with Babylon and its gods, or turn to Yahweh. It’s a stark reminder that if we look to things that don’t draw us closer to God for satisfaction, we’ll be barking up the wrong tree. Only God can reach in to our lives and make a difference. The One who can change situations and rectify relationships. Isaiah 46:4 NIV says ‘<i>Even to your old age and grey hairs I am He, I am He who will sustain you. I have made you and I will carry you; I will sustain you and I will rescue you.</i>’ If you’re feeling a bit helpless at the moment (we’ve all been there) and you’re struggling for answers, turn to the Living One. If you feel like you’ve been looking for something to fill some sort of longing, check out Isaiah 46. The One who has a hand in your life has always been there, and always will.<br></br>Here’s a challenge for today: make a list of things that have become a bit of an idol in your life. Whether it’s as simple as too much Facebook, or something more clearly out–of–bounds, write it down. Then pray through each thing, big or small, and ask God to help you to spend more time with Him.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 38–41, John 7:33–44, Ps 96, Prov 28:17–20</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 3 November</p>
<p>‘A perverse person stirs up conflict, and a gossip separates close friends.’ Proverbs 16:28 NIV</p>
<p>Defuel the Fire</p>
<p>Gossip happens. (Unfortunately!) A lot. It’s found in the hushed, sideways comment or the sarcastic observation that might hit a little too close to home. We’re risking gossip, basically, whenever we’re not 100% straight with how we talk about others. So then… gossiping is easy to do. Especially when it might get a laugh or two. Let’s face it: ‘The words of a gossip are like tasty bits of food; people like to gobble them up.’ (Proverbs 26:22 NCV) Gossip might be easy to swallow, but it doesn’t do your health much good. Look up at today’s verse—‘<i>gossip separates close friends</i>.’ It can be a hard habit to break, but it’s worth taking that extra second to consider whether what you’re about to say has positive or negative value. <br></br>But... what about when people are coming to us with gossip? We can’t help it if they’re the ones gossiping, can we? Actually, we definitely still have a responsibility. ‘<i>Fire goes out without wood, and quarrels disappear when gossip stops</i>’ (Proverbs 26:20 NLT); see if you can, be the one to defuel the potential for a bad situation. Walk away from a conversation, or actually come out and tell people you’re uncomfortable with the things they’re talking about. You’ll know in your heart whether a conversation is healthy or not. If you get that shifty, unsure feeling about something, (lovingly and gracefully) call it out. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 42–44, John 7:45–53, Ps 86, Prov 28:21–24</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 4 November</p>
<p>‘…where there is no gossip, arguments come to an end.’ Proverbs 26:20 CEV</p>
<p>Win Some</p>
<p>Confrontation. It’s all a bit difficult. Sometimes even a bit awkward. But there are times when it is actually necessary to confront things. Especially when those things are squabbles with church friends. Matthew 18:15 GWT says, ‘If a believer does something wrong, go, confront him when the two of you are alone. If he listens to you, you have won back that believer.’ Yay, friends again! Let’s all move on. Oh… hang on. Jesus goes on a bit more: ‘But if you are unsuccessful, take one or two others with you and go back again, so that everything you say may be confirmed by two or three witnesses.’ (Matthew 18:16 NLT) Let’s be clear though, this isn’t a chance to point the finger. This is about accountability. We need people to keep us in check. In fact, the passage goes on to say, ‘<i>If they still refuse to listen, tell it to the church; and if they refuse to listen even to the church, treat them as you would a pagan or a tax collector</i>.’ (Matthew 18:17 NIV) Bear in mind that Jesus had a lot of time for pagans and tax collectors (Matthew 9:9–12). The Bible *isn’t* telling us to have nothing to do with the people who don’t listen to us. We’re being encouraged to win people back to God. We need to go out of our way so that people meet with Jesus through us. Even when we’ve been hurt. <br></br>Do you feel a bit convicted? Need to rectify a situation? Have a pray about whatever it is that comes to mind, and (only after a good pray and then a chat through with someone wise, if it’s needed) take the plunge and go deal with that situation.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 45–48, John 8:1–11, Ps 30, Prov 28:25–28</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 5 November</p>
<p>‘…to the married I command, yet not I, but the Lord…’ 1 Corinthians 7:10 NKJ</p>
<p>Future? Proof</p>
<p>If you’re thinking about marriage at all, you’re probably approaching it from one of three angles: (A) Not really interested at the moment, thankyouverymuch. (B) Sometime in the near future would be cool, I think… (C) Hi there. I’m married. I’m still learning the ropes as I go, because it’s a lifelong investment.<br></br><br></br>Today’s thoughts are aimed mainly at group B, you lucky lot. But A’s, this could be for you soonish, too. And C’s, some of this may resonate, make sure don’t tune out just because you’ve ‘been there, done that’. <br></br><br></br>A lot of people wait until marriage to make known what they expect from it. Things like ideas for the future, how you want to serve God together, how you’re going to spend/save. Amongst many others, these are all important things. They’re pretty exciting things, too. But. Waiting until a clash of opinion forces a friction–filled debate over what marriage is going to look like might not be best. Instead, getting a clear idea of what you expect marriage to be like (even if it seems obvious…) is a good start. That way, you can keep it in mind when you meet a special someone/to discuss it when you’re engaged/even when you’re married. Then, you can compare ideas and maybe even change your ideas accordingly. Going over ideas of what your future might look like doesn’t have to be pressured or awkward; working it through together just proves your future will be even more secure.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 49–52, John 8:12–20, Ps 123, Prov 29:1–3</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 6 November</p>
<p>‘Be kind… forgiving each other…’ Ephesians 4:32 NIV</p>
<p>When Life Hands You Lemons, Forgive</p>
<p>Forgiveness. It’s a nice little Christian word. We throw it about every now and again, especially when someone we know has been hurt. It’s easy to remind people to forgive. It’s even easy to tell them *how* to do it. ‘It’s simple’, we say, ‘just go and tell them that they hurt you but that you’ve forgiven them.’ Jolly good. Let’s all go and get a homemade lemonade. But, hang in there! What about when we’re the ones who need to do the forgiving? Ah, yeah that’s a bit tougher. Forgiveness doesn’t mean pretending you’ve not been hurt. You might not be ready to hold hands and skip off into the sunset with the person who has wounded you, but it does mean you’ve handed your hurts over to the One who can deal with them. Psalm 56:8 ESV says: ‘<i>You have collected all my tears in Your bottle</i>.’ He sees what’s going on. And He cares. <br></br><br></br>The other major reason why it’s worth forgiving people that hurt you? It’s already been done for you. God has led by example on this one. ‘<i>Be kind and compassionate to one another, forgiving each other, just as in Christ God forgave you</i>.’ (Ephesians 4:32 NIV) He looks at us, the people that let him down repeatedly, knowing that we will do it time and time again, and He still says ‘Forgiven’. Now that’s certainly something that we can be inspired by.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 53–57, John 8:21–30, Ps 15, Prov 29:4–6</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 7 November</p>
<p>‘Yes, again and again they tempted God, and limited the Holy One of Israel.’ Psalm 78:41 NKJ</p>
<p>Success 1: It’s A Hard Box Life</p>
<p>Living inside a box isn’t fun. Depending on the size of the box, you might have to sit all scrunched up with nowhere to go. Over time, life living inside the box would become more ‘normal’ than the wide world outside. A study on frogs illustrates how this happens. Some frogs were put in separate jars and at first they kept jumping around, trying to escape. But over time, they got used to the jar and, when the lid was removed, they didn’t even attempt to jump out. Why? Because they didn’t believe they could get out (and they’d probably knocked their heads one too many times). The Israelites did the same thing: ‘<i>they…limited the Holy One of Israel. They did not remember His power</i>.’ (Psalm 78:41–42 NKJ)<br></br><br></br>Woah–there, ‘limiting God’? Did we read that right? Well, it’s squashing a big idea into one word but, in a way, yes. God’s still God, He doesn’t have limits. When it says they <i>limited </i>God, it is better understood that they <i>doubted</i> Him—think of Jesus’ experience with people from His hometown of Nazareth for example (Matthew 13:58). When we doubt God’s promises and power it’s like cutting the legs off the chair we’re sitting on. But is that ‘limiting’ Him? Well, it’s certainly limiting His involvement in that situation. Helpfully, other translations of the Hebrew word here suggest this is like ‘wounding’ God. We know He can step in and help out, but sometimes He allows us to experience life as if He wasn’t there—and that saddens Him because He knows we need Him, plain and simple.  So about your situation: think you’re too young/old? Not smart/outgoing/fit enough? Whatever box we put ourselves into, let’s remember that God’s able to step in and blow our limits and expectations out of the water.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 58–62, John 8:31–41, Ps 115, Prov 29:7–10</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 8 November</p>
<p>‘And my God will meet all your needs according to the riches of His glory in Christ Jesus.’ Philippians 4:19 NIV</p>
<p>Success 2: Limited by Money?</p>
<p>Go read Matthew 6:25–34. Some people were worried about their daily necessities, but Jesus said, ‘<i>Look at the birds of the air; they do not sow or reap or store away in barns, and yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not much more valuable than they?</i>’ (Matthew 6:26 NIV) God asks us to trust Him to provide what we need, not work without Him to clutch for it. He’s got it all sorted. So take your needs to Him, work *with* Him at the centre of your plans, and you can even take the occasional breather and enjoy a cuppa. If you’re in need of money for something, you don’t have to somehow claw the cash together on your own. Be up for pulling your weight but, as always, God will provide.<br></br><br></br>There’s a flipside to this too. Don’t let *having* money limit you, either. (Whaaat? Well, read Matthew 19:16–30. Gulp.) You’ve probably heard of ‘tithing’, a great way that God’s people in the Old Testament put God first in all they received. The New Testament doesn’t mention tithing as a system but putting God ahead of our incomes is still the only way to honour Him with our money. Ever heard the well–known passage in Acts 2:42–47 where the early Church set an awesome example for us to follow? They gave to everyone in need. If we’re holding onto our money, or even our lack of it, above God, we’re probably limiting our potential to do great things with Him. A toughie for you: pray that God will give you an opportunity to help someone in need, today, and see how you could help them.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Kings 6:1–7, Matt 14:22–33</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 9 November</p>
<p>‘But you are a chosen people... God’s special possession, that you may declare the praises of Him who called you... into His wonderful light.’ 1 Peter 2:9 NIV</p>
<p>Success 3: Good Job?</p>
<p>The <i>Vision180</i> team will be the first to say that we can be hard on ourselves. To be honest, we may have even re–written that sentence five times. But being too hard on yourself can be detrimental to your success. Think about it: when you finish a project and others compliment you on it, do you accept the praise? Or come back with: ‘Well, this bit could have been better.’ Sometimes, no matter how much those around us, and even our Bibles, offer encouragement, the improvements that we think we have to be making stop us taking any compliments on a job well done.<br></br><br></br>‘Well, yeah, but I’m supposed to do my best,’ we hear you cry. Of course you are, and we should all, always, try to do our best (Colossians 3:23 style). But what if doing something with our ‘whole heart’ doesn’t mean overthinking and not ever being satisfied with our result? What if wholehearted work means that we can walk away when whatever–it–is is done, feeling like we’d done what we could, that God had enabled us to do our best? Spending too much time thinking over our mistakes or past failures will keep us from doing [our best] that. But take a look at today’s verse. That’s how God sees you. He has appointed you to do great stuff in this world. So He’ll enable you to do it, to the best of your ability. So, do something you enjoy today—just for fun. Even if it’s amateur hour. We bet you’re more talented than you think. And if you think you’re not, we don’t believe you. Ask a friend what they think you’re good at. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Is 63–66, John 8:42–59, Ps 99, Prov 29:11–14</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 10 November</p>
<p>‘Walk with the wise and become wise, for a companion of fools suffers harm.’ Proverbs 13:20 NIV</p>
<p>Success 4: Friends</p>
<p>Bad news: if you spend time around people who don’t have goals or dreams and who think making a difference is beyond them, you’ll begin to catch that way of thinking too. So what do you do? Who should you spend your time with?<br></br><br></br>We suggest surrounding yourself with people who will encourage you and challenge you. Our friends should be the people rooting for us or running alongside us. Whenever we feel less ‘HALLELUJAH’ and more ‘mutter mutter mutter’, disappointed that something didn’t turn out the way we wanted, our friends should be there. As they help us pick up the pieces, they should be the ones to tell us to get back in the race. It’s like the author of Proverbs said: ‘<i>Walk with the wise and become wise, for a companion of fools suffers harm.</i>’ (Proverbs 13:20 NIV) If we want to be truly ‘successful’, and make a difference in this world, it’s good to have wise voices around us—even if it’s just one friend who’s there to encourage, comfort, and challenge us.<br></br><br></br>Handy side hint: this works two ways, obviously. Sometimes you need to be that friend, for those who need it. But if you’re constantly giving, and aren’t being looked after yourself, you need to change something. Even if that’s as simple as telling your current friends that you need help sometimes. So, take a look at your current friend group. Which one(s) cheer you on and challenge you? Who has a positive influence on you? Call them up to get coffee, and share with them what you learned today and determine to be there for each other.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Rom 1:1–3:20, John 9:1–12, Ps 133, Prov 29:15–18</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 11 November</p>
<p>‘…he was not aware that his face was radiant because he had spoken with the Lord.’ Exodus 34:29 NIV</p>
<p>Hide it under a Bushel? No!</p>
<p>
<i>This little light of mine, I’m gonna let it shine</i>… How many of us remember singing that song in Sunday School? If you didn’t, just picture a bunch of kids singing loudly and holding pretend candles in the air. That’s pretty much what you missed. It may be a simple song for children, but it’s still relevant for us today. Let’s look at Exodus 34:29–31. God called Moses up Mount Sinai for forty days to show him the Ten Commandments. ‘<i>When Moses came down from Mount Sinai…he was not aware that his face was radiant because he had spoken with the Lord. When Aaron and all the Israelites saw Moses, his face was radiant, and they were afraid to come near him. But Moses called to them; so Aaron and all the leaders of the community came back to him, and he spoke to them</i>.’ Moses spent time in God’s presence and it changed him: his face radiated with God’s presence.<br></br><br></br>When we spend time with God and determine to learn from Him like Moses did, people will see a difference in us. It might make them nervous at first because we act and look different, but when we spend time with God, Paul wrote that ‘...<i>Then you will shine among them like stars in the sky</i>…’ (Philippians 2:15 NIV) Now you don’t have to go full Moses-style and live up a mountain forty days or so. But regularly spending time with God and learning from Him will transform you.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Rom 3:21–6:23, John 9:13–23, Ps 83:1–8, Prov 29:19–22</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 12 November</p>
<p>
<i>'Above all else, guard your heart, for everything you do flows from it.'</i> Proverbs 4:23 NIV</p>
<p>How Do You Respond?</p>
<p>One of life’s big tests: the trainee checkout assistant. You’re in a massive rush, the self–service checkouts are all broken (‘please send an electrician to the bagging area...’), and the only checkout open has a queue back to the bakery. Peering past the queue you notice that it’s a nervous guy’s first day on till, and he’s not particularly gifted at the barcode ‘beep’ game. How do you respond? Grumble and sigh your way down the queue line until you get to the guy living out his worst nightmare and snatch your shopping with a glare to make your point? Or do you chill, text ahead that you’re going to be late, spend the queue time praying for him and give him some encouragement as you pass?<br></br><br></br>Impatience isn’t exactly a new thing, and we’ve all felt it. But the impact of how we react to these prompts reaches far beyond the moment.<br></br><br></br>The Bible says, <i>'Above all else, guard your heart, for everything you do flows from it.'</i> Translation: Your actions and responses to situations determine what is <i>really</i> flowing out from your heart. Being friendly to checkout trainee will leave you feeling pretty good, whereas expressing your impatience will cause you to feel rushed and agitated for the rest of the day. Our responses make a difference in others’ lives, and create what comes out of our own.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Rom 7:1–9:16, John 9:24–41, Ps 83:9–18, Prov 29:23–27</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 13 November</p>
<p>‘Now give me this hill country that the Lord promised me that day.’ Joshua 14:12 NIV</p>
<p>A Mountain, You Say?</p>
<p>It was finally time for the Israelites to divide up the land they’d been promised after battling for it and enduring forty years of desert wanderings. Then Caleb said, ‘<i>Here I am today, eighty–five years old! I am still as strong today as the day Moses sent me out; I’m just as vigorous to go out to battle now as I was then. Now give me this hill country that the Lord promised me that day. You yourself heard then that the Anakites were there and their cities were large and fortified, but, the Lord helping me, I will drive them out just as He said</i>.’ (Joshua 14:10–12 NIV) Despite ten of Moses’ spies describing the Anakites as ‘giants’, who made them feel like grasshoppers (Numbers 13:33), Caleb wasn’t afraid. Even at eighty–five years old he felt just as strong as he did before—because he knew God would do as He promised.<br></br><br></br>No one would’ve blamed Caleb if he’d said: ‘Guys, I’ve reached my use–by date. I’ll just set up camp here and retire.’ But no. Caleb wanted what God promised, even though it looked an impossible task. But God had promised. The giants were on his mountain, but Caleb knew God was faithful. Whatever ‘mountains’ we face, if we face them with God, then we too can trust that He will do as He promises: not make them disappear, but give us His gifts and strength to help us overcome them. We’ll even be stronger and wiser for having done so.<br></br><br></br>If there are any mountains in your life right now, ask God to help you climb them.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Rom 9:17–11:36, John 10:1–10, Ps 20, Prov 30:1–4</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 14 November</p>
<p>‘I’m just as vigorous to go out to battle now as I was then.’ Joshua 14:11 NIV</p>
<p>I’ll Take a Mountain, Please</p>
<p>When Caleb, at eighty–five, said he was prepared to fight for God’s promise to him, he asked for a mountain. He didn’t say, ‘But God. They’re so big and I’m so small and old. Can’t you just wipe them out and give the land to me?’ No, he didn’t. Sure, he could’ve. He could’ve been like so many of the Israelites and complained and whined about the situation. Instead, he looked at the giants and said ‘bring it on’: he asked for a mountain and stepped into new territory. There may have been giants, there may have been a ‘Here be dragons’ sign on their front gate, but Caleb didn’t care. He was confident he could do it because of his faith in God.<br></br><br></br>So what does that have to do with you? With all of us? Well, we need to order up a mountain. Remember yesterday when we said life wouldn’t be problem free and we’ll all have mountains? We’re taking it a step further today and encouraging you to embrace your mountains. Whatever challenge or difficulty we face is an opportunity to go on an adventure and dream. Our dreams won’t come true unless we take risks, and what kind of adventure doesn’t involve some sort of problem or risk. Think of <i>The Hobbit</i> (book or movies, you decide...) Bilbo and the others encounter difficulty after difficulty, but it’s an adventure and the difficulties make Bilbo grow and become stronger, à la Caleb, and à la you, if you embrace your mountains.<br></br><br></br>We all have stories, so what’s yours? What mountains have you conquered? Type out your adventure story. See how overcoming your mountain made you a stronger, wiser person?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Rom 12–14, John 10:11–21, Ps 8, Prov 30:5–6</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 15 November</p>
<p>‘The Lord Himself goes before you and will be with you; He will never leave you nor forsake you. Do not be afraid; do not be discouraged.’ Deuteronomy 31:8 NIV</p>
<p>I’ve Got A Mountain. Now What?</p>
<p>Maybe after reading the past couple of days, you’re feeling a little overwhelmed. Maybe the thought of asking God for a mountain terrifies you. In Deuteronomy 31, Moses stepped down from leadership and Joshua took his place, and Moses told Joshua that God was with him. Joshua had a big mountain to conquer. He had to lead the Israelites into the Promised Land. And let’s face it, taking over from Moses meant Joshua had some pretty big shoes to fill. Joshua was about to embark on a new adventure and Moses knew that would be a huge challenge, so he reminded him of God’s promises: ‘<i>The Lord Himself goes before you and will be with you; He will never leave you nor forsake you. Do not be afraid; do not be discouraged</i>.’<br></br><br></br>Asking for, or being given, a mountain isn’t to be taken lightly. It’s a massive choice, but you’re not alone in it. God sometimes does ask us to do tough and terrifying things [but]. Whether it’s moving away from home to be a missionary or volunteering at a homeless shelter or training to become a doctor, He’s going to lead you somewhere. And whatever that looks like, or whenever you feel His calling, He’ll be with you from start to finish. Think about the past few days and what you learned about Caleb and Joshua. What stood out the most to you about the little bit you’ve learned about their character? How can you implement those characteristics in your life?</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Kings 5:1–27, Matt 6:19–34, Acts 5:1–11</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 16 November</p>
<p>‘Love each other with genuine affection, and take delight in honouring each other.’ Romans 12:10 NLT</p>
<p>You vs The Grain</p>
<p>You can probably think of a bunch of ways and places (like social media, and even in the real world) that people hide behind a pseudo–personality, and never really show much of their true selves. Sometimes the slightly more inward side of emotion—being courteous to strangers, accepting compliments, honesty about how we feel—can go amiss. Quite often, we’d rather not go near those things, especially when people are watching, for fear of seeming… well, human.<br></br><br></br>>But the truth is, putting ourselves out there a little bit can be pretty healthy. God wants to grow these ‘fruits’ in you: <i>love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, gentleness and self–control</i> (Galatians 5:22–23 NLT) and that can take raw humility. God knows that, when He gets to work in us and we live by those spiritual–fruits, people will see Him in us. It brings new life to a world that’s scared to open up. <br></br><br></br>So, going against the grain isn’t the easiest, but it shows God in us, big time. Jesus is the best example of this. Predictably, He had today’s verse down perfectly. When He was tired, He still had time for crowds of people. He didn’t complain about His disciples’ lack of understanding, but was patient with them. And, He delights in us and will never be scared to show it. Taking Jesus’ attitude to your school/work/local coffee shop is a huge step to letting God work through you. Here’s a challenge for today: do a random act of kindness for a stranger. Anything from paying for a bus fare to chatting to someone who looks lonely, you name it. Go for it.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Rom 15–16, John 10:22–33, Ps 50, Prov 30:7–10</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 17 November</p>
<p>‘Love each other with genuine affection, and take delight in honouring each other.’ Romans 12:10 NLT</p>
<p>Genuine?</p>
<p>Let’s roll with the loving–people–genuinely chat once more. We’ve looked at being genuine in our words and actions towards other people. In truth, there’s other ways we can stand out from the crowd. If you cast your eyes either side of today’s verse, you’ll notice there’s some other pointers to live genuinely:<br></br><br></br>(1) ‘…<i>Hate what is wrong. Hold tightly to what is good</i>.’ (Romans 12:9 NLT) Asking God to train you in learning what is truly good for you is a huge step towards wisdom. What will it result in? Being genuine with yourself. Sometimes we let ourselves do what’s wrong, and put off seeking God’s opinion because, frankly, we love our sin, we’re drawn to sin, and our flesh doesn’t want to change. Check out 2 Corinthians 10:5 NIV—‘<i>we take captive every thought to make it obedient to Christ</i>.’ Getting our thoughts in line with the new life Jesus bought us doesn’t mean we’ll be trapped into doing stuff we know–is–right–but–don’t–really–like. It’ll mean we’re free to live in the truth of what’s REALLY good, and not just a temporary thing.<br></br><br></br>(2) ‘<i>Never be lazy, but work hard and serve the Lord enthusiastically</i>.’ (Romans 12:11 NLT) Hard work doesn’t need to be grumpy work. Being enthusiastic and genuine in our efforts, whether it’s education or work, is good for us. It requires the self–control to decide not to do a half–hearted job or look like you’re doing work when you’re on Facebook.<br></br><br></br>Get to grips with these, and you’ll be living genuinely. Knowing you’ve got nothing to hide or disguise is a good place to be. Are you having to hide things from a boss/teacher/peer? Ask God to help you find practical steps to become effective again.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ecc 1–3, John 10:34–42, Ps 81, Prov 30:11–14</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 18 November</p>
<p>‘How joyful are those who fear the Lord and delight in obeying His commands.’ Psalm 112:1 NLT</p>
<p>The (Not–So–Secret) Secret To Happiness</p>
<p>Pssst, world: we’re certain happiness doesn’t stem from wealth or success. Making sure you get a good job isn’t a bad thing, but going to uni to be a doctor solely to make money and not because you want to help people will leave a certain emptiness. If we put our time and energy into things that ignore God’s kingdom, we’ll just be wasting our time. Success and money won’t make us truly happy, but what will? Read Psalm 112 (It’s only 10 verses. Short and sweet.) When we ‘fear’ the Lord, which simply means to respect and honour Him, and take joy in doing what He tells us to, we’ll be truly happy. <br></br><br></br>Paul puts this into perspective for us: ‘<i>But whatever were gains to me I now consider loss for the sake of Christ. What is more, I consider everything a loss because of the surpassing worth of knowing Christ Jesus my Lord, for whose sake I have lost all things. I consider them garbage, that I may gain Christ and be found in him, not having a righteousness of my own that comes from the law, but that which is through faith in Christ…</i>’ (Philippians 3:7–9 NIV) Before Paul became an apostle, he had a fearsome reputation, but he gave it up to follow Christ. He said he considered them worthless compared to knowing and following Christ. And where did he say such a grand comparison? From a rotten, stinking prison. Even there, in Christ, Paul had everything he needed.<br></br><br></br>Take your mood temperature. Are you happy? Joyful? Or are you weighed down with demands around you? Reread above and see what you need to re–evaluate.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ecc 4–6, John 11:1–16, Ps 76, Prov 30:15–17</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 19 November</p>
<p>‘But we understand these things, for we have the mind of Christ.’ 1 Corinthians 2:16 NLT</p>
<p>Muddled Words</p>
<p>How many times have you sat down to read your Bible and felt completely lost? Have you ever read an entire passage, chapter or book and wondered what you even read? The Bible is not only centuries old, but contains so many different types of writing (poems, historical accounts, names–of–who–fathered–who, visions from God…) that it can be a bit of a head–scratch in places. But that doesn’t mean we should give up. People wrote the Bible through the power of the Holy Spirit (2 Timothy 3:16), and through the same Holy Spirit we are able to better understand the Bible, so long as we ask for help.<br></br><br></br>1 Corinthians 2:9–10 NLT goes further: ‘<i>No eye has seen, no ear has heard, and no mind has imagined what God has prepared for those who love Him. But it was to us that God revealed these things by His Spirit. For His Spirit searches out everything and shows us God’s deep secrets.</i>’ There may be days when the Bible seems like a jumble of words, and overwhelmingly confusing, but God gave us the Holy Spirit to guide us through and show us His truth. The Holy Spirit also empowers Pastors, Preachers, Teachers etc to help us understand His Word. The wells to the depths of Heaven’s wisdom are right there for you, the absolute best ‘message from God’ material in the world is something you can hold in your hand, and the Author Himself wants to be your guide. So, sit with your Bible (app?) closed for five minutes. Ask God to join you, to study with you, and to speak to you through what you’re about to read. Then go to a passage that you’ve struggled over before, and see what happens.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ecc 7–9, John 11:17–27, Ps 102:1–11, Prov 30:18–20</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 20 November</p>
<p>‘Let Christ’s word… live in you.’ Colossians 3:16 GWT</p>
<p>Influenced?</p>
<p>Are you being ‘influenced’ by God’s Word? It is a daily, conscious decision we have to make. But if we’re really going to allow God’s Word to live in us we have to do a few things: (1) <i>Read it</i>. It’s not about learning to recite Scripture (though that’s not a bad thing, certainly), but reading God’s word, prayerfully, brings power and wisdom. ‘...<i>the Word of God is alive and active... it penetrates even to dividing soul and spirit, joints and marrow; it judges the thoughts and attitudes of the heart</i>.’ (Hebrews 4:12 NIV) (2) <i>Meditate on it</i>. Or, ‘chew on’ it. Let your spiritual digestive juices process God’s Word until its tasty wisdom–vitamins become part of you; strengthening, energising and directing you. (3) <i>Believe it</i>. ‘<i>My Word…always produces… It will accomplish all I want it to</i>.’ (Isaiah 55:11 NLT) That is, unless His word is not believed. ‘<i>The message… did them no good, because they only heard and did not believe as well</i>.’ (Hebrews 4:2 PHPS) We can know God’s promises but, to be fully effective in our lives we also have to believe them. (4) <i>Receive it</i>. We have a habit of thinking that for some reason God’s promises can apply to everyone else, but not us. Look, when we tell you ‘you’re special’ that’s not what we meant. There’s nothing about us that makes us so ‘special’ that God’s promises can’t reach us.<br></br><br></br>Write down five of God’s promises to us that are most important to you. Now rate out of 10 how much you really believe them to apply to you. Now, read through them again and say ‘I receive this’ to each.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ecc 10–12, John 11:28–37, Ps 102:12–17, Prov 30:21–23</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 21 November</p>
<p>‘…if we ask anything according to His will, He hears us.’ 1 John 5:14 NIV</p>
<p>Waiting</p>
<p>Want a peek into what ‘God’s will’ is? Hint: some of it’s written down (see 1 Thessalonians 4:3, 5:18, 1 Peter 2:15). If you want a good guide for praying in sync with God’s will, then praying using His Scripture is a pretty solid start. That Bible also says that: ‘<i>This is the confidence we have in approaching God: that if we ask anything according to His will, He hears us. And if we know that He hears us…we know that we have what we asked of Him.</i>’ (1 John 5:14–15 NIV) Which is pretty good, really. But. If you’ve ever prayed for something and not seen it instantly materialise, you might be aware that God will give us what we’ve asked for, but in His (best) timing. So we’ve some clues on God’s Word in the meantime… <br></br><br></br>(1) <i>Ask it</i>. Throughout the Old Testament, the prophets reminded God of His promises to Israel using the Scriptures. They didn’t think He was forgetful… but they knew the value of persistently reminding Him (See Luke 11:8). <br></br><br></br>(2) <i>Share it</i>. Deuteronomy 6:6–7 sets it out. Go read it. (To someone?...)<br></br><br></br>(3) <i>Obey it</i>. Chew over this one: Obedience to God’s word is faith in action. Obedience is getting in line with God’s plan and, in obedience, we will find that we are increasingly able to ask for things according to His will. Makes sense really.<br></br><br></br>Focusing on God’s will, in prayer, in speech and in obedience, will do wonders for your relationship with Him.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 1–3, John 11:38–44, Ps 102:18–28, Prov 30:24–28 </p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 22 November</p>
<p>‘I, the Lord, have power over you, just as a potter has power over clay…’ Jeremiah 18:6 CEV</p>
<p>From Clay to Pots 1</p>
<p>The process of becoming a pot from a lump of clay can’t be a pleasant one. The clay is shaped, left to set, and then put in a furnace. But at no point does the clay stop having a purpose. Although at times it may be difficult to see *what* God the Potter is doing with you, He promises that He is. We’re a work in progress and the situations we find ourselves in, and the feelings we face, can sometimes feel more important than that, but nothing is stronger than this Potter’s commitment to finishing what He began. That said, we have to remember that the Potter has the right to mould us as He sees fit (Romans 9:19-21). If the Potter needs a vase, the clay has no right to complain that it dreamt of being a soap dish. The Potter, not the clay, determines the end–product in the same way that the Holy Spirit determines our place and role in the Body of Christ (1 Corinthians 12:18).<br></br><br></br>God has created us each with an individual purpose. He has given us the things we need to fulfil that purpose and He’s preparing us for it. Sometimes we may not know what our purpose is. Sometimes it may even appear that we aren’t being prepared at all. But we have the Master Potter, and [but] we can trust that He is working something amazing in us.<br></br><br></br>Get crafty. (Don’t look at us like that, now). Make something today—it doesn’t have to be pottery, you could bake, draw something, make a treehouse… Just live the process of creating it. Oh, and while you’re admiring your creation, step back and ponder that God created your ingredients.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Deut 9:13–29, Luke 4:1–13 </p></body><body>
<p>Monday 23 November</p>
<p>‘…He made it again into another vessel, as it seemed good to the potter…’ Jeremiah 18:4 NKJ</p>
<p>From Clay to Pots 2</p>
<p>Yesterday we looked at God’s plan to craft us into all that we can be. And guess what? There’s more good news. When we decide to do our own thing, and shut ourselves off from being open–to–God’s–will, God is still waiting… and working.<br></br><br></br>What stops us from being open to God’s work? First up, pride. It’s a pretty heavy word, pride. We probably think of it in one of its harsher–sounding forms—maybe, like not accepting help even when we really need it, just because we think we can do it alone. And to be honest, that’s what we sometimes do with God. There’s a lesson from pretty much the whole of humanity: ‘<i>Pride goes before destruction, and a haughty spirit before a fall.</i>’ (Proverbs 16:18 ESV) Pride was the first step that Adam and Eve took in believing that they knew better than God. It’s tough, but it’s a useful warning: we need to be on watch in our own lives and make sure we’re not thinking we know better than God.<br></br><br></br>And next up, complacency. Ever been praying for God to touch a part of your life, and He does? Butttttt six months later you find yourself struggling with the same thing again. Why’s that? Chances are you assumed you had it sorted and stopped keeping check. When you struggle with something, it’s rare it will completely disappear. Complacency lets pride slip back in. Have a mental look back over the last six months of your life. What have you improved on? What have you let slip? Rather than beating yourself up over it (the fact you’re looking into it shows that God’s Spirit is in your life), allow Him to move back in. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 4–6, John 11:45–57, Ps 95, Prov 30:29–33</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 24 November</p>
<p>‘God’s Spirit makes us…self–controlled…’ Galatians 5:22–23 CEV</p>
<p>Rules, Rules, Rules</p>
<p>‘Christianity just has so many rules’; ‘You’re missing out on so much because of your faith!’—ring any bells? There is such a negative view of rules in society. Sadly a lot of people see Christianity as just that—rules, rules, rules. The Bible does show us God’s commands, which require self–control, but rules aren’t just there for the sake of it. There’s good reason to restrict what we can do and how we can do it. People *without* rules and self–control become slaves to their emotions, to their desires, to this world. God’s rules give us freedom (sounds backwards, but it’s 100% true). Freedom to live as God made us to, not to conform to society’s norms. That freedom, however, can only be released if we obey God’s rules. The good news is we’re not left on our own to do this. God has sent us the Holy Spirit who lives inside us all and, if we allow Him to, helps us to exercise self–control. But self–control isn’t just a physical thing, it’s a mind thing too. It’s one thing to stop ourselves from doing something or saying something but we find it so much more difficult to stop ourselves from indulging certain thoughts (side note: temptations aren’t sin. But dwelling on temptations becomes sin...) Jesus tells us that when we actively think about stuff that isn’t healthy, we are just as guilty as if we had actually done it (Matthew 5:28). So let us also, with the help of the Holy Spirit, learn self–control for our minds. Which of God’s commands do you find hardest to obey? Write it down. Now, write a way that following it could free you from something.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 7–9, John 12:1–11, Ps 114, Prov 31:1–5</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 25 November</p>
<p>‘…do not reject the Lord’s discipline…’ Proverbs 3:11 NCV</p>
<p>No, Sweetheart</p>
<p>Which is more loving:</p>
<p>(A) The parent who answers all of their kid’s questions with ‘yes, sweetheart’ (including the request to shave the dog with a vegetable peeler). OR…<br></br><br></br>(B) The parent who lets their kid know, lovingly, when something isn’t particularly good for them, or those around them. Even if it means the child gets upset.<br></br><br></br>Now, you probably guessed that we feel like the second answer would be a better style of parenting. We get the same impression from the Bible. Proverbs 3:11–12 NIV says, ‘<i>My son, do not despise the Lord’s discipline, and do not resent His rebuke, because the Lord disciplines those He loves, as a father the son he delights in</i>.’ God knows the consequences of the ‘yes, sweetheart’ type of parenting, and He loves us all far too much to let that happen. Because of that lion–fierce love for us, He’s good and gracious enough to point us to the things that are best for us. But that’s not always comfortable. Romans 11:22 NLT says, ‘<i>Notice how God is both kind and severe. He is severe toward those who disobeyed, but kind to you if you continue to trust in His kindness…</i>’ We know that it’s the most gut–squirmingly awkward thing to be confronted with legitimate problems with the way that we think, act or speak. We know that it can be hard to know how to react to that. We know that it’s, well, frankly horrid. But it’s all part of God’s best for you. Real, loving discipline is one of the strongest ways to inspire growth. So, think of the last person that told you off for something. Do something extra–specially nice for them today.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 10–12, John 12:12–19, Ps 118:1–9, Prov 31:6–9</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 26 November</p>
<p>‘Everyone enjoys a fitting reply; it is wonderful to say the right thing at the right time!’ Proverbs 15:23 NLT</p>
<p>Word Up</p>
<p>Over the next few days, we’ll be looking at words. In fairness, if you read this mag you’ll spend a fair time looking at the little beauties. All over the page, aren’t they? But. This time we’re actually getting to grips with the power of words themselves. The power to heal, restore, to bring grace into conversation. Use them wisely and they’ll become a tool for blessing others.<br></br><br></br>Ever said something without thinking, that caused hurt, or been totally inappropriate for the situation? Knowing the right thing to say can sometimes be difficult while, at other times, it’s second nature to us. Here’s the thing: what we say is formed by what we think, and what we think is formed by what’s in our heart. ‘…<i>As he thinks in his heart, so is he</i>…’ (Proverbs 23:7 NKJ) We need to get these three parts of ourselves aligned with God in order to be able to say the right things at the right times.<br></br><br></br>When we’re in a place to influence someone, it’s best to make sure our mind is set in the right place. If you can’t help but think how funny it would be if they fall over (literally or metaphorically), perhaps it’s not time to offer too much, words–wise. The best alternative is to think encouraging thoughts. Willing that person on, and filling your brain with good thoughts will fill your heart likewise. And since ‘<i>the mouth speaks what the heart is full of</i>’ (Luke 6:45 GNT), this kind of heart–filling is a good idea to fulfil the works God has prepared for us to do.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 13–16, John 12:20–36, Ps 118:10–18, Prov 31:10–13 </p></body><body>
<p>Friday 27 November</p>
<p>‘Pleasant words are as a honeycomb, sweet to the soul, and health to the bones.’ Proverbs 16:24 KJV</p>
<p>Words are a Beehive</p>
<p>There’s a story about an early–church believer called Ambrose. While he was asleep in his crib as a baby, a swarm of bees settled on his face and clustered round his lips. When his dad arrived, they flew off and left behind a drop of honey on his mouth. Old Man Ambrose, the story goes, nodded sagely and deduced that his son was destined for a life of speaking wise and sweet words. As you do.<br></br><br></br>Our faith knows all about the power of words to heal and help. Ambrose knew it. Jesus knew it. Way back in the ancient book of Proverbs, the healing and helping power of words is everywhere. Look at the verses before today’s verse: Proverbs 16:20–24. Then think about someone you know who is wise and honest right through to their heart. Doesn’t it change how you hear the words they say? And how, if they say good words about you, you feel them right through you? If you’re known as someone who always keeps ‘small’ details, or even big things back from people, then eventually your words will just skim off the surface of your friends and family. But, if you keep speaking from your heart to people, you’ll get respect and trust. The good words you say to them will have a wonderful effect, because they’ll know you mean them. A challenge for today: smear yourself with honey and run through the streets. Haha, no. Ask God to touch your lips and give you honest and healing words from your heart. (If that feels as silly as the honey idea, do it anyway. There’s real power in asking God for that.)</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 17–19, John 12:37–50, Ps 118:19–29, Prov 31:14–17</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 28 November</p>
<p>‘Let your conversation be gracious and attractive so that you will have the right response for everyone.’ Colossians 4:6 NLT</p>
<p>Words Are Not A Cold, Dead Thing</p>
<p>MIND THE GAP. STAND WELL CLEAR, VEHICLE REVERSING. EXIT THROUGH GIFTSHOP.<br></br><br></br>We hear words like these all the time—words that talk at us but not to us, that want something from us, that come from nowhere. The world is full of these cold words, and we even use them on each other. It’s easier to treat other people like they’re not there. It takes less effort. It’s easy to think that they don’t notice, and wouldn’t care if they did.<br></br><br></br>But actually, that’s not right. The way we talk to people can make all the difference. The language that we choose to use, and the effort that we put into it, can be a part of us demonstrating God’s love to others. God tasks us with being gracious in our words. ‘Graciousness’ is giving more of yourself to others than you need to—it’s paying attention to people, recognising them especially when you don’t have to. Graciousness in conversation is one of the first markers of an on–fire Christian. It’s the difference between nodding with your eyes down when people hold a door open for you, and looking them in the eyes and saying, ‘Thanks!’ It’s why people who care for the paralysed and very elderly often make an effort to be friendly to them all the time. When we expect to be treated like an object, someone’s kind words can make all the difference. Graciousness in conversation means changing the focus of your words from yourself to the other person.<br></br><br></br>Switching the ‘I’s in your conversation to ‘You’s can help here—it says to the other person, ‘I see you, I know you’re there, and you’re worth my time.’</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 20–23, John 13:1–17, Ps 146, Prov 31:18–21</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 29 November</p>
<p>‘If you confess with your mouth that Jesus is Lord and believe in your heart that God raised Him from the dead, you will be saved.’ Romans 10:9 NKJ</p>
<p>Jesus IS Lord?</p>
<p>There’s no better decision than choosing to believe that God raised Jesus from the dead, and knowing that this resurrection has given you a new life with Him. There’s nothing better than knowing that you believe, and can declare, that Jesus is Lord. If you’ve acknowledged that, BRILLIANT. (If not, give it some thought. Yeah?) Today we’re looking at what Jesus being ‘Lord’ means. Is it believing and declaring that Jesus is ‘Lord’ over all Creation, the universe and beyond? Yessir. Is it believing and declaring that Jesus is ‘Lord’ over your whole life? Yes–indeedy. Is the second one strangely more difficult? You betcha.<br></br><br></br>To look at the universe and conclude Jesus is Lord makes sense; we can see it exhibited in the amazing galaxies. But submitting to Him and recognising He’s in charge, that we have to put Him first, (*even* over things we like, or want) well, that’s going to cost us something (Luke 14:28-32). Becoming a Christian does bring the amazingness of God into our lives, but <i>willing</i> to live the Christian life is much harder (actually it’s impossible… without God – read Mark 10:27). Jesus tells us that part of His rescue of our lives is us mysteriously joining Him in His death—‘crucifying’ our own egos and our own priorities; in fact anything that might challenge Him being Lord of our lives. And a lot in us will tend to rise up and fight this Lord we’ve invited in. It’ll take us purposefully, daily, confessing that Jesus is Lord over us, today, to ‘crucify’ our disagreements with Him. But all of that safe in the knowledge that His will is *good* for our lives, it’s part of our rescue.<br></br><br></br>Take five minutes to chat with God. Are you crucifying your in–built resistance to Him? Is He truly Lord over your life?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Exod 17.1–7, John 4:1–42</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 30 November</p>
<p>‘Let the husband render to his wife the affection due her, and likewise also the wife to her husband.’ 1 Corinthians 7:3 NKJ</p>
<p>Attention, Please<br></br><br></br>Shah Jahan wanted to build something epic in memory of his recently–deceased wife. So he took her coffin and ordered the construction of the majestic white Taj Mahal to begin around it. How sweet. But. During the process, which took many years, he went one day to check the work and tripped over an old wooden box. He threw the box out in a huff. You can see where this is going… It took him months to figure out it was his wife’s coffin. Eeeeesh.<br></br><br></br>There’s a lesson in that which relates to 1 Corinthians 7:3. And you don’t have to be married to start practicing it. Giving people ‘the affection due’ to them is important, whether they’re our Mrs or Mr or not. Now, when we say affection, we don’t mean cuddles. We mean respect, attention, help… y’know, basic human stuff that applies to every relationship we have. Mostly, we approach our friendships and family relations with decent intentions. We <i>want</i> to give others the attention and respect they deserve. But, life happens. We can get so wrapped up in the stuff we do, the things that we’re (probably metaphorically) building, that we neglect those that need our love. Not massively, but we can get snappy, not reply to that text, or generally push someone to the bottom of our priorities. Not great. Especially when you check out Matthew 7:12 (go on…read it). Yup. The bottom line is, people matter more than the busy–ness that takes up most of our lives. And it’s vital to show them.<br></br><br></br>What could you do with right now? Food? A cup of coffee? Help with cleaning? Whatever it is, make/do it for someone else, before doing your own.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 24:1–25:18, John 13:18–30, Ps 14, Prov 31:22–24</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 1 December</p>
<p>‘…Don’t let the sun go down while you are still angry, for anger gives a foothold to the devil.’ Ephesians 4:26–27 NLT</p>
<p>Breathing Fire<br></br><br></br>To start with, it’s good to acknowledge that anger is a natural response to when we see wrong. Getting angry over everything is problematic, but even Jesus made His thoughts known when people disrespected God’s house (Matthew 21:12). It’s when we hold onto that anger that it becomes a problem. We’ve all been there. Gotten into an argument one day and replayed the situation over and over again in our minds, imagined ourselves vindicated. If we don’t try to respond constructively—and calmly—we leave the door wide open for [let] all the anger we’ve stored up in our mind to spill out. And that’s when the enemy can niggle his way in, and make you start acting on a completely different path to what God wants for you. Anger makes more anger. Let anger have enough breathing room, and you start breathing fire: people start seeing you as the dragon in the den (probably without the stash of golden cash?)<br></br><br></br>Here’s what Jesus teaches about letting go of anger: ‘<i lang="en-AU">So when you offer your gift to God...and you remember that your brother or sister has something against you, leave your gift... Go and make peace with that person</i>
<span lang="en-AU">...’</span> (Matthew 5:23–24 NCV) It brings much more freedom to channel your anger into making things right. As hard as it might be, giving full vent to your anger will only let it grow. Approach life in a way where you’re willing to not let your feelings get the better of a situation. Look to resolve. Have you got a thought festering in your mind? It’s time to pray for a way to approach whoever’s involved. Or, if that’s difficult, talk to someone you can trust. Don’t let it stay inside.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 25:19–27:46, John 13:31–38, Ps 65, Prov 31:25–27</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 2 December</p>
<p>‘Filled with love and compassion, he ran to his son, embraced him, and kissed him.’ Luke 15:20 NLT</p>
<p>Play the Prodigal 1</p>
<p>Many of us who have at least spent some time in church or looking through a Bible would have come across this familiar story. A son throws a tantrum, demands his inheritance, spends it very unwisely, then plods home to his dad... only for his dad to forgive everything and restore him to the family again. Great. We are often told we can identify with the son, the Father being God. That’s not wrong, but let’s play as a different character today. What if God wants us to be the father too? When the father hitches up his robe and starts running, it’s not just because he’s well excited to see his son. The elders of the village were planning to shame him in a ceremony in front of the whole village, which would then mean that he was effectively an outcast forever. But his father got there first, and forgave him before they could. The father ran because he knew that he had to get to his son with love and grace, before the villagers could get there with the law and accompanying punishment. Which is exactly what God did for us, in sending Jesus. So here’s our question: Are <i>we</i> being ‘Dads’ (not literally...) to those around us? Is there someone you know on their way Home, that you can meet halfway, to love them before they can be judged by those around (maybe other friends, family members)? How can we be the fathers to the sons around us? Rather than waiting for someone to ask to come to church, try to ask one of your mates who seems interested—meeting them halfway. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 28:1–30:24, John 14:1–14, Ps 130, Prov 31:28–31</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 3 December</p>
<p>‘“He was lost, but now he is found.” So the party began.’ Luke 15:24 NLT</p>
<p>Play the Prodigal 2 </p>
<p>While yesterday we looked at the idea of God wanting us to be like protective fathers to prodigals, it’d be a good idea to remember that we need God to be our Father, before we can do that. After all, who can be a father before they’re a son? (Yeah, that’s right, we get deep). Before we become joyful ourselves, we have to know we’re enjoyed. Here’s three things about the story that you might not have realised yet: <i>First</i>—when the son returned after being around pigs and muck for so long, he wouldn’t have been particularly banquet–ready. Frankly, he would have stunk. Yet his father clothed him in a rich robe. God covers our stinking messes up too, when we come home to Him. <i>Secondly</i>—the guy’s father put a big ring on his hand. That ring was the family’s ring, which they would’ve stamped in wax for business–type mail. He was truly a member of the family. Same for us. God doesn’t just scan our CV and sign us up for a part–time, optional–hours contract; He puts us immediately to work, as a key representative of His family. <i>Lastly</i>—he put sandals on his son’s feet. Back in the old times (when everything was in black and white...) only accepted, established sons wore shoes in public. The father was allowing anyone who came across the son’s path to see that he was 100% forgiven, and welcomed back. Yup. You got it. God offers us that, too.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 30:25–31:55, John 14:15–25, Ps 2, Ecc 3:1–4</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 4 December</p>
<p>‘To answer before listening—that is folly...’ Proverbs 18:13 NIV</p>
<p>Together</p>
<p>You will probably agree it’s a bad thing to make assumptions about others, but why, exactly? Well, if we’re going to put others first in a way that God would want us to, we’ll have to accept them and listen to their needs. Which is harder than we’d like to think it is. In theory, it’s easy as ABC to say we accept everyone as they are. In reality, it can be much harder to see past that ‘first thing’ we might notice about them, and it can be much easier to focus on what someone might be struggling with (notice how distractions are often negative things?) Brutally honest truth: they may well have some problems. Even more brutally: we don’t have it together either.<br></br><br></br>Matthew, one of Jesus’ disciples (who wrote the Gospel of Matthew), was a tax collector; a seriously looked–down–on job at the time. If Jesus had decided to echo the voices of the crowd and shun him, Matthew would have missed out. Equally, if Jesus never took a risk with fishermen and assumed they were just school dropouts, we’d have never heard from the likes of Peter. It can be a similar story when we meet new people; believing the best of people will probably involve taking some sort of risk with them. But here’s the thing: God took a risk with you, and has accepted you as His child. Instead of putting our thoughts first, let’s listen to what God has to say. When you next meet someone new, rather than letting those initial 30 seconds be a window for judging them, let it be a chance to ask God how He wants to work in their life.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 32–34, John 14:26–15:4, Ps 147:1–11, Ecc 3:5–8</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 5 December</p>
<p>‘…Do not think of yourself more highly than you ought…’ Romans 12:3 NIV </p>
<p>Helpful Horse</p>
<p>It feels good to be people’s first port of call, doesn’t it? When someone’s stuck with something, got a gripe, needs advice, and you’re the one up for the job. You might even be pretty good at it. Some of us have the kind of gifts that make us not just good listeners, but good advice–givers. If you’re one of these painfully talented folk (hats off to you), there’s still something that you need just as much as the rest of us not–so–superhumans: help. We <i>all</i> need it. Even if you’re the smartest of the lot, Proverbs 1 sums up what you need: ‘<i>let the discerning get guidance</i>.’ (Proverbs 1:5 NIV) If you only think of yourself as a white knight of helpfulness, you’ll quickly get booted off your own horse. Even the wisest leaders need to stay teachable, and open for others to give their prayers and guidance to. We’re not trying to knock you down a peg or two, or stop you from reaching your potential as an awesome–solo–person, we promise. We’re pointing out that stepping into your potential isn’t likely to be a solo effort. Having people to encourage us when we need help is just a basic human need. And we don’t stop learning from godly people. Let’s not forget the importance of looking to other Christians, and not just turning inwards. Have a little Bible study with yourself. ‘Google’ some passages for a theme (‘fellowship’ is a good bet for today’s reading), and choose a couple to pray over. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 32–34, John 14:26–15:4, Ps 147:1–11, Ecc 3:5–8</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 6 December</p>
<p>‘But they paid no attention…’ Matthew 22:5 NIV</p>
<p>What Keeps Us from Serving Others?</p>
<p>It’s easy to mentally check out from people’s problems and not offer help to those around us. Especially when it’s exactly 7.35 minutes before we’re about to head back home after a long day, and someone needs a person to talk to. Perhaps it’s easy to think you don’t care. That isn’t the greatest place to stay, though—serving others requires us to be open. Jesus told a parable about a king who was met with indifference from invitees for his banquet: ‘<i>They </i>took no notice of this and <i>went off</i>.’ (Matthew 22:5 PHPS) By being indifferent to people, we’re making the decision to put ourselves first, so that we’re comfortable and don’t have to get involved with other people’s lives. Elie Wiesel once said, ‘The opposite of love is not hate, it’s indifference.’ And, like those invited to the king’s banquet in the parable, it can mean we miss out on a whole lot. Sometimes, when people approach you for help, it’s a great opportunity to get stuck into God’s will.<br></br><br></br>Now, we’re not saying you need to devote huge chunks of your time to every single person with an issue who comes your way. But, in a world where there’s already a lot of backstabbing and lack of care, God is more than willing to use people who make the decision to show compassion and love.<br></br><br></br>What issues are there around you in your day–to–day life? Ask God to direct you towards just one today, and see how you can make a difference.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Kings 17:1–7, 1 Kings 18:41–46, Mark 4:35–41</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 7 December</p>
<p>‘Serve one another humbly in love.’ Galatians 5:13 NIV</p>
<p>Drop Your Scorn Bucket </p>
<p>Ever looked up those websites with a ‘cringe’ section in it? With the tales of how someone tripped up in front of their crush, or called their teacher ‘mum’ in front of the whole class (which everyone’s done at some time or other, so it’s fine, right?) No one wants to be a laughing stock in front of people—so we cover up with armour to keep ourselves protected from potential cringe. Do this enough, though, and we end up hiding who we really are, and stop being vulnerable to others we want to love. It’s easier to spot fakes than you might think. If we want to love people, we have to be open about ourselves.<br></br><br></br>Jesus dived right into potential cringe moments. He never hid His love for someone because He was scared of others’ scorn (check out John 4:1–42 if you’re not sure what we mean). Every time He was ‘<i>moved with compassion</i>’ (Matthew 9:36 KJV), He gave in to the impulse to serve others—with no regard to who other people would say He was. And He never dropped scorn on others for their weaknesses—which meant others were free to be vulnerable around Him.<br></br><br></br>So maybe it’s time to stop being so afraid of being embarrassed about who we are, and start being afraid that people aren’t being loved. Over the next week, every time you do something that causes you to feel embarrassed, write it down. Look back on it a few days later—you’ll find that most of the things that happened aren’t as ‘cringey’ as they first appear. Do the same again the next week, but write down opportunities you had to show love, whether you took them or not.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 37–39, John 15:18–27, Ps 148:1–6, Ecc 5:1–3</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 8 December</p>
<p>‘…don’t let us yield to temptation…’ Matthew 6:13 NLT</p>
<p>A Study in Temptation 1</p>
<p>There’s a subtle misconception about temptation that we’re calling out today. It’s the expectation that ‘your temptations will cease, or at least decrease’. It’s a crafty one, really. If we buy the subtle lie that Christian life gets easier, then when things go wrong, we’re much more likely to start looking for the exit. It’s exactly the sort of lie someone would want to whisper in our ears if they were some sort of deceiving personality who hated God and wanted to stop people following Him. Oh wait. <br></br><br></br>Flashback to Israel’s Exodus: having been liberated from the oppression of the Ancient Egyptians, and ready to be led towards the Promised Land, the Israelites would find themselves face to face with the Canaanites, who didn’t fancy inviting a new nation in. Self–doubt creeps in, then doubt of God’s promises, and suddenly both Project: Promised–Land and Israel’s entire relationship with God is in doubt. (Numbers 13:16–14:10 gives a heads up on this situation. It took God showing up to shut up the rebels. Give it a read.) God hadn’t abandoned Israel just because things seemed tough for them, He was leading them on to a new stage in their relationship with Him (in fact, that new stage was ‘giving them the Promised Land’. So, a good one then). Getting to the ‘promised life of victory’ where you’re so close to Jesus that nothing can rock you, requires  wrestling with the temptations that would threaten you along the way.</p>
<p>Take five minutes, and a notepad, to think about the happiest or most successful time in your life so far. Now just before it—what doubts or temptations did you have to overcome? </p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 40–41, John 16:1–11, Ps 148:7–14, Ecc 5:4–6</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 9 December</p>
<p>‘Blessed is the man who endures temptation…’ James 1:12 NKJ</p>
<p>A Study in Temptation 2</p>
<p>Moving straight on from yesterday, the second misconception in our sights is similarly sneaky: the idea that ‘temptation is sin’. No. It’s a lie. A clever, nasty lie. It’s the difference between someone else showing you a photo or video you shouldn’t be looking at, and you choosing to spend time studying it. You can’t help being shown but you can definitely choose not to fixate on it. Get this one locked in: sinful ideas aren’t your fault. Acting on them (even to hold on to them and think about them actively) is when you start to turn away from God. Satan wants to lever you away from your Lord. So, whilst he tries to get you to focus on whatever–it–is (jealousy? snide comments? porn?), if he can get you despairing in guilt over the idea even occurring, he can get a double score. But Jesus was tempted. Seriously so, after 40 days of being alone without food. And yet Jesus was completely without sin (2 Corinthians 5:21). We need to know this, not just to know the difference between temptation and sin, but also to know that Jesus has been there (Hebrews 2:18), so when He helps us, it’s from experience. Make sure you know what you can be accused of and what you can’t. Be clear about the right response to tempting thoughts (i.e. ‘No, I’m not going to indulge this. I know that what’s occurring isn’t sin, but I’m stopping this right now before it becomes sin. Help me, Jesus, to choose You right now’).</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 42–43, John 16:12–18, Ps 150, Ecc 5:10–12</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 10 December</p>
<p>‘…count it all joy when you fall into various trials [temptations].’ James 1:2 NKJ</p>
<p>A Study in Temptation 3</p>
<p>If Satan popped up, face to face, and said to you, ‘I’m here to make you feel condemned, feel far from God, and then make you sin,’ we’d call out for Jesus and tell Satan where to go before he’d finished speaking. As it is, he does his work in the shadows. But that doesn’t mean we can’t see some of his gameplan. Apostle Paul wrote ‘…<i>we are not unaware of his [Satan’s] schemes</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 2:11 NIV) If we know what to expect, we’ve got our defences in place to stay strong. And, better than even that, God knows what to expect, and how to use it for our good.<br></br><br></br>The misconception to blast today: ‘temptation is time lost and effort wasted’. If we’ve been battling temptation for a long time, it’s easy to feel like we’ve been going backwards in our relationship with God, not forwards. No. Staying strong in the face of temptation is part of maturing in that walk with Him (James 1:2–4 and 1 Peter 1:7 are good places to check this out). We reckon that God allows you to face these difficult, sometimes unpleasant times, not because He wants you to squirm, but because He wants a super–strong, honed relationship with you. A relationship where you’ve learned to choose Him even in tough times. That’s what’s in it for you, and it’s <i>massively</i> worth it.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 44–46, John 16:19–24, Ps 105:1–7, Ecc 5:13–16</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 11 December</p>
<p>‘I will not... alter the word that went forth from my lips.’ Psalm 89:34 ESV</p>
<p>Stand By Your Words </p>
<p>The story goes that, a couple of hundred years back, Spanish explorer Hernando Cortes arrived in the Americas and took all his crew ashore. Then, as they watched in confusion and horror, he set fire to all the ships. They may not have known what was ahead of them, exploring the land they found themselves in, but they knew they weren’t going back.<br></br><br></br>How often, especially today, do we have such a clear sense of commitment? In the world of Edit–Undo (shoutout to Ctrl–Z), and thanks to the little ‘x’ in the corner of our Facebook posts, we’re closer to being able to ‘un–say’ something than any time in history before. And, ah, sorry mate, but since I promised I’d do that, something has come up, yeah? ...hmmm. If we say something, especially to God, He’s pretty keen that we stand by our word. Pretty keen that we have a commitment, especially to Him, that is stands up against distractions.<br></br><br></br>Not all of the promises we make are sensible ones, or easy ones. When we make a well–meaning promise we end up regretting, we’re left to decide if keeping it is the most important thing. It’s difficult. Even more so if we make that promise to God. The motivator should be, ‘would keeping this promise deepen my relationship with Jesus, and/or help this world see Him?’ If in doubt, just ask Him what is important.<br></br><br></br>Quickly flick through your last messages–what’s the last thing you said you’d do for someone? (Nice things only please though, okay?) If you’ve not done it, sort it before the day is out.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 47–49, John 16:25–33, Ps 105:8–22, Ecc 7:1–4</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 12 December</p>
<p>‘Owe nothing to anyone—except for your obligation to love one another….’ Romans 13:8 NLT</p>
<p>Debt and a Half</p>
<p>Without the handy subtitle (added at a later date by translators to help us navigate around the Bible), the way that Paul wrote these verses would have read straight through, something like this: ‘<i>Give to everyone what you owe them: if you owe taxes, pay taxes; if revenue, then revenue; if respect, then respect; if honour, then honour. Let no debt remain outstanding, except the continuing debt to love one another, for whoever loves others has fulfilled the law.</i>’ (Romans 13:7–8 NIV) Right then, that gives us a bit more context to work with. It looks like, when Paul says debt, he means more than just money. Financial debt is definitely included, but so are debts of honour and respect. Which isn’t quite as simple as paying your mate back the fiver you owe for pizza. Drats. How can we manage to give everyone everything that they deserve, then?<br></br><br></br>Well, we reckon that Paul’s whole life approach to giving people their dues comes easier when we focus on one thing. Generosity. It’s all about being willing. Have a read of 2 Corinthians 9:7. What if we can apply that as a whole–life thing, too? Whether it’s paying back cash, giving respect to someone, or sharing the love of God, there’s no point [in sharing the love] if you do it with a frown, or because you feel arm–twisted into it. But decide in your heart to give everything that you owe generously, and you’ll feel the difference. So, give back more than you owe today. Whether it really is a fiver for pizza, or something like honouring someone for something they’ve done, give it that little bit more than you have to.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Gen 50, Hag 1–2, John 17:1–12, Ps 105:23–36, Ecc 7:5–8</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 13 December</p>
<p>‘This is My commandment, that you love one another as I have loved you.’ John 15:12 NKJ</p>
<p>Wouldn’t It Be Nice?</p>
<p>Ever had a second chocolate bar drop out of a vending machine? Yeah... we haven’t either. That sort of thing, though, as brilliant as it would be, would only change our mood for a short while. The stuff that can really inspire us happens when people actively do good things for us. Have you ever had someone do something so generous that you asked them ‘why me?’ That stuff can really impact us, because someone has had to hold a thought about us for longer than a second to make those sorts of active decisions.<br></br><br></br>So, what about when it comes to us Christians? How can we do all of that heart–warming good stuff, and have it be 100% God–inspired and God–orientated? Well, John 15:12 NIV says, ‘<i>My command is this: Love each other as I have loved you</i>.’ Ah. So it’s about more than just baking someone a cake then. Doing nice stuff for people is great (and we wouldn’t say ‘no’ to a chocolate cupcake, if you’re offering), but God is all about the heart behind it. What matters most to God is that we love people like He loves them. Non–judgmentally, caringly, compassionately, amazingly and unconditionally. Whether it’s the small stuff, or the big stuff, whatever you do for others needs to come from a prayerful place of real love. Not of token–gesture niceties. That’s a high calling, but it’s what makes the difference between being ‘nice’ and being Jesus–led. There’s probably going to be a chance (soon) to show someone a real act of love. Don’t chicken out when it comes your way. Pray that you’ll be prepared to see it, and then do it.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Kings 17:17–24, Mark 5:21–43, John 11:1–45</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 14 December</p>
<p>‘…Make every effort to add to your faith…’ 2 Peter 1:5 NIV</p>
<p>Grow–Pro</p>
<p>Have a read of 2 Peter 1:3–8. (Seriously, it’ll be worth your while). This chunk of Scripture is a reminder that God has acted and now we need to live in the light of that Truth. The New Living Translation puts verses 5–9 like this: ‘…<i lang="en-AU">make every effort to respond to God’s promises. Supplement your faith with a generous provision of moral excellence, and moral excellence with knowledge, and knowledge with self-control, and self-control with patient endurance, and patient endurance with godliness, and godliness with brotherly affection, and brotherly affection with love for everyone. The more you grow like this, the more productive and useful you will be in your knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ</i>.’ So, build on what God’s already done, yearn to learn, and develop your character. Sweet. But, what does that *actually* look like? It’ll be different for each of us. Whether it’s getting involved in church life or spending time in prayer, you can be sure that if you’re ready to grow and you’ve invited God to stretch you, it’ll happen. When we’re actively seeking Jesus through our actions and prayers He will grow us (sometimes without us even noticing). It will push us to our limits and build our faith. And that’s worth chasing.<br></br><br></br>Every chase starts with a first step. The whole ‘becoming mature’ thing can feel huge, but it’s 100% doable. We just need to be willing, and take it bit by bit. So: write down three things that you reckon might get you growing in your faith. Pray each one through, then write your first step towards each action. Get going, and tick ’em off as you do them. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Est 1–4, John 17:13–26, Ps 105:37–45, Ecc 7:9–12</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 15 December</p>
<p>‘…Who sinned, this man or his parents…?’ John 9:2 NKJ</p>
<p>But Now I See 1</p>
<p>‘How did this guy end up blind? Did he sin? Did his parents sin?’ That’s essentially what Jesus’ disciples asked him when they all met a man who was blind from birth. Jesus’ answer was pretty surprising to everyone: ‘<i>Neither this man nor his parents sinned</i>.’ (John 9:3 NIV) Now, Jesus isn’t claiming this guy is free from sin (only He’s that). He’s aware that we’re all sinners. So, what’s He getting at? Firstly, Jesus demonstrated that God takes responsibility for the man’s blindness (see also Exodus 4:11, Prov 16:4) and revealed that God has a purpose, even for evil and suffering. The disciple’s assumed that suffering was the direct result of sin somewhere along the line. It must be his fault. Or his parents. To them, that was the only possible explanation. But Jesus says ‘…<i>this happened so that the works of God might be displayed in him</i>.’ (John 9:3 NIV) Secondly, rather than pointing the finger, jumping to conclusions or looking for causal connections, Jesus is setting their attitude straight. He doesn’t just answer their question—He changes it. Instead of ‘Whose fault is this?’ Jesus wants them to ask, ‘What can we do to heal him?’ He’s pointing out the need to see suffering as an occasion to reveal God’s glory. Now that’s a pretty tall order. It can be tough to find God in painful situations. But Jesus puts it into perspective once again, ‘<i>As long as it is day, we must do the works of Him who sent Me</i>...’ (John 9:4–5 NIV) Whatever the situation, Jesus can be found in it. Let’s look for opportunities for His glory, and keep the finger–pointing or panicking to a minimum.<br></br><br></br>Who do you know that’s going through tough stuff? Get together and pray with them. Pray specifically that God’s glory would come from the situation. It’s really hard to do, but it’s worth it.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Est 5–10, John 18:1–11, Ps 18:1–29, Prov 26:24–27</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 16 December</p>
<p>‘…He spit on the ground, made some mud with the saliva, and put it on the man’s eyes.’ John 9:6 NIV</p>
<p>But Now I See 2</p>
<p>Right, we’ve covered the first bit of Jesus’ encounter. Then comes the healing. In John 9:6–17, the Pharisees aren’t too happy. What? Did they not like a good happily–ever–after? Weren’t they fans of amazing miracles? Actually, they took issue with what Jesus physically did. In spitting on mud, Jesus had made clay. It wasn’t that they hated mud or clay. Their issue was that Jesus *made* something on the Sabbath. In fact, in John 9:16 NIV, the Pharisees said, ‘<i>This man is not from God, for He does not keep the Sabbath</i>.’ Not only was He making stuff, He was healing people. And they struggled with that too, ‘<i>How can a sinner perform such signs?</i>’ they asked. (John 9:16 NIV) <br></br><br></br>Now, we may know that Jesus is from God, and that He’s the only non–sinning human to have ever walked the earth. But as much as we’d love to be more like Him, we reckon in this story we see ourselves in the Pharisees a bit. Sometimes we have an off–kilter idea of who God is. In our thinking we can restrict Him to times and places (like when we think worship only happens at 11 am on a Sunday…?) We can just get caught up in the predictability of life, and expect God to fit right into it. Thing is, He’s the creator of life. It’s definitely His prerogative to change, heal and resurrect. Maybe it’s time we started trusting, and then living out, what Jesus said, and still says. Know someone that really needs a miracle? Pray for them right now and ask God to show how you can practically be the hands and feet of Jesus in that situation.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 1–4, John 18:12–24, Ps 57, Ecc 7:13–15</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 17 December</p>
<p>‘…One thing I know: that though I was blind, now I see.’ John 9:25 NKJ</p>
<p>But Now I See 3</p>
<p>The Pharisees weren’t too happy with Jesus healing this blind guy. They thought that He didn’t have the power and authority to do that sort of thing. Only… He did. And He does. It can be easy to, unknowingly, get into the thought pattern that that ‘Bible Jesus’ is a different Jesus to the one that lives within us and through us today. Hebrews 13:8 NIV says, ‘<i>Jesus Christ is the same yesterday and today and forever</i>.’ We can end up putting God’s Word in a nice little box marked ‘Bible stories’, and we get them out on rainy days. But the reality that Hebrews shows us is that the same Jesus that healed this guy is still at work today.<br></br><br></br>Great stuff. But then… one of the things that’s hard to get our head around, is that God is completely just. It can be really tough to understand why God heals some people and not others, and heals at certain times and not others. Our human reaction is to believe it’s based on how well behaved we’ve been, or how much God likes us, but Jesus taught us that while physical healing is important, God's priority is for our spiritual healing (see Matthew 9:1-8). It's ok to ask Jesus the ‘why’ question when you don't understand, but we know this for sure: He loves you. Like, a lot. And He knows what He’s doing. You’re in safe hands.<br></br><br></br>Grab a journal or notebook and write down the news headlines for the next 3 days. Pray them through, each day. Then write Hebrews 13:8 underneath as a reminder that Jesus remains the same.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 5–7, John 18:25–32, Ps 67, Ecc 7:19–22</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 18 December</p>
<p>‘…he went and washed, and came back seeing.’ John 9:7 NKJ</p>
<p>But Now I See 4</p>
<p>Have a read of John 9:13–34. Not only have the Pharisees asked the guy how he’s been healed, they’ve approached his parents to double–check his story. The parents bat it back to the son, and the Pharisees ask again. So he answers with, ‘<i>I have told you already and you did not listen. Why do you want to hear it again? Do you want to become His disciples too?</i>’ (John 9:27 NIV) Either this guy is getting sassy with the Pharisees, or he’s genuinely questioning their motives. Whatever he’s thinking, this guy is focused on Jesus. His heart is 100% set on the miracle he’s received. He tells the Pharisees: ‘<i>Whether He is a sinner or not, I don’t know. One thing I do know. I was blind but now I see!</i>’ (John 9:25 NIV) He’s essentially saying, ‘Look, I get that you have your rules, but I have sight. I have a miracle. A new lease of life.’<br></br><br></br>Sometimes we need to stop and see what God has actually done for His people in the past (stories from the Bible), in our lives and the lives of people we know. We sometimes get so busy that we take stuff for granted. We find ourselves forgetting His miracles, the transformations, the fresh hope and the healings that have been given to us, or to those around us. Of course, we shouldn’t <i>live</i> in the past, even when that particular past event is something good. You should keep the memories of God’s previous faithfulness close to your heart, so that your faith becomes stronger in the knowledge of His ongoing awesomeness.  <br></br><br></br>We’d love to hear what God has done in your life and what He’s still doing. Let us know @ <i>Vision180</i> on Facebook.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 8–10, John 18:33–40, Ps 12, Ecc 9:10–12</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 19 December</p>
<p>‘If this man were not from God, he could do nothing.’ John 9:33 NIV</p>
<p>But Now I See 5</p>
<p>So, Jesus heals a blind man. But the Pharisees still aren’t happy. They half–warn the healed man, by saying ‘…<i>we don’t even know where He comes from</i>.’ (John 9:29 NIV) That, however, doesn’t even phase him. His reply is: ‘<i>Now that is remarkable! You don’t know where He comes from, yet He opened my eyes</i>.’ (John 9:30 NIV) He’s astounded at the fact that Jesus did something so unusual for him, saying: ‘<i>Nobody has ever heard of opening the eyes of a man born blind. If this man were not from God, He could do nothing</i>.’ (John 9:33 NIV) There’s a reminder for us here. Without God, we can do nothing. Ok, we might make a decent cup of coffee. But who gave us those hands that switched the kettle on? Who created the coffee beans? (Side note: we’re really craving a cuppa. And a Tim Tam slam). Sometimes we take credit for the things God does. Even accidentally. Or, we can give in when people do the whole ‘we don’t even know if that was God’ thing. In John 15:5 NIV, Jesus says, ‘<i>I am the vine; you are the branches. If you remain in Me and I in you, you will bear much fruit; apart from Me you can do nothing</i>.’ That’s a big idea, but God’s basically reminding us that the only reason we can do anything is Him. Let’s not lose sight of that, and hold onto it especially when we have people trying to convince us otherwise. Make a hot drink while you do it, consider where each thing you need to make it comes from. Bet you eventually end up at God.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 11–14, John 19:1–7, Ps 47, Ecc 10:1–4</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 20 December</p>
<p>‘I will not look at anything wicked… those who turn against You…will not be found near me.’ Psalm 101:3 NCV</p>
<p>Eyes Light Up</p>
<p>The internet is a thing we’re quite fond of. We can talk to faraway friends, we can check what else that actress appeared in, and we have access to masses of information about the airspeed of a swallow in seconds. It’s given us access to all sorts of great stuff, but also some not–so–great stuff. Sometimes those lines can become blurred. How bad is bad? Is watching a YouTube performer who swears a lot as bad as some of the other stuff we could be looking at? Well, look at this verse Paul wrote: ‘…<i>whatever is true, whatever is noble, whatever is right, whatever is pure, whatever is lovely, whatever is admirable—if anything is excellent or praiseworthy—think about such things</i>.’ (Philippians 4:8 NIV) Is what you’re listening to, reading or watching beneficial or corrupting? Even if we don’t watch something <i>because</i> there’s an ‘intimate scene’ (and it is only one scene after all—apart from that, it’s great), we still have to take note of where our web browsing is subliminally taking us, mentally and spiritually. Even the stuff that we don’t really want to see still makes an impact. And that sometimes means that we might have to be pretty ruthless about what we turn away from and say with the Psalmist: ‘I will not look at anything wicked.’ Jesus said, ‘<i>the eye is the lamp of the body</i>.’ (John 6:22 NIV) So let’s make sure we’re filling our minds with light. So, if you’re struggling with some not–so–great internet stuff, show this reading to your pastor or an older, wiser Christian to get a conversation started.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 27:30–33, Num 31:48–54, 1 Cor 16:1–3</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 21 December</p>
<p>‘…if you have faith and do not doubt…’ Matthew 21:21 NIV</p>
<p>Ctrl Key</p>
<p>In a world where we mostly want to do things our way, faith can sometimes become an abstract concept. It can be pretty easy to believe that it’s a bad call to rely on anything that we can’t control. But in the midst of whatever–it–is this world is telling us, God calls us to have faith. He asks us to trust in Him. Our response to this can often be to give Him super focus for a few days. Then, like the grabby humans we all are, we can inevitably try to take back control of our lives, away from Him. It happens, especially when things get difficult. However, let’s be realistic. God is a king. Creator of the world. Occasional, partial control will never fit. We are called to be part of a greater Kingdom, one which is not of this world. And that requires more.<br></br><br></br>When Jesus called the disciples He didn’t give them a big sales pitch or paint vivid pictures of where they would go. He asked them to follow Him, and it took them on an amazing journey. The same call comes to each of us. The road ahead may be unclear, but God is asking us to follow Him. It may not be easy or obvious, but we can have confidence in the One who will never lead us astray. Like the disciples, we’re asked to love and trust our God, no matter what else is going on for us.<br></br><br></br>Is there something that you want to keep control of, yourself? Write it down, share it with someone, and ask them to pray for you.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 15–17, John 19:8–16, Ps 128, Ecc 10:5–9</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 22 December</p>
<p>‘I appeal to you...in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that all of you agree with one another.’ 1 Corinthians 1:10 NIV</p>
<p>Bold In Broken Places</p>
<p>We’ve all probably got one or two stories about arguments, or issues, or divisions within a church. That’s nothing new. Paul wrote a letter to the church in Corinth (yep, that’d be 1 Corinthians), and part of his advice to them was about getting over their church–related gripes. The thing is, the Church here on earth is made up of human people. And we’re flawed.<br></br><br></br>But when Jesus was asked what the greatest commandment is (check out Matthew 22:34–40), He responded by saying to first love God, and then to love your neighbour. These are the key things that we must never lose sight of in our experience of the church. It was created to be a beautiful thing. And despite our brokenness, it still can be. <br></br><br></br>A guy called Jamie Tworkowski epitomises that. He and some others met a girl called Renee, ruined by drugs and self–harm, and could not look away. They spent days just loving her and being the body of Christ in the midst of her darkness. From this, the charity ‘To Write Love on Her Arms’ was formed, beginning by selling T–shirts to raise money for treatment for Renee.<br></br><br></br>This is what happens when we have our ears open to hear God, and are prepared to love people. As Jamie himself says, ‘We were made to be lovers bold in broken places, pouring ourselves out again and again until we’re called home.’ We would all want to be in a church that really lived that out. And we can be. It can start with us. Think of something, just one beautiful act, that’d show (at least a portion of) this world what the church could, and should, be. Make it happen. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 18–20, John 19:17–30, Ps 113, Ecc 10:10–14</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 23 December</p>
<p>‘…the hearts of the people melted, and became like water.’ Joshua 7:5 NKJ</p>
<p>Shiny Things</p>
<p>In Joshua 7, the Israelites have just crossed over into the Promised Land, after wandering in the desert for 40 years. Walls had miraculously tumbled down, they moved in to the very place they’d been longing for, hearts melted, and everything was lovely.<br></br><br></br>But. Isn’t there always a <i>but</i>? There’s one guy who decides it’s not enough. Achan sees some clothes in the latest fashion and a stack of silver, and he decides he’s having it, like some kind of magpie. Knowing it’s wrong, he buries them underground, to hide them from view.<br></br><br></br>So often we can relate to Achan. Things can be going well, and then we mess up. A natural reaction is that we can bury our mess–ups deep down, hoping that no–one will ever find out and reject us. We feel that our own failings and sin are just too bad. We can talk about God never running out of forgiveness, but at the same time feel that we’ve maybe screwed up one time too many.<br></br><br></br>1 John 1:19 is an absolute gem for the times we feel that. It says: ‘<i>If we confess our sins, He is faithful and just and will forgive us our sins and purify us from all unrighteousness.</i>’ (1 John 1:9 NIV) God’s forgiveness has been cleansing people since the dawn of time, and it’s not about to stop now. Whatever you’ve done, you can turn to Him. If you’re honest with Him, He will help you turn away from even the worst things.<br></br><br></br>So, find a fellow Christian that you really trust. Agree to meet with them regularly to confess things and pray together. It might be hard at first, but it can stop silent guilt controlling your life.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 21–23, John 19:31–42, Ps 117, Ecc 10:15–19</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 24 December</p>
<p>‘Wise men…came…saying, “Where is He…?”’ Matthew 2:1–2 NKJ</p>
<p>Faithfully Seeking (1)</p>
<p>Kids with kitchen towels on their heads shouting ‘Look yonder! A star!’ and toddling across the school stage. Those were the days, right? Whether you played Wise Man #3 in your school nativity play or not, this ‘wise men’ business brings to mind a few questions (and not just ‘Where DID my acting career go after that?’) Who were they? Where <i>'in the east'</i> did they come from? Why did God choose to get their attention through a shiny star? And why was Herod and all of Jerusalem <i>'troubled'</i> when they came to town?<br></br><br></br>Today we’re looking at their faithful efforts to follow that star. These guys travelled. We don’t know how far or what convinced them God was out there. But we do know that they were willing to do it. Drop the nativity images and questions about what was really going on. The big question we should be asking ourselves is this: just how willing are we to seek God out when it’s the most inconvenient, busy time? Jeremiah 29:13 says ‘<i>You will seek Me and find Me when you seek Me with all your heart</i>.’ If we want a deep, rich relationship with God that draws us closer to Him every day, we’ve got to seek Him out. These wise men, travellers from a faraway country, did just that. Will we?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 24–28, John 20:1–9, Ps 97, Ecc 10:20–11:3</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 25 December</p>
<p>‘They saw the young Child… and worshipped Him.’ Matthew 2:11 NKJ</p>
<p>Faithfully Seeking (2)</p>
<p>Merry Christmas, <i>Vision180</i> reader. Really, thanks for dropping in today. You’re looking festive.<br></br><br></br>So, yesterday we were chatting about you seeking God. Today we’re chatting about God seeking you. The wise men had a pretty clear sign from God about where He wanted them to be, He guided them by a star the entire way. Matthew 2:9 NIV says: ‘…<i>the star they had seen when it rose went ahead of them until it stopped over the place where the Child was</i>.’ Handy. <br></br><br></br>What about when we’re willing to follow God but He doesn’t provide us with a shiny sky beacon? Well, He’s pretty good at knowing what works well and what doesn’t. We can trust that whether it’s a recurring theme in our Bible studies, a poignant prayer time or a shiny sky beacon, He’ll speak to us. Psalm 32:8 NIV says: ‘<i>I will instruct you and teach you in the way you should go</i>.’ It’s also worth looking at the way that God protected these travellers. He didn’t just say ‘Oi, follow this star!’—He actually kept them safe from a dangerous king who wanted them dead (have a look at Matthew 2:12). <br></br><br></br>It can be so easy for us to want to try to be where God wants us, but forget that He’s with us in the journey and not just waiting at the destination. Make the most of the confidence of knowing that the Majesty of Heaven goes with you. And remember it by writing Psalm 32:8 over an image of a star and making it your phone background for the festive period. Use it as a reminder that God is with you. Oh, and have some pudding. </p>
<p>SoulFood Christmas Day: Is 7:14, Luke 2:1–20, Mic 5:2–5a, Is 9:6–7 </p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 26 December</p>
<p>‘No human being must separate… what God has joined together.’ Mark 10:9 GNT</p>
<p>Sometimes Relationships Are Hard 1</p>
<p>Realistic interruption before we begin: not every relationship is healthy. If physical, mental, or emotional (or even spiritual) abuse threatens your safety, or anyone’s actually, get out. Stay safe, okay? In situations when a relationship can be fixed, though, they can end up being a source of shared joy and strength. So for the next few days, we’ll be looking at injecting some health into relationships. (And for those of you not in one, we figured you might want these tips anyway?) <br></br><br></br>Today’s tips for healthy relationships: get God’s perspective of sin, yours *and* theirs.<br></br><br></br>Maybe this is obvious. Maybe you agree in theory, but how’s that working out in practice? Maybe you’re trying your best, but they’re being selfish, and never listening. Maybe they’re deliberately being as sinful and difficult as possible, and you’re just an offended saint. Is it their job to fix those horrendous habits and your job to make sure they get fixed?... OR. <br></br><br></br>Perspective shift: Are you giving them a hard time, out loud or with silent treatments, to make them see what a terrible person they are? From God’s perspective, sin is sin. Yours and theirs. All of the above are harmful to relationships. Rather than ranking [others] sins (especially if you’re sure theirs is worse than yours), try dealing with the situation the way Jesus taught (see Matthew 7:4–5 for starters). Trust us, you’ll be amazed at how God will start to work with their problem when you get honest and deal with yours. Open Matthew 7:4–5, and spend a while praying through your situation with it in front of you. What do you need to deal with?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 29–31, John 20:10–18, Ps 139:1–12, Ecc 11:4–6</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 27 December</p>
<p>‘In order that Satan might not outwit us…’ 2 Corinthians 2:11 NIV</p>
<p>Sometimes Relationships Are Hard 2</p>
<p>Marriage was God’s idea. He got there even before anyone first thought of chucking rose petals at a happy couple. To Him, marriage is a foundational rock of His earthly Kingdom (which is pretty cool, when you think about it like that—more on that tomorrow). Once you’ve committed to a spouse (albeit with yesterday’s care–warning), your marriage is a celebration, to God.<br></br><br></br>However: God’s foundational plans tend to be prime targets for Satan. Notice how in Adam and Eve’s relationship, Satan didn’t just separate them from God (major in itself), but twisted their perspective, and divided them from each other, too (Genesis 3:12). Lies, suspicion, and a whole pile of blaming each other, are among Satan’s tactics to divide ‘<i>what God has joined together</i>.’ (Mark 10:9 NIV) Your own relationships, especially marriage, will be subject to the same threats from ‘…<i>the father of lies</i>.’ (John 8:44 NLT) But note that God has an antidote. Notice how easy it is to recall that time your partner hurt you? Have you been keeping a subconscious tab of your partner’s flaws/failings? Are they really the problem, and you completely justified in not showing them grace? God says ‘…<i>love…keeps no record of wrongs</i>…’ (1 Corinthians 13:4–5 NIV) And also: ‘<i>I have forgiven in the sight of Christ…in order that Satan might not outwit us…we are not unaware of his schemes</i>.’ (2 Corinthians 2:10–11 NIV) That doesn’t mean love [doesn't] lives in denial. But it regularly denies the ‘self’, putting the other first. And nothing melts resentment like appreciation. If you’ve a special someone, think of something you appreciate about them, and tell them. If not, this is equally important for family.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ps 103:8–18, John 3:16–18, Acts 2:38–41</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 28 December</p>
<p>‘Pray then like this…Your will be done…’ Matthew 6:9–10 ESV</p>
<p>Sometimes Relationships Are Hard 3</p>
<p>Today, we’ve another not–quite–revolutionary idea for you: <i>pray</i>. Well, the idea’s not new. But actually doing it might well revolutionise your relationship. The way you pray is also really important: praying for the solution you really really want might not actually be inviting God to work there. Ouch. Are you blinkered? Are you praying ‘Lord, why haven’t You fixed them yet? Why haven’t You done what I want that obviously fixes them?!’ If instead you pray: ‘Lord, do Your thing, fix us Your way…’, then you’re on much more receptive ground. His perspective is going to be the one that has the best chance of fixing anything, after all. That’s also probably why He taught us to pray ‘<i>Your will be done</i>…’ The Bible says: ‘<i>This is the confidence we have in approaching God: that if we ask anything according to His will, He hears us. And if we know that He hears us…we know that we have what we asked of Him</i>.’ (1 John 5:14–15 NIV)<br></br><br></br><i>Love is not feelings</i>. (WHAT?!) If we focus on warmth and fuzziness, we miss that love is an act of will, about acting in ways that are ‘loving’. That’s why commitment is central in marriage, it isn’t designed to be carried by feelings. Isn’t that acting hypocritically? No, it’s rising above resentment, hurt, and fear and practising real faith. Love, sometimes, is an act of willing yourself to act for someone else, even when you don’t feel like it. And it’s a parallel of how God wants You to relate to Him, too.<br></br><br></br>Ask yourself: ‘If I were loving unconditionally right now, what would I be doing? How would I be responding to my partner?’ Then do it.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 32–34, John 20:19–31, Ps 139:13–24, Ecc 11:7–10</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 29 December</p>
<p>‘Leave your troubles with the Lord…’ Psalm 55:22 GNT</p>
<p>Sometimes Relationships Are Hard 4</p>
<p>Yeah. Sometimes relationships, especially marriages, are hard. But mostly because people come with baggage, rough edges and sore wounds. In times gone by, monastic communities were places you could go, not just to live completely devoted to God, but in the firm knowledge you’d be in close, constant contact with people, and getting hit by more than a few rough edges. These community experiences didn’t just help you focus on God, they exposed the bits of your personality that needed work. Which was often a painful experience. Sooo… marriage is like that. It’s like a grinding machine where the spikey bits of us, which we’d otherwise get away with, are knocked off and polished down. It’s a core of (learning how to do) selfless love, that can be a bedrock for a Kingdom on a mission of His love.<br></br><br></br>When a marriage is in trouble, as well as getting professional help (which can be a really good thing), in fact long before that, it needs to be given to God. If you as individuals, along with your marriage as a unity, are given into His hands, the situation changes completely. Your point–scoring and personal pride get replaced by His priorities. So long as you’re ‘straightening out’ your significant other, you’re part of the problem. Give it to God, and it becomes His to sort. Not only that, but you’ll experience peace. The psalmist puts it this way: ‘<i>Leave your troubles with the Lord… He never lets honest people be defeated</i>…’ So, praise God for the spikey bits He’s taken off you. And spend a bit of time thinking about how He can be first in all of your relationships.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 35–37, John 21:1–6, Ps 116, Ecc 12:1</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 30 December</p>
<p>‘…The God of Heaven will give us success…’ Nehemiah 2:20 NIV</p>
<p>Fail Bounce</p>
<p>Your Failures. Sheesh, the very words are shudder–inducing. But, hey, it’s not like we’re bringing it up in exam season. (At least we hope not. In the week between Christmas and New Year? Our deepest sympathies, if that’s the case.) Truth is, failure is a part of life—and a part of the learning curve. Thomas Edison admitted that it took quite a few tries (around 3000!) before he nailed the incandescent light bulb. And CS Lewis (yes, famous for <i>The Chronicles of Narnia</i>) was turned down 800 times before he sold a single piece of writing. But Edison didn’t regret or try to hide those previous tries. In fact, he owned his ‘failed’ attempts and was grateful for them. He said, ‘I haven’t failed. I’ve found three thousand ways that don’t work.’ Nice outlook there. And I’m sure those publishers gave ‘shoulda, woulda, coulda’ about ten minutes of thought before they moved on to the next great author. Proverbs 24:16 NIV says, ‘<i>though the righteous fall seven times, they rise again</i>…’ So rather than beat yourself up about something you wish you’d done differently, take that and do it differently next time around. For most things in life, we get a second chance. And as far as God is concerned, we get a third, and a fourth, and—ok, quite a few more. The point is, God *wants* you to succeed. And it’s a lot easier to succeed with God by your side, rooting for you.<br></br><br></br>When was the last time you felt like you’d failed at something? Keeping a promise, or even a schedule? Think about what went wrong, pray, and try it again. Don’t be scared.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 38–39, John 21:7–14, Ps 23, Ecc 12:13–14</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 31 December</p>
<p>‘…Don’t let the world around you squeeze you into its own mould…’ Romans 12:2 PHPS</p>
<p>Breaking the Mould</p>
<p>When we find ourselves in new surroundings, one of the biggest worries can be whether or not we’ll fit in. Will we get along with people? Because, inconvenient as it can be as a priority, we like to be liked. And we almost invariably will find like–minded people to become friends with but, unfortunately, there is probably always going to be someone against us too. There may be a reason for that and there may not be, but, honestly, we’re never going to please everybody. And it can be difficult sometimes not to let that get to us. The thought that someone doesn’t like who we are can be tough. But.<br></br><br></br>If we were to ‘<i>let the world squeeze [us] into its own mould</i>…’ as Romans 12:2 PHPS warns against, we’re giving others far too much power over us. And, no offence, world, but it doesn’t really get us. It probably has a few assumptions about you that are way off, that underestimate you, and don’t see the gifts and personality God’s given to you. Frankly, we’re more than that mould in the first place. Bring God in, and that mould is shattered. He has a different perspective on you, and a different way for you. If we ask God to be at the centre of who we are, He gives us power in our own lives. Psalm 56:4 NCV says, ‘…<i>I trust God, so I am not afraid. What can human beings do to me?</i>’ He is our defence—and there really isn’t a better one.<br></br><br></br>What 3 words best describe a friend of yours? Write them down, then reread them: is there anything missing? If even the 3 best words you have aren’t enough to describe them accurately, there’s no way that a negative opinion can mould you.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Job 40–42, John 21:15–25, Ps 77:11–20, Pr 9:10–12</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 1 January</p>
<p>‘How can I know all the sins lurking in my heart? Cleanse me from these hidden faults.’ Psalm 19:12 NLT</p>
<p>Blind Spots</p>
<p>Happy New Year, <i>Vision180</i>–ers! Now’s the time to be looking ahead as well as looking out for blind spots. If you’ve learnt to drive, you’ll know first–hand what it’s like to deal with them. When you can’t see a fair proportion of what’s around you on the road, it takes some getting used to. We all have blind spots: pieces of our lives that we’ll never see without God’s help. Sure, it may seem like you know yourself better than anyone else does. After all, only you, and God, know what you’re thinking. Then again, a lot of the time, you don’t know yourself very well at all. You see, we’re all biased: we all look out for what’s best for us. We like to listen to the people who think like us and agree with us, but we often don’t attempt to listen to [not] people who think differently. And sometimes, it’s easy to ignore certain ungodly things that lurk, unseen, within us. <br></br><br></br>The truth is, the Holy Spirit knows us best. Take a look at what the psalmist said, ‘<i>How can I know all the sins lurking in my heart? Cleanse me from these hidden faults. Keep Your servant from deliberate sins! Don’t let them control me…May the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart be pleasing to You</i>…’ (Psalm 19:12–14 NLT) The psalmist knew he had a blind spot, and he asked God to help him see it. So, as this year starts, pray about the stuff that you can’t see in your own life and ask God to eliminate your blind spots.</p>
<p>SoulFood New Years Day: Rom 13:12 – 14:19, John 1:1–14</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 2 January</p>
<p>‘But who can discern their own errors?’ Psalm 19:12 NIV</p>
<p>Blindfolded in a Sweet Shop</p>
<p>Traversing the world with our desires leading us, we can churn up a right mess in our wake. At our worst, we’re like kids dropped blindfolded into a sweet shop: rifling around for our favourite sweets while trashing the place. We only see what makes us feel good, and we don’t see who we hurt or the mess we left getting to it. When someone takes the blindfold off and shows us the mess, we inevitably feel helpless and humiliated; but then what? We’re back into the same routine of letting our desires lead us.<br></br><br></br>Paul the apostle knew that he committed sins without knowing (1 Corinthians 4:4). But he knew that God alone knew his every wrong, and that God had chosen to blot out his sins because of Jesus. Paul didn’t have to remember every single sin to know that God had forgiven him for them all. The psalmist who wrote today’s verse finished off like this: ‘<i>Declare me innocent from hidden faults</i>.’ (Psalm 19:12 ESV) He knew that he couldn’t remember every sin he ever committed—but he knew that God could free him anyway. And what did he do? He asked that God would lead him out from even the sins he couldn’t see. This doesn’t mean that the mess he’d made, or those he’d hurt, would stop existing. But it does mean that his half–desires didn’t have to lead him any more—now that he connected back to the true centre of all desire, God. <br></br><br></br>So, get brave. Fearlessly, ask God to show you your hidden faults, and ask Him to deal with them.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Th 1–3, Luke 1:1–10, Ps 90, Prov 1:1–7</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 3 January</p>
<p>‘...you have...put on the new self, which is being renewed in knowledge in the image of its Creator.’ Colossians 3:9–10 NIV</p>
<p>True Self</p>
<p>The verses above in Colossians, hmm. At first they sound a little painful. Who wants to take off their ‘old’ self and put on a ‘new’ self? What does that even mean? Aren’t we told to be ourselves and accept who we are already? Of course we are. But we’re not being told to be someone else. This is a description of how every Christian is being made into God’s new version of ourselves. The best our unique selves can be.<br></br><br></br>So let’s look at Colossians again. ‘<i>But now you must also rid yourselves of all such things as these: anger, rage, malice, slander, and filthy language from your lips. Do not lie to each other, since you have taken off your old self with its practices and have put on the new self, which is being renewed in knowledge in the image of its Creator.</i>’ (Colossians 3:8–10 NIV) Ok. Let that sink in. We need to be willing to work through emotions and actions that are not part of us living true to the way God made us. Sometimes, God will strip back the bad stuff really quickly. Other times, though, it doesn’t happen all at once, even when we wish we could kick that habit. ‘Being renewed’ is ongoing. It’s ok that it takes time. In fact, all the time. Every day. God keeps honing us until life’s interrupted by meeting Him face to face. And then, He’ll be interested in what progress we made, rather than expecting us to have got to ‘perfect’. So stick with Him. Keep putting on that new self.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 2 Chron 7:12–16 , Matt 6:5–15, Luke 18:1–8</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 4 January</p>
<p>‘May…the meditation of my heart be pleasing to You…’ Psalm 19:14 NLT</p>
<p>Convicts of God</p>
<p>Jesus promised us that when the Holy Spirit came He would convict us of sin. But do we always know how to recognise ‘conviction’? The most common confusion is between ‘conviction’ (a sense of wrongdoing given by the Holy Spirit) and ‘condemnation’ (a feeling from yourself, others or Satan that you’re rubbish, and God couldn’t love/forgive you). The first says <i>what you’ve done is wrong</i>, but offers you a way out (grace and mercy); the second says <i>who you are</i> is the problem and only offers judgment. So what does conviction look like?<br></br><br></br>In short: it’s the Holy Spirit revealing sin. That means Him pointing out what needs to change, to protect and help us. It means God only does it for the purpose of showing us what to reject, because it brings us closer to Him. It <i>never</i> is to make us feel like rejects, or unloved.<br></br><br></br>So then conviction doesn’t mean ‘getting caught’. The feeling we get when people see the wrong we’ve done isn’t necessarily God’s conviction, it can just be our own sense of social shame. A test is: if we had got away with it, would we feel the same? Conviction also isn’t ‘fear of punishment’; that’s still pretty selfish at heart. When God prompts us to look at our bad actions, we can tell it’s His influence on us, rather than our own self–preserving egos at work.<br></br><br></br>To be fair, if ‘conviction’ [it] means God showing us how to get right with Him, then however tough it feels at the time, we should probably be desperate for it. Have a prayer today: ‘Lord, show me what I need to apologise for. Convict my heart about things I’m doing against You, and help me turn that conviction straight into repenting and getting right with You. Amen.’</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 1–4, Luke 1:11–25, Ps 10:1–11, Prov 1:8–16</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 5 January</p>
<p>‘Do not exalt yourself… and do not claim a place among great men.’ Proverbs 25:6 NIV</p>
<p>#TopChristian</p>
<p>Filing into church and finding your way to a seat, you notice something again that you’ve always taken for granted: the front row is taken up by worship leaders, the youth pastors, the leaders and their families. ‘Why is that?’ you wonder. And, on the tails of that first thought, are you likely to thank God for their service? Or might your brain wander to: ‘Why isn’t that me?...’ <br></br><br></br>It’s not a bad thought to want to be in dedicated service to God. But what else is in that thought? There might have been other places where this thought has come to your mind: in school, where there was always a circle of kids that everyone longed to be a part of; maybe at uni, or even at work, with the Big Names that everyone knows. That desire to be important in other people’s minds is one of the reasons we want into the circle of ‘special people’ at the centre of most social groups. That desire can make some people ruthless and hard in their aim to ‘level up’ above others. God knows how our longing to be in the top set (wherever that might be) can corrupt us. So He meets it Himself. We’re <u><i>all</i></u> warmly welcomed by our Father. In His Kingdom, there are no first–tier and second–tier Christians. As for the leadership roles here on earth? We’re not to bother barging in on them. Jesus said, ‘<i>Take the lowest place, so that when your host comes, he will say to you, “Friend, move up to a better place.” Then you will be honoured in the presence of all the other guests</i>.’ (Luke 14:10 NIV)  </p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 5–7, Luke 1:26–38, Ps 10:12–18, Prov 1:17–19</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 6 January</p>
<p>‘…The right words bring satisfaction.’ Proverbs 18:20 NLT</p>
<p>I’ve Got the Power</p>
<p>Words are powerful. Whether it’s something blurted out unthinkingly in the middle of a conversation or a carefully thought–out and heavily edited line of poetry, the words we use hold a lot of weight. We all know the ‘sticks and stones’ line isn’t entirely accurate (more the ‘words will never hurt me’ part, not that they couldn’t break your bones). Words can hurt. But they can heal too. Proverbs 18:21 NLT says, ‘<i>The tongue can bring death or life; those who love to talk will reap the consequences</i>’—a warning, yes, but an encouragement too. What we say—in sermons or worship songs or while ordering a coffee—can help people immeasurably. Sometimes without us even knowing it. When God gives you a power like that, it’s not helping anybody to squander it out of fear. That can be as harmful as being reckless with it. No pressure.<br></br><br></br>Yes, really: no pressure. As always, God is waiting for us to ask for help. The power we hold in words can be daunting, but all we have to do is ask God to guide us to the right things to say. Not every conversation we have will change somebody’s life, granted, but you never know which one might.<br></br><br></br>Use your words. First, pray over the conversations you’ll have today. Then just talk to people. It may be a ‘you look nice’ to someone you don’t really know or it may be a life–changing message to someone you know is struggling. Something in between is good too. </p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 8–10, Luke 1:39–56, Ps 42:1–5, Prov 1:20–23</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 7 January</p>
<p>‘…We walk by faith, not by sight.’ 2 Corinthians 5:7 NKJ</p>
<p>Floodlights on Your Future? 1</p>
<p>It’s not easy to trust in something when you have no idea what’s going to happen, so we don’t tend to do it a lot. Even things like parachuting are thoroughly tested and evaluated and safety–checked (which is a very, very good thing) by an expert before we do it. (Well, when we say ‘we’ in relation to parachuting, we might just mean ‘people’…)<br></br><br></br>You don’t take a test until you’ve been taught the material by someone much more knowledgeable. You don’t throw a back–flip until you’ve been trained by someone qualified (we hope). But it’s not possible to know what to expect in everything you do. You never really know what to expect in a new job, or even when you wake up tomorrow. That’s not to inspire any anxiety or fear though—it sounds a lot scarier than it is. There’s no way to be an expert on life before you’ve lived it but, wonderfully for us, God isn’t fussed by that whole ‘time’ thing. He knows what’s ahead of us, and He’s far far far more knowledgeable than us (sorry for any bubble–bursting but we thought you should know). Isaiah 42:16 NIV says, ‘<i>I will bring the blind by ways they have not known</i>…’ So there’s no need to be scared when you don’t know what lies ahead as long as you’re willing to trust in God to guide you through it. <br></br><br></br>Ready? There’s no shortage of blindfold obstacle course/trust fall games out there. If you get time this week, why not grab a friend and have a laugh while giving a few a go.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 11:1–13:37, Luke 1:57–66, Ps 42:6–11, Prov 1:24–28</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 8 January</p>
<p>‘…We walk by faith, not by sight.’ 2 Corinthians 5:7 NKJ</p>
<p>Floodlights on Your Future? 2</p>
<p>Yesterday we figured that God knows what He’s doing, even if we have no idea where we’re headed. But even knowing how much more of a clue God has than we do, it can still be hard to blindly head into the unknown. This is particularly true, if you’re not sure yet where God is leading you. But as well as knowing a lot more than us, God makes a promise too. ‘…<i>I will turn the darkness into light before them and make the rough places smooth. These are the things I will do; I will not forsake them</i>.’ (Isaiah 42:16 NIV) God tells us that He will show us where we’re headed if we trust in Him. There is already a plan for us, but trying to see into the future to discover what it is without God (or a time machine) is beyond pointless.<br></br><br></br>Paul writes, ‘<i>I pray that your hearts will be flooded with light so that you can see something of the future He has called you to share…I pray that you will begin to understand how incredibly great His power is to help those who believe Him.</i>’ (Ephesians 1:18–19 TLB) It’s scary to keep going without knowing, and it’s scary having to wait but, at the right time, God will show you what you’ve been trying to see. There are countless stories that will tell you the same in the Bible. Write down a prayer asking God to show you the way forward, and to give you the trust to follow His Word even ‘in the dark’ (Psalm 119:105). Keep coming back to that prayer this week.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 13:38–14:57, Luke 1:67–80, Ps 3, Prov 1:29–31</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 9 January</p>
<p>‘…Glorify God in your body…’ 1 Corinthians 6:20 NKJ</p>
<p>Body: Rockin’ (Not Perfection)</p>
<p>We might think of our bodies as tents: temporary measures that wear out quickly. But the Bible also calls it a Temple. Your body does a lot for you. When your mind and spirit are over–worked, your body tells you to eat and sleep, making sure you don’t burn out. Making sure you can keep going. And it does the whole breathing thing without even being asked. Long story clichéd: your body is a gift. One of the best gifts we ever receive, not least because God is the giver. And it’s a gift we’re sometimes guilty of being ungrateful for. How many times do we wish our bodies were harder/better/faster/stronger? We forget that the embarrassing belly–rumble in a quiet room is ensuring that we fuel ourselves, so that we have the energy to do the amazing things we’re capable of. It’s not often we thank God for a body at all—let alone our own body (the one about which we have countless complaints). But why not?<br></br><br></br>Rather than forgetting to look after the bodies we’ve been given, by not giving them enough rest, or the right kind of nourishment, let’s look after[our bodies] them and thank Him for them. Maybe you hate your thighs; thank God that you can dad–dance with them. It’s the mouth He gave to you that lets you talk and sing, the eyes that He designed that enable you to read and see beauty. He designed your body incredibly. Absolutely incredibly. So look after it as best you can. Whenever you catch yourself criticising your body today, think of a reason you’re thankful for it instead. Do it tomorrow too.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 15–17, Luke 2:1–15, Ps 46, Prov 1:32–33</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 10 January</p>
<p>‘…show deep love for each other, for love covers a multitude of sins.’ 1 Peter 4:8 NLT</p>
<p>Leftover Sandwiches</p>
<p>Did you have that friend? You know, the one whose mum packed a special lunch: sangers made with leftovers. Potato and carrot, or beetroot and broccoli. You know the story, and it ends with a whole lot of mess.<br></br><br></br>We can feel like our mistakes cling to the front of our jumper, for all the world to see. But when we feel like we’ve messed up, and disappointed people, God has His arms wide open. We could imagine Him as a parent, waiting at the school gates for the kids to return. When He sees one of His kids is upset, He wants to hug His child despite the messy jumper. You might be familiar with the parable of the Lost Son (Luke 15) and can see the story we’re working with here. Basically, what we’re getting at is the fact that God is willing to get involved in our mess, even when we feel covered in our mistakes.<br></br><br></br>He will always run to embrace us, even when we’ve covered ourselves in not–so–sweet–smelling stuff. Now, to bring it home, take a look at today’s verse. We’re called to show the same love to each other. Especially because we’re all prone to messing up. Showing people we care for them, even when they’ve messed up, is a calling for us. If you know someone who’s been struggling in some way recently, drop them a message, even just to ask how they are. Letting someone know you’re there is a bigger step than it might first seem.</p>
<p>SoulFood: 1 Sam 3:1–11, Act 9:1–9</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 11 January</p>
<p>‘…God has not given us a spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of a sound mind.’ 2 Timothy 1:7 NKJ</p>
<p>Spirit of Fear?</p>
<p>Read the verse directly before, and the verse directly after, 2 Timothy 1:7. Paul is talking to Timothy about being able to have faith in the gifts and mission that God has given him. He’s telling him to not be ashamed of those things. And in verse 7 he provides the reason. In that verse, the words ‘<i>spirit of</i>’ are actually referring to something pretty human, and natural, rather than super–natural. It basically means an ‘attitude of’, or ‘disposition of’. Paul is telling Timothy that God has given him an attitude of love, power and of clear thinking. And that means that Timothy is able to live out what God wants for him.<br></br><br></br>We reckon the same applies to you, too. You’re invited to have faith in what God’s given you, and in the Gospel. The thing that you’re choosing to put your trust in really is trustworthy. When things go wrong around you, that doesn’t mean the Gospel’s gone wrong, it doesn’t mean that God’s gone wrong. You really can have complete faith in Him. He’s given you the ability to have an attitude of power, love and clear thinking, which means that you have nothing to be afraid of, in any circumstance. <br></br><br></br>So. Take the God–given, attitude–changing message of the Gospel, and know that you can carry it with faith, not with fear. Fear breeds fear. Fear welcomes in yet more fear. But faith welcomes in hope. Faith welcomes in [and] the presence of God. What’s your biggest fear? Write down any logical reasons that you have to be afraid. Now write down all the reasons you have to trust God, including Bible verses. Keep them close.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 18–20, Luke 2:16–32, Ps 71:1–16, Prov 2:1–2</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 12 January</p>
<p>‘…God has not given us a spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of a sound mind.’ 2 Timothy 1:7 NKJ</p>
<p>The Power of Love</p>
<p>Getting close to God means fear will shrivel; it’s the only thing that can happen as we get a sense of comfort and security in God’s love (see 1 John 4:8). So. The scene is set. What does God want to fill us with?<br></br><br></br>Check the verse again. POWER AND LOVE. Now, power on its own brings breakthrough, insight and whatever else God would use to move mountains in our lives. But it needs love. Living in a wholehearted, accepting way, looking to put others first, is the best way to live out Godly power. Ultimately, His will is for power and love to work together in us.<br></br><br></br>God Himself works like that. He is the King of extraordinary power, who is motivated by love. The first thing you’ll find in your Bible (Genesis 1:1) is His power to create the heavens and earth, and us. Humans. Now, we are His precious creation. He used His power to create something that He definitely loves [us]. A lot. Enough to die in our place, so that we can be in relationship with Him. All because of His love.<br></br><br></br>And He asks us to mirror that, to pair up His power with a love for the world. He’s more than willing to share those things with us; He gives us His spirit freely. Our world is bound to change when we step into that. What can you do today that combines power and love?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 21:1–23:25, Luke 2:33–40, Ps 71:17–24, Prov 2:3–5</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 13 January</p>
<p>‘…God has not given us a spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of a sound mind.’ 2 Timothy 1:7 NKJ</p>
<p>Sound.</p>
<p>Let’s get to the bottom of this verse from 2 Timothy. Having a ‘<i>sound mind</i>’ seems like an odd thing to be promised. Paul is reminding Timothy of the way God helps him process things. That includes the mental–tools that He makes available to all of us, but He has also given us His Word which tells us the godly way to live. Things like self–control and peace. Discernment is a big part of that. Now, we’ve all got some natural sense of what’s good for us, and what isn’t. Godly discernment, though, that comes with a sound mind from Him, goes a step further. God has gifted each of us with a sense of what's right and wrong (our conscience) to help us know what is wise and morally sound, from the mundane (maybe I shouldn’t be on Facebook when I have 43 deadlines tomorrow), right up to the more profound/harder–to–pin–down stuff. Like when we sense that something/somewhere just isn’t quite right, spiritually. Or when He gives us an idea that we REALLY shouldn’t go to that place, for our sake. Or maybe we sense the need to pray for and support someone, that we might not normally pick up on.<br></br><br></br>While the conscience God has given us, and His Spirit, guide us in an almost automatic fashion, we are still obligated to be work at being discerning. Paul encouraged Timothy in this way by reminding him to <i>'Follow the pattern of sound words' (</i>2 Timothy 1:13-14) he'd learned from Paul and the Scriptures, handling God's Word accurately (2 Timothy 2:15, 3:14-16). Right and wrong, good and evil, effective and ineffective, worthwhile and worthless. When faced with choices, God and His Word will give you a right sense of what to step in to, and what to step away from. So remember, read your Bible every day and ask God to help you discern life's challenges. Oh, and keep a list on your phone of the times that you feel it come into play starting today.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 23:26–25:55, Luke 2:41–52, Ps 74:1–11, Prov 2:6</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 14 January</p>
<p>‘…They prosper in all they do.’ Psalm 1:3 NLT</p>
<p>Proper Prosperity</p>
<p> ‘…<i>They prosper in all they do</i>.’ Sweet. Sorted, then? No action necessary, just go prosper. End of reading.<br></br><br></br>Or maybe not. Let’s take it back to the context. In fact, go read the first six verses of Psalm 1. Ah, so there’s more to this ‘prosperity’ thing than simply kicking back and saying, ‘alright God, hit my bank accounts with the extra zeroes.’ Let’s start from the beginning.<br></br><br></br>‘<i>Blessed is the man who walks not in the counsel of the wicked…but his delight is in the law of the Lord, and on His law he meditates day and night</i>.’ (Psalm 1:1–2 ESV) We have something to do, then. Our choices, whether we decide to spend time around people who drag us down, what influences we allow into our lives, how often we soak up God’s word… those things matter. And they’ll affect our productivity.<br></br><br></br>Verse 3 is all about that. It’s saying that, if we plant ourselves in God’s laws, we’ll flourish and produce fruit. That’s what it means to prosper. Prosperity isn’t necessarily a money thing. Psalm 1 suggests it’s anything that ‘<i>yields its fruit in season</i>’ (Psalm 1:3 ESV), so anything that bears good fruit. That’s something that blesses others, not just ourselves. It’s not just take–take–take. It’s as much about what we soak in, and what we give out, as it is about what we can get for ourselves.<br></br><br></br>Find your closest stream, river or lake, and go visit it. See if there’s anything growing alongside the river, like a tree. If there is, sit under it for at least fifteen minutes, spending time with God. If you’re feeling extra–summery, take a picnic and a friend along for that prayer time.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Lev 26–27, Luke 3:1–10, Ps 74:12–23, Prov 2:7–8</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 15 January</p>
<p>‘…Speak the truth in love…’ Ephesians 4:15 NLT</p>
<p>Why Try Harder?</p>
<p>Heard of today’s verse before? Speaking the truth in love can come across as a slightly vague instruction, but it’s really, really useful for building lasting relationships. The kind of relationships that get to a point where there’s an inevitable clash–of–preferences, and you’re left needing to resolve an issue.<br></br><br></br>So, yes, we’re going in at the deep end: what does it look like to resolve conflict in a healthy, godly way? In a difficult situation, it’s all too easy to make comments aimed directly at someone’s self–worth; something that only God should have a say in. Stuff like ‘You always mess up’, ‘Why do I bother with you?’ generally aren’t beneficial. They’re likely to leave bad feelings, rather than resolve the issue. All sorts of relationships fall over this kind of thing way too much. What’s a better approach is to focus on what the issue actually is—‘I don’t feel as though you made enough of an effort with that’ or ‘You upset me when you said that’ all stay truer to the issue.<br></br><br></br>So… Why bother trying? And, why is <i>Vision180</i> dishing out advice on this kind of thing? Well, we all need help to follow God’s will of avoiding arguing and complaining (Philippians 2:4). Let’s face it, it’s hard. Social media is a minefield for public naming and shaming and falling out. Our influences aren’t always biblical, so it’s good to get practical ideas under our belts on how to work things through. Today, cast your eyes over Philippians 2:1–18. It’s a challenging passage, but equally inspiring. Choose one piece of advice from it to REALLY live out today.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Phil 1–4, Luke 3:11–20, Ps 79, Prov 2:9–10</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 16 January</p>
<p>‘As soon as they were freed, Peter and John returned to the other believers…’ Acts 4:23 NLT</p>
<p>Burst Your Bubble</p>
<p>The first Christians were a tight–knit group. After anything went down in their community (like when Peter and John were hauled to the authorities just before today’s verse), they immediately got together, talked it over and praised God. As Christians it’s fantastic to have people around who will point us to God when things get tough, and when we have downtime. Who do you spend time with? Maybe you fit into one of two groups:<br></br><br></br>(1)  if you spend a lot of time with non–Christian friends, that’s really cool. In fact, having a friendship group that’s not all on your faith–wavelength is great for living out your faith. If they’re genuine friends, they won’t be put off by your Bible app or the fact you go to church on Sunday. Maybe you have these friends because it’s been difficult to get into a friendship group at church. You’re not alone in that, but it’s really important to make an effort to know some faith–minded folk. Even if they aren’t your best friends, a Christian grounding is important.<br></br><br></br>(2) And the flipside: if you find yourself with Christians most of the time, it’s cool. The first Christians did. Because you share more, at your core, with other followers of Jesus, you’ll naturally share more of a friendship base with them. But apply the same rule as above. It’s good to have a mix of friends so that you can naturally share your relationship with God with non–Christians who are growing to trust you. <br></br><br></br>Think your friendship group is mostly composed of Christians, or non–Christians? Pray about how you can make the first move in getting to know more of the other group.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Dan 1–2, Luke 3:21–38, Ps 81, Prov 2:11–15</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 17 January</p>
<p>‘…Enlarge my territory…’ 1 Chronicles 4:10 NKJ</p>
<p>More and Better Ahead 1</p>
<p>You don’t have to be afraid. Yes, you, the one with a shoddier job market waiting for you than your parents, a less certain housing situation and the pressure to have it all together already. Or, you, the one with a varied and painful romantic past. Or you, the one quietly figuring out where your life will go, trying to work hard and stay true to your friends and family.<br></br><br></br>Future fear getting the better of you? Jabez is a guy mentioned in the Bible—he only gets two verses. But what he says speaks for volumes of books (and, true, there have been volumes of books, and inspirational posters and bracelets and you name it…) Jabez understood the value of asking God to bless his future. ‘<i>Jabez called upon the God of Israel, saying, “Oh that You would bless me and enlarge my border, and that Your hand might be with me, and that You would keep me from harm so that it might not bring me pain!”</i>’ (1 Chronicles 4:10 ESV) This guy absolutely gets it! He welcomed God into his future, and depended on God being in that future. Are you struggling to let go of pain? Know that God doesn’t waste anything you’ve been through. Struggling to see a future? God won’t just protect you, He’ll enlarge your life, for good ends and for His closer and closer friendship every day. Every day and in every way, you, reader, are getting more glorious. <br></br><br></br>Write Jabez’s prayer, small, in the middle of the biggest piece of paper you can find and put it on your wall. No matter where you are in life, God has expanses of goodness waiting for you, in YOUR life, not way off in the clouds somewhere.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Judges 16:23–31, 2 Cor 12:3–11</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 18 January</p>
<p>‘…Go to the land that I will show you.’ Genesis 12:1 NLT</p>
<p>More and Better Ahead 2 </p>
<p>What if God spoke to you today and said: ‘Hey, ever read Matthew 19:21? Yeah? Go on then. Let go of everything, leave home, and I’ll take it from there’? We don’t reckon there’d be anyone out there that would find that an easy task. But that’s almost exactly what God asked Abraham to do. (Obviously without the Matthew reference. Chronological order and all that…) God said: ‘<i>Leave your native country, your relatives, and your father’s family, and go to the land that I will show you</i>’ (Genesis 12:1 NLT), and Abraham did. Note, God didn’t say ‘go to the land I’ve <i>already</i> shown you’, or even ‘the land I’m showing you now.’ He said ‘the land that I will show you.’ <i>Will</i>. As in, <i>haven’t already</i>. As in, <i>walk out in faith—trust Me, I know where I'm taking you</i>, even though you don't. Gulp. There’s a heap to learn in that. Imagine if we were more willing to live like Abraham. We’d say that getting our hearts into a place where we can make any change that God asks, because we trust Him wholly, would be brilliant. That’s the sort of heart that could hear Matthew 19:21, and just do it. Now, you don’t need to chuck everything into a rucksack and head out. That’s not what we’re saying. You just need to be willing to hear the need for change, any change, and make the choice to trust God enough to take the first step. Come back to us tomorrow for some more specific advice on that. But today, ask God to point out something you could do without, and a person to give it to. Then do it. Start letting Him direct you daily.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Dan 3–4, Luke 4:1–13, Ps 84, Prov 2:16–19</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 19 January</p>
<p>‘…Tell the children of Israel to go forward.’ Exodus 14:15 NKJ</p>
<p>More and Better Ahead 3</p>
<p>Exodus 14. Moses finds himself with a huge obstacle, the sea, and something has to change. That situation gives us a good picture of what we can feel when we’re facing tricky circumstances, where something has to change for us to move forward.<br></br><br></br>First, we get the people’s reaction (read verses 10-12). They’re like: ‘Moses, are you crazy? We’re going to die. We were better before, as slaves.’ Familiar? Ever been faced with a risky, big–change moment, and had no idea of how you’ll get through it? Sometimes, fear can make us want to turn back, to retreat to what we used to have, even if what we used to have was awful.<br></br><br></br>The second reaction we see is Moses’ (in verses 13- 14). He tells the people to calm down, stay still, and that God will do something. Closer to the mark, at least. But not quite there. He seems to have faith in God’s ability to help, but he just stays rooted. Also familiar. Option two: when faced with change, we just… don’t. We stop, and stagnate, waiting for something to swoop in and save us.<br></br><br></br>Verse 15, though, has the answer. God grabs Moses’ attention, and basically says, ‘Ok, chill. Stop all the blabbing. Just move. Go for it.’ He gives Moses just enough instructions for his next step, but no further than that. He’s asking Moses to trust, and to act. And that’s His advice to us. When we’re faced with a big change, we don’t need to retreat back, or get stuck. We just need to take the first, God–orchestrated step.<br></br><br></br>When you’re walking somewhere today, stop completely. Pray through something you’d like to see change, then take your next step, and carry on.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Dan 5–7, Luke 4:14–30, Ps 89:1–14, Prov 2:20</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 20 January</p>
<p>‘…I am the Lord your God, who teaches you what is good for you…’ Isaiah 48:17 NLT</p>
<p>The Good Stuff</p>
<p>Believe it or not, God wants what’s best for you. Isaiah 48:17 is a lovely verse, isn’t it? God gives us all the good things; He’s teaching us what we need to know. Great. Now onto verse 18. ‘<i>If only you had paid attention to My commands, your peace would have been like a river, your well–being like the waves of the sea.</i>’ Tough stuff. Let’s dig into that…<br></br><br></br>So, whether we’re talking about God’s commands that apply to everyone, or the things that He specifically teaches us, as individuals, the point is that we can live in a way that glorifies Him. Which is what God wants—to reveal Himself to the earth that He loves. Because of that, He makes sure that we have those commands available, and is constantly teaching us stuff. <br></br><br></br>So where does it go wrong? Well, rather than sticking with the stuff that makes us strong—God’s guide to living right, and the abilities and skills He’s honing in us—we start to look elsewhere. We forget to do what He’s asked, and we try to take charge of our own development. But that’s not where we find peace, or well–being. Read Isaiah 48:17 again. ‘<i>I am the Lord your God, who teaches you what is best for you, who directs you in the way you should go</i>.’ If you feel like you’re in need of some of that peace, you’ll find it in Him. If you feel like you’re off track, you’ll find your way back through Him. Just ask Him.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Dan 8–10, Luke 4:31–44, Ps 89:15–37, Prov 2:21–22</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 21 January</p>
<p>‘…Be careful not to fall.’ 1 Corinthians 10:12 CEV</p>
<p>Cheat–Proof</p>
<p>Most people don’t plan on having an affair. Perhaps that’s obvious. When a person gets married, they probably really mean their vows. So what goes wrong? And why are we talking about marriage again?<br></br><br></br>Well, there’s a good principle in here for all of us. Being faithful, having integrity in our relationships, doesn’t start with a ring. (You probably knew that, right?) Whatever level of relationship we’re at, as soon as we think ‘It couldn’t happen to <i>me</i>,’ we’re already dropping our guard for staying faithful. Our faithfulness when dating will become our faithfulness when married, if/when that happens. So how do we keep integrity in our relationships, whatever they look like right now? (1) <i>Talk with God, daily</i>. Jesus taught us to ask for daily bread (Matthew 6:7–13), so we’d need to go back to Him tomorrow. A daily relationship with God will arm us against distractions that might unravel us. Also note that the prayer is plural (OUR Father, OUR sins…) It’s designed to be prayed together. Is prayer at the centre of your relationship? It’s a solid idea to put it there. (2) <i>Talk along with God’s Word</i>. Chatting over the Bible together is a massively powerful tool in helping you live right, and strongly, together. (3) <i>Communicate with each other</i>. No–brainer maybe, this one, but chat with ‘other people’, about possible weaknesses you have, about threats to the relationship. Be honest, and ready to change if you’re putting a relationship at risk somehow. Listen and learn together. Put this into practice. If this doesn’t apply to you right now, chat the principles through with a mate and see how you can be prepping your heart, even now, for whatever future God has for you.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Dan 11–12, Luke 5:1–11, Ps 89:38–52, Prov 3:1–2</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 22 January</p>
<p>‘The law of the Lord is perfect…’ Psalm 19:7 NKJ</p>
<p>Psalm Dunk 1</p>
<p>Let us put this simply: God’s Word is powerful. Beyond this world, powerful. That’s not to say that the Bible is a magic book (hint: don’t worship the book itself but do have a BIG respect for what it says), but equally it’s not a human work, like Shakespeare or Aristotle. The Bible is a record of God’s words to humanity. It tells us what God says and is hugely powerful. Like, ‘<i>let there be light</i>’ powerful. So, using Psalm 19, here’s a rundown on that power in our Bible.<br></br><br></br>(1) ‘<i>The law of the Lord is perfect</i>…’ Your mind went straight to ‘do and don’t’ rules, didn’t it? But ‘law’ is much bigger. Like, ‘laws of physics’ bigger. You can question God as to whether His morals are perfect (hint: they are), but not many of us would question the law of gravity. His laws work. Often mysteriously, and perfectly. What does that tell us about the rest of His law?...<br></br><br></br>(2) ‘<i>The statutes of the Lord are trustworthy</i>…’ (Psalm 19:7 NIV) What, you <i>don’t</i> know everything? Woah. Guess what, neither do we. In the absence of personal omniscience, it turns out we need to decide what to trust. What God says is, by definition, trustworthy. It’s also been proven to be so, by folk who’ve followed it throughout history. No amount of study would get us to a place that’s wiser than the wisdom He offers us. Top tip, that. So, go read Psalm 19 from front to back. Ask yourself: the law of God made this psalm writer worship… why?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Jas 1–2, Luke 5:12–26, Ps 91, Prov 3:3–4</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 23 January</p>
<p>‘The commandments of the Lord are right…’ Psalm 19:8 NIV</p>
<p>Psalm Dunk 2</p>
<p>God’s commandments are not just right in the sense that they are logically correct. Psalm 19:8 NKJ says that God’s commandments are ‘<i>pure, enlightening the eyes</i>.’ Their holiness hurts the eyes. They’re more than human ideas: collected together, God’s laws are the guidelines from the One who is before time, and they bring His power and presence into any situation in creation.<br></br><br></br>As Psalm 19’s writer realised, by keeping God’s laws, we get a heads–up on what’s right and wrong that we wouldn’t get based off our own head–knowledge: ‘<i>By your teachings, Lord, I am warned; by obeying them, I am greatly rewarded</i>.’ (Psalm 19:11 CEV) Our own danger–radar is glitchy at best. And just hoping to upgrade it won’t do: we need an entirely new system. God’s is faultless, and His laws reflect that, even if we don’t always 100% understand it. The writer of Psalm 19 has such a massive appreciation of God’s law—there’s no lip service while hoping, under the breath, that they didn’t exist. (Does that sound strange? If so, priority check time: what matters most in life: God, or what other folk are getting up to? Sorry if that’s uncomfortable… but we mean it for the best, honest.) <br></br><br></br>Jesus said that the greatest commandment is love. That’s worth keeping in mind while reading the most famous laws: Deuteronomy 5:1–22. Go read them. Now, think about them as promises, not ‘you shall not or else...’ type rules, and read them again. Because of God’s love for you, and yours for Him, you’ll eventually not <i>want</i> to ‘<i>have other gods</i>’...Get the picture?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Jas 3–5, Luke 5:27–39, Ps 96, Prov 3:5–6</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 24 January</p>
<p>‘…You will be missed, because your seat will be empty.’ 1 Samuel 20:18 NIV</p>
<p>Shared History</p>
<p>We can so often live in an isolated way. Many of us can find it easier to pull away from people, preferring time in front of the TV or computer. We walk around looking at a phone screen instead of the people we’re passing, filling our lives with noise but missing real community. Maybe you feel lonely sometimes. Maybe you even feel like you don’t matter.<br></br><br></br>We matter so much to God that He was humbled, spat on, and killed—all so we would be called His. Not only that, but He sent Himself, and His people, to tell you. The person who put this <i>Vision180</i> reading into your hand (or onto your screen) cared enough to want you to see it. When we think about it, in fact, God’s done some pretty amazing things, arranged some pretty stunning ‘coincidences’, for some of us even given words, pictures and healings. He’s amazing, and has been pretty keen on showing us He thinks we’re amazing too.<br></br><br></br>But when we’re fearful or lonely, that isn’t always easy to remember. So hearing someone tell you about what God has done, ‘giving testimony’, can be an amazingly powerful encouragement. Ever shared your testimony to encourage someone? Ever asked someone for theirs? A friend’s testimony can be even better to hear—knowing the people in stories where God is at work can make these true stories even more powerful, and if you tell yours, you might even catch a glimpse of just a little of how much you matter.<br></br><br></br>This issue we’re getting in on the testimony action, so check out our featured testimonies, and maybe share them with a friend who they might help.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Ezek 47:1–12, Rev 21:22–22:5</p></body><body>
<p>Monday 25 January</p>
<p>‘…If you hold anything against anyone, forgive them…’ Mark 11:25 NIV</p>
<p>Onwards</p>
<p>It’s amazing what we can find comforting. Whether it’s a cuppa with plenty of milk and sugar, or an old jumper, the easiest things to hold onto when we feel in need of a little soothing are, most often, the things we’ve known and had for a while. <br></br><br></br>When we’re wronged, we can also find ourselves comforted by <i>not</i> forgiving. It’s easy to nestle down into being sure that we were in the right, that we’re the victim, almost holding it up as something to be proud of. The problem is that this can eat away at us, and leads to us becoming bitter and judgemental.<br></br><br></br>Jesus modelled true forgiveness. He didn’t even hold a grudge against the people who physically nailed Him to that piece of wood, or against those who tormented Him while He was dying. Luke 23:34, right? <br></br><br></br>Now, we know. You’re not Jesus. And forgiveness is hard. It is painful, humbling and often unfair. Sometimes, the really big things can take years, counselling, reconciliation and more, to be brought to a point of forgiveness. In those situations, we just need to be willing to take the first step, to begin the process, for the healthiness of our own lives. In fact, if you have something big like that to work through, have a conversation with someone you trust, and ask them to help you move on.<br></br><br></br>And as for the little things? That stuff that we really could let go of, here and now? Know that God has forgiven <i>you</i>, and pay that forward. Write down the unforgiven things you’ve held onto. Rip them up and go for a walk. Put them in a bin somewhere, and leave them behind.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Num 1–2, Luke 6:1–16, Ps 100, Prov 3:7–8</p></body><body>
<p>Tuesday 26 January </p>
<p>‘Children are a gift from the Lord…’ Psalm 127:3 ISV</p>
<p>Kids Are Alright 1</p>
<p>Ok, so you might not be the kind of person who gets squishy–feelings looking at a newborn’s placid face. You might not be the sort that could happily spend hours cartwheeling round a field with a six–year–old. But you still have something to learn from kids. They have a reckless innocence that we could all do with more of. Jesus knew it. He said, ‘<i>Truly, I say to you, unless you turn and become like children, you will never enter the Kingdom of Heaven</i>.’ (Matthew 18:3 ESV) Kids don’t need to feel like they have it all sorted. Rather than worry what people think of the toys they left all over the living room, they’re focused on the joy they get from playing with what they’ve been given. We reckon it’s about time we shake off the self–consciousness that keeps asking, ‘But what will people think?’ and live the life in the way that God frees us up to do. <br></br><br></br>That includes showing grace, and not worrying about always being ‘right’. Sometimes, the worry of looking like we’ve lost an argument, particularly a theological debate, can sap the innocent, child–like joy of telling people about Jesus. It can also push them away. Question to take away (well, two actually): Are you known for being right, or for showing grace? Are you known for your joy, or your flawless always–having–it–togetherness? Challenge for today: (1) play on a playground (2) buy something from an ice cream van (whatever it is must include sprinkles) (3) have a water fight. Extra points if you can do all three with a child you know.</p>
<p>SoulFood Australia Day: Num 3:1–4:33, Luke 6:17–26, Ps 104:1–23, Prov 3:9–10</p></body><body>
<p>Wednesday 27 January</p>
<p>‘…Blessed are those who have many children…’ Psalm 127:5 NIV</p>
<p>Kids Are Alright 2</p>
<p>So, you took on yesterday’s advice, and had a day filled with childish joyfulness, openness and confidence. Really, really great. But now we have to raise the question… what about when it doesn’t seem to work? Especially in how we speak to others about Jesus? What do we do when our sincere living doesn’t bring people into God’s Kingdom in the way that we expect? Well, go read the story of Cain and Abel in Genesis 4:1–16. They both had the same input–parenting from Adam and Eve—and one turned out great, the other… not so much. That can be how our evangelistic living and out–loud–Gospel–sharing works out, too. We can try our best, share Jesus with child–like optimism, and still not see results. But that’s ok. When we’re being faithful to God; He sees, and treasures, our efforts. Not all of them fall on good soil (in Matthew 13:3–9 fashion), but we can trust that it’s all part of God’s plan.<br></br><br></br>However, we do still have to make those efforts. Proverbs 22:6 AMP gives some advice we could use to do that: ‘Train up a child in… keeping with his individual gift or bent.’ <br></br><br></br>We’re not saying treat people like kids, but to recognise we have to teach people about Jesus in a way that’s right for them. For some people, that means they need to be told about His love straight away. Some will have to be shown that love for a while, before they’re ready for us to share the truth of Jesus with them.<br></br><br></br>Pray for God to show you who’s ready to hear about Him. Then actively invite them to get to know Him, in whatever way seems right for them.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Num 4:34–6:27, Luke 6:27–42, Ps 104:24–35, Prov 3:11–12</p></body><body>
<p>Thursday 28 January</p>
<p>‘I will instruct you and teach you in the way you should go…’ Psalm 32:8 NIV</p>
<p>‘Whoever Does The Will Of My Father...’</p>
<p>We can spend a lot of our days just–about–half–sure we’re doing the right thing. Sometimes we get those lightning moments where we feel particularly prodded from Above to do something. But, even when we feel called by God to do something, we can start to question it afterwards. Mostly, it’s easy to drift along and, well, simply guess at what we’re supposed to be doing next. <br></br><br></br>The thing is, God does have a plan, and it’s better than anything we could guess at (see Proverbs 19:21 for details). And sometimes, we need to make a decent effort to move into a place where we can hear it, rather than just drifting, guessing and vaguely hoping that He might give us some directions at some point. One of the biggest shifts that can help with this is ‘surrendering your will’. Yeah, we know, Christian–cliché siren time. But seriously. When we really dig into it, that phrase means one thing. Sacrifice. Putting God’s will above our own means that we have to learn to sacrifice[ing] our own expectations and strivings, to be replaced by His. That’s costly (not always financially, sometimes even in time, or reputation), occasionally uncomfortable or awkward, and most definitely inconvenient. But it’s so worth it. Check out Matthew 12:50 for why. Mind. Blown.<br></br><br></br>If you’re ready for it, repeat Jesus’ words in John 5:30—‘I seek not my own will but the will of God’—a few times. Then write three things you can do for others this week: one that costs time, one that’s inconvenient, and one that’s outside of your comfort zone. Ask someone to keep you accountable to do them this week.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Num 7, Luke 6:43–7:10, Ps 107:1–9, Prov 3:13–18</p></body><body>
<p>Friday 29 January</p>
<p>‘…We take captive every thought to make it obedient to Christ.’ 2 Corinthians 10:5 NIV</p>
<p>Wrestled Into Line</p>
<p>Hebrews 12:11 AMP says: ‘<i>For the time being no [aspect of] discipline brings joy, but seems grievous and painful; but afterwards it yields a peaceable fruit of righteousness to those who have been trained by it</i>...’ That’s particularly true when it comes to having our thoughts wrestled into line with what God wants for us. Let’s face it, we’re the kind of people that are used to being able to make noodles in three minutes, and instantly video–chat with the person we want to speak to, rather than wait for a snail–mail reply. We’re the instant gratification generation. So, when we come to ‘<i>take captive every thought</i>’ (2 Corinthians 10:5 NIV), it’s a struggle. Because, when we first start to try, it doesn’t feel good. It doesn’t feel natural. It doesn’t feel as easy as adding 500ml of boiling water to a pot of dehydrated carbs. <br></br><br></br>Let’s go back to Hebrews 12:11. Discipline, as we said, doesn’t bring immediate joy. But we do get ‘<i>trained</i>’ by it. Like marathon training, the first few attempts are gruelling, hard work, even painful. But we can get to a point of it becoming a little easier (though, as long as we’re human, it’s never going to be 100% easy).<br></br><br></br>God will help, but it’s on us to make the right choices, daily. And the more we do it, on purpose, the more instinctive it’ll become to choose to think about the things that draw us closer to Him.<br></br><br></br>Today’s challenge: Set an alarm for every hour of the day, between 9am and 9pm (a silent one if necessary). Whatever your thoughts are on when the alarm goes off, no matter how God–orientated or not, pray through that thing.</p>
<p>SoulFood: Num 8–10, Luke 7:11–23, Ps 107:10–16, Prov 3:19–20</p></body><body>
<p>Saturday 30 January</p>
<p>‘…He shall direct your paths.’ Proverbs 3:6 NKJ</p>
<p>The Journey</p>
<p>We live in an era where we don’t need to plan any journeys. We can just tap our desired destination into the <i>Google Maps</i>, and off we go. However, you’re not human if you’ve never challenged that little electronic voice, thinking you have a better idea. Chances are, overriding the thing that’s made to get you somewhere safely doesn’t end well (unless it thinks that river is the highway…)<br></br><br></br>It can be a similar story in our journey with God. Now, He’s never going to lead us the wrong way, but when we can’t see where we’re headed, it’s tempting to want to wrestle control back. <br></br><br></br>Psalm 23 describes both ends of the journey. At the top of the scale, we can find that God leads us through ‘<i>green pastures</i>’ (Psalm 23:2 ESV), a place where we can be restored and find rest. At the low point, we can be in the ‘<i>darkest valley</i>.’ (Psalm 23:4 NIV) Loneliness, conflict, struggling. Real difficulties certainly aren’t a walk in the park, but that doesn’t mean they’re the time to ignore what God’s saying and go your own way. He knows what He’s doing. Hard times make us grow. God will always have your back (see today’s verse), and will make sure your journey is more than worth it.<br></br><br></br>The question that we have to face, wherever we are in our journey, is this: Are we going to keep our eyes fixed on Him, trusting that He knows what’s best for us?</p>
<p>SoulFood: Num 11–13, Luke 7:24–35, Ps 107:17–22, Prov 3:21–24</p></body><body>
<p>Sunday 31 January</p>
<p>‘…My strength is made perfect in weakness…’ 2 Corinthians 12:9 NIV</p>
<p>Vulnerable</p>
<p>Before Adam and Eve messed up, we’re told that ‘<i>they were both naked… and… not ashamed</i>.’ (Genesis 2:25 NKJ) Now why, of all the details we could be told about Adam and Eve, is the fact they were starkers something we’d need to know?<br></br><br></br>Well, eventually, Adam and Eve messed up (*spoiler alert*). They separated themselves from God, and began to feel awkward about their nakedness. And since then, so have the rest of us: nakedness is a big deal. It means we’re vulnerable. (This is also why that birthday–suit is for life–long, covenant–bound relationships only. Marriage matters, folks.)<br></br><br></br>We reckon we’re told about Adam and Eve’s lack of clothing so that we can track the change in how they feel about that, in relation to God. Suddenly, they start to feel they have something to (literally) hide. They feel weak, and helpless. Which you would, in the middle of a huge garden with no clothes on, having just realised the situation. Anyone who’s worn a swimming suit in public has a glimpse of that self–consciousness.<br></br><br></br>But. God saw them, and sees us, for all that we are, regardless of how we try to hide. No matter how much we dread being seen, weak and vulnerable, stripped down to the real us, He sees every lumpy, blemished, undesirable bit of us, and loves us anyway. Yes, we mean that He loves every bit of your body that you hate. But we mean your soul, too (we’re guessing you spotted that already). Don’t dread being real with Him. He sees you, and loves you (yes, YOU). </p>
<p>SoulFood: Exod 16:1–35, John 6:30–40 </p>
</body>
</html>