<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE j2xml PUBLIC "-//eshiol.it//DTD J2XML data file 1.5.6//EN" "http://www.eshiol.it/j2xml/1506/j2xml.dtd">
<j2xml version="1.5.6">
<content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2541]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Problem solved]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[problem-solved]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['God...is the...controller of all things.' 1 Timothy 6:15 PHPS<br /><br /><p>We all get that fluttery feeling in our stomachs-it might be confirmation that last night's turkey twizzlers did actually need a further ten minutes in the oven or it might mean you're suffering with a bad case of worry. So how do you stop that seasick sensation? First, always ensure your food is piping hot. Second, get a grip on your anxiety. </p>
<p>Scribble down your problem on paper. What exactly are you worrying about? Be specific. Then put your brain in gear. Write down alternative solutions to your problem. Weigh each solution up-ask yourself 'What've I got to lose?' and 'What've I got to gain?' Face up to your fear. Now you have it on paper, face each possible outcome and prepare yourself what it would mean if the worst did happen. </p>
<p>Commit yourself to improving the situation. Is there something you could do, practically, that would help ensure the best possible outcome? Most importantly give it over to God. Pray for wisdom. Bend your ear to what He's saying through the Word. After all, He is 'the...controller of all things'. Shape your problems into praises and watch your problem perspective-shift. '...if any of you needs wisdom, you should ask God for it. He is generous and enjoys giving to all people, so He will give you wisdom. But...you must...not doubt.' (James 1:5-6 NCV)</p>
<br /><br />SoulFood: Dan 3-4, Luke 22:39-46, Ps 130, Pr 10:12<br /><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=21661&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-04-14 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-04-14 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3991]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[problem, paper, what, would, mean, the, worst, did, happen, commit]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['God...is the...controller of ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[986]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2542]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Seal the deal]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[seal-the-deal]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Having believed, you were marked...with a seal...' Ephesians 1:13 NIV<br /><br /><p>People have ideas about getting into heaven that are not taught in the Bible. At funerals we hear how 'Old Ermitrude always watched <i>Songs of Praise</i>' as if somehow this is worth extra brownie points for her at the gates of eternity. Some people say, 'I'm a good person-if there's a God, I'll be all right.' </p>
<p>But Heaven doesn't have an entrance for 'good' people-it's through the sinner's door people cross the threshold. Other folks believe that Heaven's here, on earth. If a world of heartbreak and selfishness is the definition of Heaven, it's time to get a new dictionary. Nope, Jesus said, 'I am the way, and the truth, and the life. The only way to the Father is through Me.' (John 14:6 NCV) The road marked 'Jesus' is the only route to Heaven. Stake your life on Jesus and you're promised eternity with Him. He doesn't need your good works, your Christian catchphrases and passwords; He just wants you. </p>
<p>If you've given yourself over to Him, 'you were marked...with a seal, the promised Holy Spirit...guaranteeing [your]...redemption.' (Ephesians 1:13-14 NIV) No ifs, no buts, no maybes. Redemption: that means He bought you for a price. Jesus' death on the cross paid the price for your sin and bought your ticket to the afterlife. The deal is sealed. You don't have to worry about impressing God to get your name on the guest list-Jesus has got you covered. </p>
<br /><br />SoulFood: Dan 5-7, Luke 22:47-53, Ps 103:1-12, Pr 10:13<br /><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=21662&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-04-15 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-04-15 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3992]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[seal, ephesians, sians, nivpeople, people, say, good, person, there, god]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Having believed, you were mar]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[994]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2543]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Peep show]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[peep-show]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['... the sin that so easily trips us up...' Hebrews 12:1 NLT<br /><br /><p>Once upon a time, all a young person had to worry about was jamming their foot into a teeny glass slipper in the hopes of one day marrying a Prince Charming. However, things have changed and the world has rapidly grown into one big peep show. With the lyrics of some of the songs on our iPods, is it any wonder we struggle to keep those thoughts pure? </p>
<p>Well, today we're going to trial a tactic for standing up against the 'sin that so easily trips us up'. </p>
<p><i>First, get busy with your delete</i> <i>button</i>. If there's stuff on your iPod or on your hard drive that you know trips you up, delete it now. Why throw fuel on sin's fire? <i>Second, watch what you watch</i>. You need to turn off anything you're watching because it's a turn on. <i>Third, be your own boss</i>. When you start to fantasise about the curves and bumps of the opposite sex, be the boss of your brain. Take control-focus on something that won't lead you down Sin Street. <i>Fourth, show some respect</i>. That person you're ogling is somebody's future wife or husband-keep your hands off. <i>Fifth, beware of the</i> <i>baby.</i> It grows up. James 1:15 NCV warns: '...desire leads to sin, and then the sin grows and brings death.' </p>
<br /><br />SoulFood: Ps 118:19-29, Matt 21:1-16<br /><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=21663&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-04-16 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-04-16 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3993]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[peep, show, with, your, delete, button, husband, keep, hands, off]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['... the sin that so easily tr]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[965]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2545]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Follow like sheep]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[follow-like-sheep]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['The Lord is my shepherd...' Psalm 23:1 NKJ<br /><br /><p>So you might not download too many tunes based on sheep but, in David's day, his biggest seller was a little song by the name of Psalm 23. It opens with a line about a sheep's best friend. Why bother mentioning our fluffy little friends? </p>
<p>After all they're just dumb animals. They wander about with no purpose other than filling their own stomachs. They'll happily eat the grass at the edge of a cliff. They can't stand up for themselves; in a death-match between a wolf and a sheep, the bloodthirsty creature will claw and bite and use fangs, while the sheep will try and knit a two-tone cardigan with its finest wool. They're dirty: while a cat prides itself on keeping clean, a sheep is happy in the muck. Well, sorry about the dent to your pride, but the descriptions could fit you too. Think about it, we can wander through life without any purpose. We'll happily walk unawares into dangerous situations. We're sure no match for that spiritual wolf: Satan. And often we're filthy with sin. </p>
<p>What any dumb sheep needs is a good shepherd to stop it from falling into a dangerous ditch. Jesus is the Good Shepherd. His is the voice you need to hear for life. He's the one who will rescue you from the devil's schemes. He's the one who can clean you up. Will you follow like a sheep? </p>
<br /><br />SoulFood: Dan 8-10, Luke 22:54-62, Ps 103:13-22, Pr 10:14<br /><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=21664&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-04-17 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-04-17 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3994]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[follow, like, sheep, soulfood, ood, dan, luke, uke]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['The Lord is my shepherd...' P]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1053]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2546]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Want for nothing]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[want-for-nothing]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['... I shall not want.' Psalm 23:1 NKJ<br /><br /><p>Remember how you just <b>had</b> to do retail therapy? You put Myers out of stock on your pilgrimage! And as you burned plastic at the till you had that fluttering feeling in your stomach that finally your life was complete thanks to a pair of slouchy, well-worn denims. </p>
<p>Click forward one weekend and you're back where you started-feeling empty, in need of your next retail therapy. You see, as Luke 12:15 NLT puts it, 'Don't be greedy for what you don't have. Real life is not measured by how much we own.' Long-term happiness isn't found in a department store; authentic joy comes from going deep with God. </p>
<p>That's what poet David was getting at with 'The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want'. What we have with God far outweighs what we don't have. Pastor Jack Hinton understood that when he went on a mission trip to a leper colony. While leading worship, a woman who'd been facing away from him turned round. Her face was totally eaten up by leprosy. She had no nose, no ears; she lifted a fingerless hand in the air and asked, 'Can we sing <i>Count Your Blessings</i>?' Wow-what an attitude. Despite all illness had thrown at her, this woman cottoned on that she was blessed: she had a friend in the author of the universe. </p>
<p>Is your life harsh? Focus on the good of God and you'll pull through it. </p>
<br /><br />SoulFood: Dan 11-12, Luke 22:63-71, Ps 16, Pr 10:15<br /><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=21665&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-04-18 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-04-18 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3995]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[want, psalm, alm, nkjremember, member, how, you, just, had, retail]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['... I shall not want.' Psalm ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[920]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2549]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Less is more]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[less-is-more]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['He makes me to lie down in green pastures.' Psalm 23:2 NKJ<br /><br /><p>'He makes me to lie down in green pastures...' Who wants to slump on a field and get bitten by mozzies while collecting pollen up your hooter? Actually, this verse isn't really about hay fever and grassy lawns, it's a reminder how taking rest is good for the soul. </p>
<p>So, you think that cloud-spotting in the sunny outdoors isn't going to build God's Kingdom on this planet? Since when has saving the planet been solely left to you? Life goes on with you; life goes on without you. A spot of charging the batteries, enjoying God's creation, praising out in the open is part of what you need to fulfil God's calling. </p>
<p>It's so vital that God didn't just commend it, He <i>commanded</i> it. Of all the ten commandments Moses took from God, the one which was spelled out using the most words was the one about rest. Clearly God didn't want us to miss out on this one. Each week, we are to work into it twenty four hours of slowing down, sitting down, lying down, saying 'no' to work and 'yes' to worship. </p>
<p>It reminds us that the be-all and end-all of the world doesn't rest with us. It reminds us that we are made for God's pleasure and we are to enjoy Him. It reminds us that even God, Creator of everything, rested on the seventh day-and the world didn't crash. So chill out-God commands it. </p>
<br /><br />SoulFood: Jam 1-2, Luke 23:1-12, Ps 7:1-9, Pr 10:16<br /><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=21666&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-04-19 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-04-19 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3996]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[less, more, aletheia, soul, lely, left, you, life, goes, without]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['He makes me to lie down in gr]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1025]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2551]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Still waters]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[still-waters]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['He leads me beside the still waters.' Psalm 23:2 NKJ<br /><br /><p>Philip Yancey says, 'Faith means trusting in advance, what will only make sense in reverse.' If you fear the future, look back and see how God took care of you in the past. Don't visit fortune tellers at the fair or read your star signs. God tells us to say 'no' to that stuff and anyway His guidance is nothing like that. Even though He can see the whole of the future, He often doesn't let us in on it (and if He does, He usually only gives us glimpses rather than complete chapters). </p>
<p>Truth is, you were made to live for today. Anything that happens in the future will happen anyway, so why worry about tomorrow? Let Proverbs 3:5-7 NLT massage those tense muscles with these words: 'Trust in the Lord with all your heart; do not depend on your own understanding. Seek His will in all you do, and He will direct your paths. Don't be impressed with your own wisdom. Instead, fear the Lord and turn your back on evil.' </p>
<p>Did you get that? 'Don't be impressed with your own wisdom.' It's not joss-sticks and deep breathing relaxation exercises that lead us to still waters-it's God. Jesus said, 'If people want to follow Me, they must give up the things they want. They must be willing to give up their lives daily to follow Me.' (Luke 9:23 NCV) Do you trust Jesus at the wheel careering you over rough terrain ahead? '...trust yourself to the God who made you, for He will never fail you.' (1 Peter 4:19 NLT)</p>
<br /><br />SoulFood: Jam 3-5, Luke 23:13-25, Ps 7:10-17, Pr 10:17-18<br /><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=21667&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-04-20 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-04-20 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3997]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[still, waters, psalm, alm, nkjphilip, philip, yancey, says, faith, ith]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['He leads me beside the still ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1028]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2552]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Good Friday - In Hope]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[good-friday-in-hope]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...in hope that the creation itself will be liberated...' Romans 8:20-21 NIV<br /><br /><p>What would this day have been like for the disciples? For three fantastic years they'd being living the dream. They'd been in Jesus' entourage. But there was more than that, more than just being the centre of attention in every town and village they visited. Deep down in their own hearts they knew that they'd found the One, the Messiah, the hope their nation had been waiting for. Life was making sense, miracles were happening every day, and they weren't just spectators-they were in the thick of the action. And then it all got a bit serious. They found themselves looking over their shoulders after dark. They started hearing whispers and rumours. And Jesus himself started saying crazy things about having to leave them to go elsewhere, to a place they couldn't follow Him.   </p>
<p>Today is a day of remembrance for us but not really a day of sadness because we know the end of the story. But for the disciples and the other close friends of Jesus this Friday afternoon was heart-breaking on an unimaginable scale. Jesus had tried to encourage them to trust Him but they just didn't understand. They couldn't see what He could see.  And how often are we just like them? When God allows sadness and suffering to cross our path we can quickly find ourselves feeling depressed or victimised because we don't see the other side. Paul reflects back on the 'frustration' of the whole world and says even that was 'in hope' of a future liberation. That's the liberation we celebrate over this weekend, Jesus bringing freedom to all creation through His death and resurrection! </p><br /><br />SoulFood: Gen 22:1-18, Luke 23:26-49, Ps 22, Is 53<br /><img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=21677&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''>]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-04-21 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-04-21 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3998]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[good, friday, hope, that, the, creation, itself, will, liberated, romans]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...in hope that the creation ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1190]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2579]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[I'm lovin' it! (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[im-lovin-it-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...do not set aside...grace...' Galatians 2:21 NKJ<br /><br />
<p>Which is easier: earning love or being loved? Earning love is like treating God's grace as some kind of wages for the work we do for Him. So every time we pop our tithe into the offering, we've earned a heavenly pat on the back. Or if we manage the Lord's Prayer before drifting off to dreamland, we get another tick on our scorecard from God.</p>
<p>The problem is thinking we have to earn God's love so it is up to us to keep the momentum going. This leads to more wrong thinking<em>'</em><em>i</em><em>f we</em><em>'</em><em>re performing </em><em>ok </em><em>God must think we</em><em>'</em><em>re </em><em>ok</em><em>'</em> and <em>'</em><em>if we let </em><em>go</em><em> of God, </em><em>He</em><em>'</em><em>ll</em><em> let </em><em>go</em><em> of us</em><em>'</em>. Striving to look right, sound right, and say the right things will suffocate us if we are doing it in our own strength.</p>
<p>Being loved by God is a much easier deal. God's love doesn't get the weighing scales out to measure how well we're doing. He doesn't mark a nasty red cross next to all our efforts. He doesn't ask us to toe the company line without concern for our wellbeing.</p>
<p>God's love can set us free from all the pressure of worrying we are only loved if we are perfect; He accepts us as we are, warts and all. Being loved by God takes the emphasis off our efforts and stresses the importance of who we areHis children. Responding to God's grace is far more freeing than trying to earn brownie points. After all it's God who cleans up our act, not us. Ask Him.</p>
<br /><br />SoulFood: Num 32:25-33:56, Mark 5:11-20, Ps 44:17-26, Pr 11:12-13<br /><img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=23332&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; />]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-05-08 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2011-06-02 06:35:25]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-05-08 14:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3999]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[lovin, aletheia, etheia, not, set, aside, grace, galatians, tians, nkjwhich]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...do not set aside...grace..]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1596]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2572]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[I'm lovin' it! (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[im-lovin-it-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[I'm lovin' it! (1)<br />'...do not set aside...grace...' Galatians 2:21 NKJ<br />Which is easier: earning love or being loved? Earning love is like treating God's grace as some kind of wages for the work we do for Him. So every time we pop our tithe into the offering, we've earned a heavenly pat on the back. Or if we manage the Lord's Prayer before drifting off to dreamland, we get another tick on our scorecard from God.<br />The problem is thinking we have to earn God's love so it is up to us to keep the momentum going. This leads to more wrong thinking-'if we're performing ok God must think we're ok' and 'if we let go of God, He'll let go of us'. Striving to look right, sound right, and say the right things will suffocate us if we are doing it in our own strength.<br />Being loved by God is a much easier deal. God's love doesn't get the weighing scales out to measure how well we're doing. He doesn't mark a nasty red cross next to all our efforts. He doesn't ask us to toe the company line without concern for our wellbeing.<br />God's love can set us free from all the pressure of worrying we are only loved if we are perfect; He accepts us as we are, warts and all. Being loved by God takes the emphasis off our efforts and stresses the importance of who we are-His children. Responding to God's grace is far more freeing than trying to earn brownie points. After all it's God who cleans up our act, not us. Ask Him.<br />SoulFood: Num 32:25-33:56, Mark 5:11-20, Ps 44:17-26, Pr 11:12-13]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-05-09 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2011-05-31 04:53:23]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-05-03 01:24:02]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[4]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[4000]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA[]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[2187]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2573]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[I'm lovin' it! (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[im-lovin-it-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[I'm lovin' it! (2)<br />'...we have been made holy through the sacrifice...of Jesus Christ once for all.' Hebrews 10:10 NIV<br />Picture this: you're effortlessly radiant; a shining bride about to seal the nuptial deal with your forever sweetheart. You've come to the part where the celebrant says, 'And will you love her; for richer, for poorer; for better or worse?' Instead of coming out with the obligatory 'I will', your hubby-to-be reaches into his pocket and pulls out a long list he's scribbled on a piece of scrap paper.<br />The list includes: 'I hereby will love her, but only on the conditions she ditches her Myer store card, learns the finer details of the offside rule, and never again sings Lamb-chop's <em>Song That Never Ends</em>.'<br />Come on, girls, how many seconds before you connected your fist to your fiancé's teeth? We wouldn't get very far in a relationship based on terms and conditions. And yet for some reason, we can place terms and conditions on our relationship with God.<br />We imagine God's long list of reasons that stop Him from loving us: they don't read their Bible enough, they think rude thoughts, they lose their temper, etc etc. Romans 8:38-39 NIV reminds us that God is the complete opposite of pick 'n' choose love: '...neither death nor life, neither angels nor demons, neither the present nor the future, nor any powers, neither height nor depth, nor anything else in all creation, will be able to separate us from the love of God that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.'<br />SoulFood: Num 34-36, Mark 5:21-30, Ps 57, Pr 11:14]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2011-05-10 14:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2011-05-31 04:52:49]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2011-05-03 01:25:02]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[3]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[4001]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA[]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[2484]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[697]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[K1 (Part A)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[k1-part-a]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[<h2 class=&quot;subtitle&quot;>…MAKE THE KINGDOM OF GOD YOUR PRIMARY CONCERN.</h2>
<span class=&quot;reference&quot;>MATTHEW 6:33 NLT</span><br />What does it mean to put God’s kingdom first in your life? Well, there’s loads of good answers to that question, here’s a top ten: a) love ‘…love your enemies…If you love only those who love you, what good is that?...’ (Matthew 5:44-46 NLT) b) faith in God ‘If you had faith as small as a mustard seed…Nothing would be impossible.’ ‘…But with God, everything is possible.’ (Matthew 17:20; Matthew 19:26 NLT) c) obedience to God ‘…anyone who obeys God’s laws and teaches them will be great in the Kingdom of Heaven’ (Matthew 5:19 NLT) d) holy living ‘…let your good deeds shine out for all to see, so that everyone will praise your heavenly Father’ (Matthew 5:16 NLT) e) disciple-making ‘Therefore, go and make disciples of all the nations…’ (Matthew 28:19 NLT) f) justice ‘God blesses those who are hungry and thirsty for justice…’ (Matthew 5:6 NLT) g) peace ‘God blesses those who work for peace…’ (Matthew 5:9 NLT) h) generosity ‘When you give a gift to someone in need…Give your gifts in secret, and your Father, who knows all secrets, will reward you’ (Matthew 6:2-4 NLT) i) integrity ‘Just say a simple, ‘Yes, I will’ or ‘No, I won’t’…’ (Matthew 5:37 NLT) j) biblical knowledge ‘…Your problem is that you don’t know the Scriptures…’ (Matthew 22:29 NLT).  PS The point is not what order they come in – it’s making sure you have them in your life!]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2006-07-27 00:00:00]]></created>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2011-05-10 01:35:35]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2009-04-02 00:00:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[3]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[4002]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA[]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[3449]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><section mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[8]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Broadcast]]></title>
<name><![CDATA[]]></name>
<alias><![CDATA[broadcast]]></alias>
<image><![CDATA[]]></image>
<scope><![CDATA[content]]></scope>
<image_position><![CDATA[left]]></image_position>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
<published><![CDATA[1]]></published>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<ordering><![CDATA[7]]></ordering>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<params><![CDATA[]]></params>
</section><category mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[33]]></id>
<parent_id><![CDATA[0]]></parent_id>
<title><![CDATA[word4U2day]]></title>
<name><![CDATA[]]></name>
<alias><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></alias>
<image><![CDATA[]]></image>
<image_position><![CDATA[left]]></image_position>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
<published><![CDATA[1]]></published>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<ordering><![CDATA[10]]></ordering>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<params><![CDATA[]]></params>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
</category><user mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4188]]></id>
</user><user mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4371]]></id>
</user><user mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[1123]]></id>
<name><![CDATA[Grant Kennedy]]></name>
<username><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></username>
<email><![CDATA[gkennedy@ucb.com.au]]></email>
<password><![CDATA[2c1254eec94d77359316370e0ab0d994:ns4oKlgpodxSB6vTneF3cmpOcoC5cjZ3]]></password>
<usertype><![CDATA[Super Administrator]]></usertype>
<block><![CDATA[0]]></block>
<sendEmail><![CDATA[1]]></sendEmail>
<gid><![CDATA[25]]></gid>
<registerDate><![CDATA[2009-04-16 01:37:00]]></registerDate>
<lastvisitDate><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:05:05]]></lastvisitDate>
<activation><![CDATA[]]></activation>
<params><![CDATA[admin_language=
language=
editor=
helpsite=
timezone=10

]]></params>
</user></j2xml>