<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE j2xml PUBLIC "-//eshiol.it//DTD J2XML data file 1.5.6//EN" "http://www.eshiol.it/j2xml/1506/j2xml.dtd">
<j2xml version="1.5.6">
<content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2334]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[How to Test Your Thoughts]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[how-to-test-your-thoughts]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...We take captive every thought to make it obedient to Christ.' 2 Corinthians 10:5 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150729.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;You will never be any better, wiser or happier than the thoughts that influence you. You say, ‘I can’t help it; these thoughts just come into my mind.’ Yes, you can! ‘The weapons we fight with…have divine power to demolish strongholds…we take captive every thought to make it obedient to Christ.’ (2 Corinthians 10:4–5 NIV) A ‘stronghold’ is a thought–pattern that controls you. It could be fear, greed, inferiority, lust, etc. It’s a ‘stronghold’ because it holds you strongly in its grip. How do you break that grip? With God’s Word. For example, when fear and inadequacy tell you you’re not good enough to succeed, become proactive and say, ‘I can do all things through Christ who strengthens me.’ (Philippians 4:13 NKJV) If your immediate goal is to ‘feel good’, you’ll never develop self–control. ‘For the time being no discipline brings joy, but seems grievous and painful; but afterwards it yields a peaceable fruit of righteousness to those who have been trained by it…’ (Hebrews 12:11 AMP) Discipline doesn’t bring immediate joy, but it brings lasting joy later on. Note the words ‘trained by it’. You must train your mind to go the right way; otherwise it’ll take you the wrong way. God says, ‘…I have set before you life and death, blessing and cursing: therefore choose life…’ (Deuteronomy 30:19 NKJV) God gives you choices. But He won’t make your choices for you; you must do that. In order to walk in God’s blessing each day, you must choose the right thoughts each day, and the longer you keep doing it the easier it will become. You’ve just got to get through the ‘training’ period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezra 3-5, Mark 1:21-34, Ps 78:9-16, Prov 19:24-26&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright © 2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67172&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-28 15:08:16]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[135]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-08-04 11:02:42]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-28 15:08:16]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[how, test, your, immediate, goal, feel, good, you, never, develop]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...We take captive every thou]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1195]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2335]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Stop Trying To Control Everything (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[stop-trying-to-control-everything-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...He shall direct your paths.' Proverbs 3:6 NKJV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150730.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Without self–control we end up hurting ourselves, but when we become overly controlling of ourselves or others, it’s an indication that we’re not trusting God enough. In the final analysis God alone determines our outcomes. So: ‘Trust in the Lord with all your heart, and lean not on your own understanding; in all your ways acknowledge Him, and He shall direct your paths.’ (Proverbs 3:5–6 NKJV) If you find yourself trying to control every detail and aspect of your life, try using these strategies for developing the right mindset: (1) Understand that you are not an independent, self–sufficient being. ‘…We are His people, and the sheep of His pasture.’ (Psalm 100:3 NKJV) Sheep cannot take care of themselves; they need the shepherd to feed them, lead and protect them. Getting the idea? (2) When the unexpected happens, practise responding calmly. God is never taken by surprise. What seems like a crisis is often an opportunity for Him to demonstrate His love and care for you. (3) Focus on the internal and leave the external to God. Once you settle within yourself that you cannot control most external happenings, but only your internal response to them, you’ll be able to stop stressing out over the uncontrollable and the inevitable. Take a deep breath to slow the flow of adrenaline, send up a silent prayer, then turn the problem over to God. Realise that His plans for your life have not been derailed. ‘You saw me before I was born. Every day of my life was recorded in your book. Every moment was laid out before a single day had passed.’ (Psalm 139:16 NLT) Stop trying to control everything. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezra 6-8, Mark 1:35-45, Ps 78:17-31, Prov 19:27-29 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67173&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-29 15:12:26]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-29 15:12:26]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[stop, stressing, out, over, the, uncontrollable, and, inevitable, take, deep]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...He shall direct your paths]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1006]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2336]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Stop Trying To Control Everything (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[stop-trying-to-control-everything-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...My strength is made perfect in weakness...' 2 Corinthians 12:9 NKJV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150731.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you find that you are overly controlling, try doing these three things: (1) Rather than dreading your helplessness, embrace it as a place of strength. It positions you to experience God’s power. ‘My grace is sufficient for you, for My strength is made perfect in weakness.’ (2 Corinthians 12:9 NKJV) Let go, and let God! (2) Be quick to express your helplessness to God. King Jehoshaphat realised that his forces were no match for three invading armies. So he prayed: ‘Oh, our God …we have no power against this great multitude that is coming against us; nor do we know what to do, but our eyes are upon You.’ (2 Chronicles 20:12 NKJV) How does his story end? Miraculously! The invading armies destroyed each other and Jehoshaphat’s army didn’t have to fight at all. Your biggest miracles will happen when you feel the least able, and trust God to intervene. (3) Meditate on Scriptures that speak about the sovereignty of God and the futility of trying to control life. ‘People throw lots to make a decision, but the answer comes from the Lord.’ (Proverbs 16:33 NCV) ‘We may make a lot of plans, but the Lord will do what He has decided.’ (Proverbs 19:21 CEV) ‘He does as He pleases among… the angels of Heaven and among… the people of the earth. No one can stop Him or say to Him, “What do you mean by doing these things?”’ (Daniel 4:35 NLT) ‘…For He chose us in advance, and He makes everything work out according to His plan.’ (Ephesians 1:11 NLT) Relax and start trusting God—He knows what He’s doing and He has your best interests at heart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezra 9-10, Mark 2:1-12, Ps 78:32-39, Prov 20:1-3 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67175&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-30 15:09:39]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-30 15:09:39]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[stop, him, say, what, art, soulfood, ezra, zra, mark, ark]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...My strength is made perfec]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[999]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2337]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[When Jesus Comes on Board]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[when-jesus-comes-on-board]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['He got into one of the boats...belonging to Simon...' Luke 5:3 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150801.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;One day Jesus ‘…&lt;em&gt;saw at the water’s edge two boats, left there by the fishermen, who were washing their nets. He got into one of the boats…belonging to Simon, and asked him to put out a little from shore. Then He sat down and taught the people from the boat. When He had finished speaking, He said to Simon, “Put out into deep water, and let down the nets for a catch.” Simon answered, “Master, we’ve worked hard all night and haven’t caught anything. But because You say so, I will let down the nets.” When they had done so, they caught such a large number of fish that their nets began to break&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Luke 5:2–6 NIV) Are you sitting today where Peter sat? Your outlook is bleak, your nets are empty, you’ve tried everything you know and you’re ready to give up? It happens; you get to the place where you simply stop expecting anything good. You’ve experienced too many disappointments and you’re afraid to dream, reach, stretch or broaden your horizons. Jesus knows how hard you’ve tried and today He’s inviting you to try again—this time with Him. Even though you’re wrestling with depression and tormenting memories, unemployment, addiction, financial failure or sickness, the Lord of new beginnings wants to come on board. If you listen to Him, He will show you what to do. Now, what He says may not initially make sense to you. But if you’re willing to respond like Peter—‘&lt;em&gt;Because You say so, I will&lt;/em&gt;’—you’re on the threshold of a miracle. Today, listen and obey the words of Jesus and watch how your situation changes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Jn 1:1-3:10, Mark 2:13-22, Ps 78:40-55, Prov 20:4-6 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67617&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-31 15:07:00]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-31 15:07:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[when, jesus, comes, board, you, willing, respond, like, peter, because]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['He got into one of the boats.]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1113]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2338]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Don't Go by Your Feelings]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[dont-go-by-your-feelings]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...you will be able to discern what is best...' Philippians 1:10 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150802.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;God gave you feelings, and you should never be ashamed of them. They can alert you to danger and give you insight into various situations. God actually uses our feelings to draw us closer to Him and highlight areas in our lives that need to be submitted to His Holy Spirit. But feelings are subjective; you can’t always trust them. Jon Walker says: ‘When old feelings creep back in we feel fearful, ashamed, hopeless, not good enough, unlovable, victimised, helpless and resentful… An event can trigger these reactions…ending a relationship, stress, problems at work and at home, times of change or illness…and sometimes these feelings return for no reason.’ So you must test your feelings, otherwise you’ll end up allowing ‘…&lt;em&gt;your feelings [to] get out of control&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Colossians 3:5 NIV) It can be disastrous to act on what you see, hear and feel. Instead of reacting to feelings, you must learn to act on what God’s Word says. That’s the gold standard, and it never changes! For instance, even if you feel like you can walk on water, you can only do it if God has called you to step out of the boat. Paul says, ‘…&lt;em&gt;my prayer [is] that [you]…abound…in knowledge and…insight…that you may be able to discern what is best&lt;/em&gt;…’ (Philippians 1:9–10 NIV) Bottom line: don’t rely on your feelings, rely on the knowledge and truth of God’s Word. You may feel worthless, but God says, ‘…&lt;em&gt;You are precious to Me …I love you&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Isaiah 43:4 NLT) You may feel like a failure, but God says, ‘&lt;em&gt;There is…no condemnation for those…in Christ&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Romans 8:1 NIV) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezek 37:1-14, Matt 27:50-53, 1 Thess 4:13-18 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67618&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-01 15:11:29]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-01 15:11:29]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[don, rely, your, feelings, the, knowledge, and, truth, god, word]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...you will be able to discer]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1315]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2339]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[It All Belongs to God (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[it-all-belongs-to-god-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['These all wait for You, that You may give them their food in due season.' Psalm 104:27 NKJV &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150803.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We fear losing our job, our health insurance and our retirement benefits, so we amass possessions, thinking the more we have, the safer we are. Jesus told a parable of one such person: ‘...&lt;em&gt;“The land of a rich man produced plentifully, and he thought to himself, ‘What shall I do, for I have nowhere to store my crops?’ And he said, ‘I will do this: I will tear down my barns and build larger ones, and there I will store all my grain and my goods&lt;/em&gt;.' (Luke 12:16-18 ESV) Can’t you hear the presumption in those words? Just like us stockpiling pensions, possessions and property, he accumulated and stacked until his barns of belongings were overflowing. Then he said, “&lt;em&gt;...Soul, you have ample goods laid up for many years; relax, eat, drink, be merry.&lt;/em&gt;” (Luke 12:19 ESV) The Bible says, ‘&lt;em&gt;Command those who are rich…not to…trust in uncertain riches but in the living God&lt;/em&gt;…’ (1 Timothy 6:17 NKJV) Riches don’t bring security. The more you have, the more you have to lose! It’s ironic; the more you accumulate the more protective you become, and the greater your concern that it could all be swept away by events you can’t control. That’s not how God intended you to live. He wants you to save and He wants you to sow. And when you’ve done all that wisdom demands, to trust in nothing but Him. The Psalmist said, ‘…&lt;em&gt;Living things…small and great…all wait for You, that You may give them their food in due season&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Psalm 104:25–27 NKJV) And He does. God’s the great giver, absolutely generous and utterly dependable. The resounding message of Scripture is clear: God owns it all. God shares it all. So place your trust in Him—not in belongings. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Jn 3:11-5:21, Mark 2:23-3:6, Ps 78:56-64, Prov 20:7-10 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67619&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-02 15:09:24]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-02 15:09:24]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[for, you, hear, the, presumption, those, words, just, like, stockpiling]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['These all wait for You, that ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1063]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2340]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[It All Belongs to God (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[it-all-belongs-to-god-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['When I fed them, they were satisfied; when they were satisfied, they became proud; then they forgot Me.' Hosea 13:6 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150804.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paul writes: ‘&lt;em&gt;Command those who are rich in this present age not to be haughty, nor to trust in uncertain riches but in the living God, Who gives us richly all things to enjoy. Let them do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to give, willing to share&lt;/em&gt;.’ (1 Timothy 6:17–18 NKJV) Are you ‘rich in this present age’? Almost half the world—more than three billion people—lives on less than $4 a day. So if your income is more than that, you’re rich by comparison. But prosperity comes with a warning: don’t be arrogant. ‘&lt;em&gt;Pride goes before destruction, a haughty spirit before a fall&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Proverbs 16:18 NIV) The Scottish historian Thomas Carlyle wrote, ‘Adversity is sometimes hard upon a man. But for one man who can stand prosperity, there are a hundred that will stand adversity.’ God wants you to enjoy things without becoming obsessed with them. Accumulating possessions has a way of eclipsing God, no matter how meagre they may be. There’s a predictable progression from poverty to pride. The poor man prays and works; God hears and blesses. The humble man becomes rich and forgets God. The faithful poor man becomes the proud rich man. As God said through Hosea, ‘&lt;em&gt;When I fed them, they were satisfied; when they were satisfied, they became proud; then they forgot Me.&lt;/em&gt;’ How can you avoid this trap? Remember that everything you own comes from God, and He’s the source of everything you’ll need in the future. So live with a grateful heart, and in total dependence on Him. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 1-2, Mark 3:7-19, Ps 78:65-72, Prov 20:11-14 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67620&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-03 15:05:00]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-03 15:05:00]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[command, mmand, those, who, are, rich, this, present, age, not]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['When I fed them, they were sa]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[874]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2341]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[It All Belongs to God (3)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[it-all-belongs-to-god-3]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['&quot;The silver is Mine and the gold&quot;...declares the Lord...' Haggai 2:8 NIV &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150805.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;How would you describe someone who built a house without giving any forethought to the foundation? Foolish! Likewise, God says, don’t put your trust in ‘&lt;em&gt;uncertain riches&lt;/em&gt;’ (1 Timothy 6:17 NKJV). Between 1948 and 2001 the U.S. economy endured ten recessions, each averaging one year, and resulting in the loss of billions of dollars. That means every five years or so, the economy dumps its suitors and starts all over again. What word would you use to describe a husband who philandered his way through nine different wives over fifty years? Fickle? And how would you describe wife number ten? Foolish? Abraham was one of the richest men of his generation, and so was Job. The New Testament church had some rich people in it. The Bible says, ‘…&lt;em&gt;all who were possessors of lands or houses sold them …brought the proceeds…and laid them at the apostles’ feet&lt;/em&gt;…’ (Acts 4:34–35 NKJV) God wants you to be blessed financially so you can bless His work. But the reason He doesn’t give some of us more money is because He knows we don’t have the maturity to handle it. It would be our undoing. And to those He does entrust with money, He says, ‘&lt;em&gt;Let them do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to give, willing to share.&lt;/em&gt;’ (1 Timothy 6:18 NKJV) You don’t really own anything; you’re just a steward. ‘&lt;em&gt;“The silver is Mine and the gold is Mine,” declares the Lord.&lt;/em&gt;’ The truth is, you’ll never be financially secure until you’re willing to say, ‘Yes!’ to God in whatever He asks you to do, knowing that He will always take care of you. Always! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 3:1-4:23, Mark 3:20-35, Ps 119:1-8, Prov 20:15-18 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67621&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-04 15:11:25]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[135]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-08-05 02:55:27]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-04 15:11:25]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[hout, giving, any, forethought, the, foundation, foolish, likewise, god, says]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['The silver is Mine and the g]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[664]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2342]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[It All Belongs to God (4)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[it-all-belongs-to-god-4]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['To the Lord your God belong the heavens...the earth and everything in it.' Deuteronomy 10:14 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150806.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to our money, we like to think, ‘I earned it, so it’s mine.’ But that’s where you’re dead wrong! The Bible says: ‘&lt;em&gt;To the Lord your God belong the heavens…the earth and everything in it.&lt;/em&gt;’ (Deuteronomy 10:14 NIV) ‘&lt;em&gt;Yours, O Lord, is the greatness…the power… the glory…the majesty and the splendour, for everything in Heaven and earth is Yours&lt;/em&gt;.’ (1 Chronicles 29:11 NIV) ‘&lt;em&gt;“The silver…and the gold is Mine,” declares the Lord Almighty.&lt;/em&gt;’ (Haggai 2:8 NIV) Riches are like Monopoly money; if you’re better than your competition, you end up with the deeds to the most expensive properties. But guess what? At the end of the day when the game is over, the participants leave the table and all the stuff goes back in the box. And if you were overly aggressive, the other players may end up not liking you. Here’s a humbling Scripture: ‘&lt;em&gt;Do not be overawed when others grow rich... for they will take nothing with them when they die... Though while they live they count themselves blessed—they will join those... who will never again see the light of life. People who have wealth but lack understanding are like the beasts that perish&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Psalm 49:16–20 NIV) The God who owns it all gives it to us for two reasons: (1) To enjoy. (2) To invest into fulfilling His purposes on earth. When we live with that attitude, we replace fear with faith in God.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 4:24-5:26, Mark 4:1-12, Ps 119:9-16, Prov 20:19-21 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67623&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-05 15:05:57]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-05 15:05:57]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[deuteronomy, omy, nivhttp, www, thewordfortoday, com, media, twftaudio, when, the]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['To the Lord your God belong t]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[587]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2343]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Ask God]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[ask-god]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...in Him we live, and move, and have our being.' Acts 17:28 NKJV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150807.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;George Washington Carver, an agricultural chemist who discovered three hundred uses for peanuts, shared these observations about God: ‘As a very small boy exploring the almost virgin woods of the old Carver place, I had the impression someone had just been there ahead of me. Things were so orderly, so clean, so harmoniously beautiful. A few years later in these same woods…I was practically overwhelmed with the sense of some great pres-ence. Not only had someone been there, someone was there…Years later when I read in the Scriptures, “…&lt;em&gt;in Him we live, and move, and have our being&lt;/em&gt;,” I knew what the writer meant. Never since have I been without this consciousness of the Creator speaking to me… the out–doors has been to me more and more a great cathedral in which God could be continuously spoken to and heard from… Man, who needed a purpose, a mission to keep him alive, had one. He could be…God’s co–worker… My purpose alone must be God’s purpose—to increase the welfare and happiness of His people… Why, then, should we, who believe in Christ, be so surprised at what God can do with a willing man in a laboratory?’ In 1921 Carver spoke before the United States House of Representatives. The chairman asked, ‘Dr. Carver, how did you learn all these things?’ He answered, ‘From an old book.’ The chairman asked, ‘What book?’ Carver replied, ‘The Bible.’ The chairman enquired, ‘Does the Bible talk about peanuts?’ Carver replied, ‘No sir, but it tells about the God who made the peanut. I asked Him to show me what to do with the peanut, and He did.’ Do you need a creative idea or solution today? Ask God! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 6:1-7:19, Mark 4:13-25, Ps 119:17-24, Prov 20:22-24 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67624&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-06 15:06:58]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-06 15:06:58]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[ask, carver, ver, how, did, you, learn, all, these, things]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...in Him we live, and move, ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[874]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2344]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[How to Overcome Perfectionism]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[how-to-overcome-perfectionism]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...think about the things that are good...' Philippians 4:8 NCV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150808.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be honest: Have you ever met a perfectionist who was truly happy? No, because when things must always ‘be a certain way’, life becomes miserable because it’s constantly changing. As soon as you solve one problem, another comes along. Instead of dwelling on their blessings and being grateful, perfectionists focus on what’s wrong and why they need to fix it. It may be a job they did that was less than perfect, a few kilos they need to lose, or even a disorganised wardrobe. Or it could be someone else’s imperfections: the way they live their life, how they behave, or the way they look. Constantly dwelling on flaws—your own or someone else’s—makes it impossible to be grateful. And gratitude is at the core of happiness. Now, let’s be clear; we’re not talking about striving to do better. That’s a good thing. We’re talking about obsessing over what’s wrong. There’ll always be a better way to do something, but that doesn’t mean you can’t enjoy life the way it is right now. So what’s the cure? Catch yourself before you fall into the trap of insisting that things should be different from how they are. Stop and remind yourself that, in the absence of your judgment, everything will work out just fine. Paul says, ‘…&lt;em&gt;in all things God works for the good of those who love Him&lt;/em&gt;…’ (Romans 8:28 NIV) Are you getting it? God’s in control; it’s ok for you to let go. Instead of focusing on the negative, ‘&lt;em&gt;think about the things that are good and worthy of praise&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Philippians 4:8 NCV) When you do, you’ll begin to discover how wonderful life is. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 7:20-9:44, Mark 4:26-41, Ps 119:25-32, Prov 20:25-27 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67625&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-07 15:11:29]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-07 15:11:29]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[how, they, behave, the, way, look, constantly, dwelling, flaws, your]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...think about the things tha]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[705]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2345]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[The Power of Vision (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[the-power-of-vision-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...men shall dream dreams [and]...see visions.' Joel 2:28 NKJV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150809.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A boy supposedly once asked Michelangelo why he was working so hard chipping away on the block of marble that would become his greatest masterpiece: David. The artist replied, ‘There’s an angel inside this rock and I’m setting him free.’ The power of vision enables you to see a potential masterpiece in what others overlook or consider worthless. It also helps you discover things within yourself you never knew were there. It brings out the best in you. Many of the people God used in Scripture looked like losers before they looked like winners. After the disciples fished all night and caught nothing, Jesus told them, ‘…&lt;em&gt;Do not be afraid. From now on you will catch men&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Luke 5:10 NKJV) They did, and they ended up: (1) building a church that’s still thriving two thousand years later; (2) writing history’s greatest books; (3) having our sons named after them. Does that mean you can just dream a dream and God will fulfil it? No. Paul says, ‘…&lt;em&gt;You are not your own; you were bought at a price. Therefore honour God&lt;/em&gt;…’ (1 Corinthians 6:19–20 NIV) Belonging to Christ means you lost the right to take your talents, opportunities and experiences and run off in any direction you please. But why would you even want to? What could possibly be more fulfilling than God’s purpose for your life? And what could be more tragic than missing it? You can’t wring enough meaning out of secular accomplishments to satisfy your soul. The hole you’re trying to fill has an eternal dimension only Christ can fill. That’s why you must pray, ‘Lord, show me Your vision for my life.’ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Eccl 11:7-12:1, Ps 39:4-13, 2 Tim 4:6-8&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67626&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-08 15:05:35]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-08 15:05:35]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[the, wordfortoday, com, media, twftaudio, boy, supposedly, once, asked, michelangelo]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...men shall dream dreams [an]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[747]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2346]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[The Power of Vision (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[the-power-of-vision-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...acknowledge Him, and He shall direct your paths.' Proverbs 3:6 NKJV &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150810.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having God’s vision for your life gives you four things: (1) &lt;em&gt;Passion&lt;/em&gt;. It makes you wake up in the morning and bound out of bed because there’s something out there you love to do; something you believe in and are good at; something bigger than you; something you can hardly wait to get at. (2) &lt;em&gt;Motivation&lt;/em&gt;. Author Richard B. Edler said: ‘Safe living generally makes for regrets later on. We are all given talents and dreams. Sometimes the two don’t match. But more often than not we compromise both before ever finding out. Later on, we find ourselves looking back longingly to that time when we should’ve chased our true dreams and talents for all they’re worth. Don’t be pressured into thinking your dreams or talents aren’t prudent. They were never meant to be… They were meant to bring joy and fulfilment to your life.’ (3) &lt;em&gt;Direction&lt;/em&gt;. Vision simplifies decision–making. Anything that moves you closer to your vision gets a green light; everything else should be approached with caution. Vision brings what’s important to the surface, and weeds out anything that stands in your way. Without vision, good things will keep you from achieving great things. People without a clear vision are easily distracted. They’ve a tendency to drift aimlessly from one thing to another. They’ve no spiritual, relational, financial or moral compass. Consequently, they make decisions that rob them of their dreams. (4) &lt;em&gt;Purpose&lt;/em&gt;. Having vision is like getting a sneak preview of things to come. It says, ‘If you don’t show up, something important won’t happen. Your life matters. Without you, what could be—won’t be.’ &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 10:1-12:22, Mark 5:1-10, Ps 119:33-40, Prov 20:28-30 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67627&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-09 15:17:44]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-09 15:17:44]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[the, wordfortoday, com, media, twftaudio, having, god, vision, for, your]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...acknowledge Him, and He sh]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[333]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2347]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[The Power of Vision (3)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[the-power-of-vision-3]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['I will instruct you...in the way you should go.' Psalm 32:8 NKJV &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150811.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mother Teresa didn’t set out searching for fame; it found her. She simply went to India, found a need no one else was meeting, heard the call of God, allowed her heart to be consumed by it, and ministered to multitudes of the world’s most neglected and forgotten people in the slums of Calcutta. One of her most famous slogans was, ‘A life not lived for others is not a life at all.’ Let’s face it; much of what we do each day doesn’t seem to matter until it’s evaluated as part of a larger picture. When you take the minutiae of any given day, drop it into the cauldron of a God–ordained vision and stir it around, suddenly there’s purpose, worth, adrenaline and the joy that comes from knowing you’re fulfilling your destiny. It’s like the difference between filling bags with dirt and building a levee to save a town. There’s nothing glamorous about filling sandbags, but saving a town from the ravages of a flood is another matter entirely. Building a levee gives meaning to the drudgery of shovelling dirt into sandbags. And it’s like that with your vision. Many times the everyday routine of life can feel like shovelling dirt. But take those same routines and view them through the lens of a God–given purpose, and suddenly everything looks very different. Vision brings your world into focus. It brings order and purpose out of chaos. It enables you to see everything in a fresh light. And the good news is that God is the giver of visions—so ask Him for one! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 12:23-15:29, Mark 5:11-20, Ps 119:41-48, Prov 21:1-3 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright  2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67628&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-10 15:32:24]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-10 15:32:24]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[the, way, you, should, psalm, alm, nkjv, http, www, thewordfortoday]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['I will instruct you...in the ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[82]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2329]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Are You Afraid of Losing Someone?]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[are-you-afraid-of-losing-someone]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...You will be missed, because your seat will be empty.' 1 Samuel 20:18 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150724.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who’s the one person whose death you dread most? Is it causing you anxiety? If so, begin to put these things into practice: (1) Ask God for the grace to accept death as an inevitable part of life. Both you and your loved one will eventually die, and no one but God knows who’s going to do so first. Therefore, worrying about something outside your control only robs you of your peace and joy. (2) Maximise each moment. If you knew the exact date of your loved one’s departure, what would you wish you’d done? Or not done? Would you take that trip you’ve always talked about? Would you be less critical and more complimentary? Would you spend more time with them, and tell them more often that you love them? (3) Don’t give another moment of your time to silly arguments and little irritations. (4) Make every effort to be sure your loved one is in right standing with God. Then you can be assured they’re at peace, and that you’ll spend eternity together. (5) Remember, your loved one is God’s loved one, too. And He loves them even more than you do. When the time comes, God will be right there with you. ‘Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil: for You are with me…’ (Psalm 23:4 NKJV) (6) Try to picture your loved one in Heaven. Jesus said, ‘…I go to prepare a place for you…that where I am, there you may be also.’ (John 14:2–3 NKJV) The parting will only be momentary, but the reunion will be forever. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Tim 1-3, Matt 28:1-10, Ps 42:1-5, Prov 19:12-14&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright © 2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=67167&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-23 15:09:13]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-23 15:09:13]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[1]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[are, with, psalm, alm, nkjv, try, picture, your, loved, one]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...You will be missed, becaus]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[925]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2260]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[How to Activate God's Word (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[how-to-activate-gods-word-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Let Christ's word...live in you.' Colossians 3:16 GWT &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150520.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Making the right decisions and choosing the right actions are the crux of living successfully. If you are the source of your own wisdom, or you're looking to others, your odds are not good. Paul writes, 'Let Christ's word with all its wisdom and richness live in you.' If you do, you'll have the winning strategy for your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you must: (1) &lt;em&gt;Read it&lt;/em&gt;. You don't have to understand it all; it's not an intellectual exercise. Reading it prayerfully brings power and wisdom because '...&lt;em&gt;the Word that God speaks is alive and active... [penetrating] to the place where soul and spirit meet&lt;/em&gt;.' (Hebrews 4:12 PHPS) (2) &lt;em&gt;Meditate on it&lt;/em&gt;. That means 'chew on' it. Let your spiritual digestive juices process God's Word until its nutrients become part of you: strengthening, energising and directing you. (3) &lt;em&gt;Believe it&lt;/em&gt;. '&lt;em&gt;My Word...always produces... It will accomplish all I want it to&lt;/em&gt;.' (Isaiah 55:11 NLT) There's only one thing that can short-circuit God's Word - unbelief. '&lt;em&gt;The message...did them no good, because they only heard and did not believe as well&lt;/em&gt;.' (Hebrews 4:2 PHPS). 'Hearing' opens the door; 'believing' walks through it and activates the promise. (4) &lt;em&gt;Receive it&lt;/em&gt;. No matter how strongly you believe in God's promises and His intention to give them to you, they're not yours until you receive them by faith. '&lt;em&gt;Therefore I tell you, whatever you ask for in prayer, believe that you have received it, and it will be yours&lt;/em&gt;.' (Mark 11:24 NIV) So believe your answer is on the way, and keep your faith strong until it arrives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Judg 4-6, Matt 12:1-14, Ps 93, Prov 13:7-8&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright © 2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=66565&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-05-19 15:08:11]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-05-19 15:08:11]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[2]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[how, strongly, you, believe, god, promises, and, his, intention, give]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Let Christ's word...live in y]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1675]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2211]]></id>
<title><![CDATA['Granny Brand' (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[granny-brand-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...We can certainly do it.' Numbers 13:30 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150408.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s the rest of Evelyn Brand’s story. At age seventy she received word from her home mission office that they weren’t going to give her another five–year term. But she had Caleb’s ‘we can certainly do it’ attitude. A party was held to celebrate her time in India, and everyone there cheered her on. ‘Have a good trip back home,’ they all said. ‘I’ll tell you a little secret,’ she announced, ‘I’m not going back home. I’m staying in India.’ Evelyn had a little shack built with some resources that she had smuggled in. Then she bought a pony to get around the mountains, and this septuagenarian would ride from village to village on horseback to tell people about Jesus. She did that for five years on her own. One day, at 75 years old, she fell and broke her hip. Her son, Paul Brand, the eminent doctor, said to her, ‘Mum, you’ve had a great run. God’s used you. It’s time to give it up now. You can go back home.’ She replied, ‘I am not going back home.’ She spent another eighteen years travelling from one village to another on horseback. Falls, concussions, sicknesses and ageing could not stop her. Finally, when she hit 93 years old, she could not ride a horse any more. So the men in these villages—because they loved Granny Brand so much—put her on a stretcher and carried her from one village to another. She lived two more years and gave those years as a gift, carried on a stretcher, to help the poorest of the poor. She died, but she never retired. She just graduated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Jer 36:27-40:16, Luke 24:25-35, Ps 25:8-15, Prov 10:1-3&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright © 2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=65459&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-04-07 15:05:13]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-04-07 15:05:13]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[granny, brand, devotional, tional, ren, going, give, her, another, five]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...We can certainly do it.' N]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1403]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2212]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Someone Is Always Watching You]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[someone-is-always-watching-you]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Let your light so shine before men...' Matthew 5:16 NKJV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150409.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A reporter once said to Joe DiMaggio, the famous baseball player, ‘You always seem to play with the same intensity. You run out every grounder and race after every fly ball, even when the Yankees have a big lead in the pennant race and there’s nothing on the line. How come?’ DiMaggio replied, ‘I always remind myself that there might be someone in the stands who never saw me play before.’ That’s the kind of unselfish mindset you must maintain in order to influence others for good and for God. It takes energy and intentionality, whether one–on–one or in a group, but it pays dividends. Nicodemus, a Jewish leader, was drawn to Christ because he’d listened to His teachings and observed His works from afar. He may have come to Jesus at night to avoid ridicule, but the fact is, he came because he couldn’t stay away! (John 3:1–21). The Bible says you’re a ‘…&lt;em&gt;letter…known and read by everybody&lt;/em&gt;.’ (2 Corinthians 3:2 NIV) Today someone is watching how you handle problems; how you treat your family and your employees; how you act when the boss isn’t around; how you respond to criticism or temptation. Don’t disappoint them. Jesus said: ‘&lt;em&gt;You are the light of the world. A city that is set on a hill cannot be hidden. Nor do they light a lamp and put it under a basket, but on a lampstand, and it gives light to all who are in the house. Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works and glorify your Father in Heaven&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Matthew 5:14–16 NKJV)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Jer 41-44, Luke 24:36-44, Ps 25:16-22, Prov 10:4-7&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright © 2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=65460&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-04-08 15:13:09]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-04-08 15:13:09]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[4]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[someone, the, stands, who, never, saw, play, before, that, set]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Let your light so shine befor]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1309]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2213]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Are You Flourishing? (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[are-you-flourishing-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...It is [God] who has made us, and not we ourselves...' Psalm 100:3 NAS &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150410.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do you need motivation today? Take a look at the palm tree. (1) &lt;em&gt;You can cut it, but you can’t kill it!&lt;/em&gt; The minerals and nutrients most trees need to survive are found on the surface, just below the bark, so, when you cut them, they die. But not the palm tree. Its life comes from within, so it flourishes, even under attack. Listen: ‘...&lt;em&gt;we have this treasure in earthen vessels&lt;/em&gt;...’ (2 Corinthians 4:7 NAS) How wonderful; even though the earthen vessel without may be cut and wounded, the treasure within is secure, beyond the enemy’s reach! (2) &lt;em&gt;It will bend, but it won’t break.&lt;/em&gt; Tropical winds can blow most trees away, but not the palm tree. The stronger the wind, the further it bends—sometimes all the way to the ground. Yet when the storm ceases, it straightens up again and is actually stronger in the place where it bent. What a picture! We were made to bend, but not break, because God strengthens us ‘...&lt;em&gt;with His glorious power so [we] will have all the patience and endurance [we] need&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Colossians 1:11 NLT) (3) Its depth always exceeds its height! While the roots of the average plant go only a few feet under the ground, the palm tree’s roots can go down hundreds of metres in search of water. David said, ‘&lt;em&gt;As the deer pants for streams of water, so my soul pants for you..&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Psalm 42:1 NIV) Go deep, work on your own connection to God and you’ll never be uprooted or barren or blown away!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Jer 45-48, Luke 24:45-53, Ps 50:1-15, Prov 10:8-10 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright © 2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=65461&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-04-09 15:07:31]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[135]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-05-29 05:24:56]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-04-09 15:07:31]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[5]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[are, found, the, surface, just, below, bark, when, you, cut]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...It is [God] who has made u]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1811]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2215]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Are You Flourishing? (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[are-you-flourishing-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...They will flourish in the courts of our God.' Psalm 92:13 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150411.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inside you there’s a battle between your flourishing self—the person you were created to be—and your languishing self. ‘What’s that?’ you ask. Your languishing self feels uneasy and discontent. You’re drawn to bad habits like mindlessly watching TV, drinking too much, misusing sex, excessive spending—things designed to temporarily anaesthetise pain. Your thoughts automatically drift in the direction of fear and anger. Learning doesn’t feel worthwhile. You think about yourself most of the time. Whereas flourishing [thriving, blossoming, and prospering] takes place: (1) &lt;em&gt;In your spirit&lt;/em&gt;. You sense you’re beginning to receive ideas and energy from an outside source. And you are. You’re being empowered by God’s Spirit. We talk about being inspired, which literally means ‘God–breathed’. God breathes into you; you come alive and feel like you’ve a purpose for living. (2) &lt;em&gt;In your mind&lt;/em&gt;. Your thoughts are marked by joy and peace. You have a desire to love and to learn. You’re literally being transformed by ‘…&lt;em&gt;the renewing of your mind&lt;/em&gt;…’ (Romans 12:2 NIV) (3) &lt;em&gt;In your time&lt;/em&gt;. You wake each day with a sense of excitement, and you realise you’re never too young to flourish. Mozart was composing brilliant music when he was five. Paul told Timothy, ‘&lt;em&gt;Don’t let anyone look down on you because you are young&lt;/em&gt;…’ (1 Timothy 4:12 NIV) You also realise you’re never too old to flourish. Grandma Moses was 69 when she took up painting, and artist Marc Chagall did some of his best work in his nineties. It’s humbling to acknowledge you can’t be anything you want. But once you accept that and seek to maximise what God created you to be, you start flourishing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Jer 49-50, Matt 1:1-6, Ps 50:16-23, Prov 10:11-13&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Word for Today&lt;/em&gt; is authored by Bob and Debby Gass and published under licence from UCB International Copyright © 2015&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=3&amp;track=65462&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[devotional]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-04-10 15:07:27]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-04-10 15:07:27]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[6]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[are, you, come, alive, and, feel, like, purpose, for, living]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...They will flourish in the ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[1191]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><section mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[10]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[The Word for Today]]></title>
<name><![CDATA[]]></name>
<alias><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></alias>
<image><![CDATA[]]></image>
<scope><![CDATA[content]]></scope>
<image_position><![CDATA[left]]></image_position>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
<published><![CDATA[1]]></published>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<ordering><![CDATA[10]]></ordering>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<params><![CDATA[]]></params>
</section><category mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[34]]></id>
<parent_id><![CDATA[0]]></parent_id>
<title><![CDATA[Devotional]]></title>
<name><![CDATA[]]></name>
<alias><![CDATA[devotional]]></alias>
<image><![CDATA[]]></image>
<image_position><![CDATA[left]]></image_position>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
<published><![CDATA[1]]></published>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<ordering><![CDATA[1]]></ordering>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<params><![CDATA[]]></params>
<sectionid><![CDATA[the-word-for-today]]></sectionid>
</category><user mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[77]]></id>
<name><![CDATA[Bob Gass]]></name>
<username><![CDATA[bob.gass]]></username>
<email><![CDATA[skip.parker@rbg.co.nz]]></email>
<password><![CDATA[c9fdc2928775a20cdf4c882e2660a530:8gj3gG1oaxo5gPlmcPnluVotFk04AZZN]]></password>
<usertype><![CDATA[Super Administrator]]></usertype>
<block><![CDATA[0]]></block>
<sendEmail><![CDATA[0]]></sendEmail>
<gid><![CDATA[25]]></gid>
<registerDate><![CDATA[2010-07-14 07:23:31]]></registerDate>
<lastvisitDate><![CDATA[2012-12-13 01:57:21]]></lastvisitDate>
<activation><![CDATA[]]></activation>
<params><![CDATA[admin_language=
language=
editor=
helpsite=
timezone=12

]]></params>
</user></j2xml>