<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE j2xml PUBLIC "-//eshiol.it//DTD J2XML data file 1.5.6//EN" "http://www.eshiol.it/j2xml/1506/j2xml.dtd">
<j2xml version="1.5.6">
<content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4320]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Clear-Cut Call: Responding To God]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[clear-cut-call-responding-to-god]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['When I heard these words I sat down and wept...' Nehemiah 1:4 NRS&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150812.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t feel like you’ve ever heard God’s clear–cut call for you? When you get an unshakeable sense of ‘I want to see change’ deep inside, you’re on to something. You might not feel like that about a particular issue right now but keep praying and you will. Let’s see what Nehemiah did when he heard God call him. The call to Nehemiah began with terrible news. God’s people were suffering and His holy city was destroyed. Nehemiah’s response was to sit down and weep. Bawl his eyes out. This is instinctive, natural and right. We talk a lot about being joyful in Church, but the Bible is also full of people weeping in response to the suffering they see. Their tears reflect God’s pain. When we see suffering, it *should* hurt us when we know it goes against the grain of God’s will for the world. And, before Nehemiah could even respond in sorrow, he had to hear the news. In the same way, we have to hear before we can respond. And to hear, we have to listen. We have to open our ears and hearts to news of places and people in need. We have to allow ourselves to be stirred, to feel discomfort. But, crucially, we’ve then got to follow it with action. Compassion is not just a feeling, it’s a response. Pick a situation around you or a story in the news you think needs to change, and take it to God and ask Him how and when you should get involved. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 16-18, Mark 5:21-30, Ps 119:49-56, Prov 21:4-6 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67728&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-11 15:19:01]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-11 15:19:01]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[clear, cut, call, for, you, when, heard, god, him, the]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['When I heard these words I sa]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[103]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4321]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Clear-Cut Call: Asking For Help]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[clear-cut-call-asking-for-help]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['If it pleases the King... I ask...' Nehemiah 2:5 NRS &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150813.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bring back to mind the situation or person you spent time thinking about yesterday. Time to work out how to respond. Nehemiah’s got this next step down. He asked for help, and not just from anyone. He went to the highest human authority available—the king. He felt no shame about appealing on behalf of his people to someone with some downright intimidating cred. Got a person or place on your heart? Don’t be ashamed to ask for help—or be too proud to ask those with power to help you. Some (in fact, most) tasks in God’s Kingdom will need more than a one–man band approach. Nehemiah knew he was doing the work of God, but he also knew that there were power structures in place that he had to work with to bring about Godly change. What’s more, the king he approached wasn’t a follower of God. The connections God will give you when you say ‘yes’ to His plan might not be ones you expect. Be open to His surprises. When God makes a way, He makes a way. So then, back to that situation or person you thought of yesterday. Who could you go to for help as you let God work in you? Is there someone in authority—a boss, a relative, a politician—you could ask? What support could they offer you? Are you brave enough to get on it? Share your concern for this place or person with at least one authority figure this week, and ask them for advice and support. You might be surprised by what they can do, and what support they offer you. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 19:1-23:20, Mark 5:31-43, Ps 119:57-64, Prov 21:7-9 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67729&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-12 15:07:01]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-12 15:07:01]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[clear, cut, call, asking, for, today, com, media, twftaudio, bring]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['If it pleases the King... I a]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[97]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4322]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Clear-Cut Call: Get To Work]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[clear-cut-call-get-to-work]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...They replied, &quot;Let us start rebuilding.&quot; So they began this good work.' Nehemiah 2:18 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150814.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, we looked at sharing our call with others. After that, the best advice any of us will hear is simply: ‘make a start’. Taking the plunge is what stops your call from just being a dead–end. So why don’t we? We tell ourselves we don’t have the right things in place. Like: (1) ‘I’m not qualified’? Well, Kingdom work usually involves called (*not* qualified) people doing things they never dreamt of. (2) ‘People aren’t agreeing with me’? We’ll get into this tomorrow, but for now, know this: God’s people always get flak. David’s own brother took pot–shots at him before the Goliath fight, even calling him ‘evil’ (1 Samuel 17:28). (3) And what about ‘the timing isn’t right just yet’? Ecclesiastes 11:4 NIV says: ‘&lt;em&gt;Whoever watches the wind will not plant; whoever looks at the clouds will not reap&lt;/em&gt;.’ If you’re looking for a sign that the time is right, you might end up missing it. Whatever you need, don’t be afraid to ask. Nehemiah went for it—he shared his plan with some friends, got them to commit, and then they began. In fact, the whole of chapter 3 is just a list of the different people who helped Nehemiah in different ways. He was humble enough to ask for help, and bold enough to confidently share his plan, knowing that it was worthwhile. Can you support a Christian group who are facing seriously difficult opposition and spreading the Gospel anyway? Prayer is a significant need. Consider an organisation like opendoors.org.au &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 23:21-26:19, Mark 6:1-13, Ps 119:65-72, Prov 21:10-13 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67730&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-13 15:11:20]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-13 15:11:20]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[clear, cut, call, with, others, after, that, the, best, advice]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...They replied, Let us star]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[91]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4323]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Clear-Cut Call: Unfamiliar Paths]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[clear-cut-call-unfamiliar-paths]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Lord, let Your ear be attentive to the prayer of this Your servant...' Nehemiah 1:11 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150815.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whether you have a clear–cut plan for the future or not, it’s always best to bring whatever we have to God in prayer. Often we’ve got a–million–and–one possible ideas for the future: excitement, back–up plans, ‘when I’ve got enough money’ plans... If that’s the boat you’re in, God will help you to narrow down the options, if you reciprocate that attentive ear thing (check out today’s verse), and listen right back to Him. Or perhaps, like a lot of us, you’re the opposite. The ‘what are you doing next year?’ question is one that haunts a lot of us, mostly because we’re pretty bad at getting hold of ideas for the futures. Wherever we find ourselves, it’s likely we’ll all benefit from a reminder: ‘…&lt;em&gt;along unfamiliar paths I will guide them; I will turn the darkness into light be-fore them and make the rough places smooth. These are the things I will do; I will not forsake them&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Isaiah 42:16 NIV) Whether the ‘darkness’ is the sea of choices you feel you have to wade through, or a sense of blankness about the future, God will be there. We’ll be taking a last look at Nehemiah’s wall–building capers tomorrow, but for now, remember how much prayer he put in before he went along with God’s plan. Be encouraged: it’s not an overnight process. Just bring what you have before Him, and leave the ball in His court. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 26:20-29:30, Mark 6:14-29, Ps 119:73-80, Prov 21:14-16 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67731&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-14 15:05:42]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[4378]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-08-19 05:30:40]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-14 15:05:42]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[clear, cut, plan, for, the, future, not, always, best, bring]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Lord, let Your ear be attenti]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[78]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4324]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Clear-Cut Call: Swords and Trowels]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[clear-cut-call-swords-and-trowels]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...Those who carried materials did their work with one hand and held a weapon in the other.' Nehemiah 4:17 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150816.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, Nehemiah took on God’s mission to rebuild the walls of Jerusalem. Good on him. Couldn’t be much better and easier, right? Hmmm. Actually, he faced pretty tough opposition: heavy criticism and even threats to his life. The reality is, when we follow out a call God has for our lives (no matter how big or small), there may be opposition. You could find that you’ll be struggling to carry out that call. Opposition is exactly what Nehemiah’s workers were ready for; they were building with a sword in one hand and a trowel in the other. When you’ve got a deep sense of God’s approval and conviction for a call, it’s important to get yourself grounded in it. Keeping a journal of the times you’ve prayed, and the ways you’ve found God responds, is a good way of doing this (hey, if you haven’t got a journal, maybe it’s time to splash out on one?), as well as listing some helpful Bible verses. Then, when you find yourself facing opposition, maybe even from your own doubts, those words will become your Ephesians 6:17 style defence. Let’s take the whole ‘following God’s call’ thing seriously. We humans come alive when God gives us a mission. It’s so worth catching hold of God’s short and long term plans for our lives. Write a Bible verse about God’s protection down (let’s call it your sword–verse). Write one about how to build your life around Him on another piece of paper (your trowel–verse). Hold one in each hand, and pray for Him to direct you in His plan. Carry the verses with you today. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Jer 31:31-37, Heb 8:1-13 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67732&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-15 15:12:01]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[4378]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-08-19 05:30:39]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-15 15:12:01]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[clear, cut, call, god, has, for, our, lives, matter, how]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...Those who carried material]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[74]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4325]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Mixed Motives]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[mixed-motives]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Amaziah did what was pleasing in the Lord's sight, but not wholeheartedly.' 2 Chronicles 25:2 NLT&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150817.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Question: can we do things that God wants in a way which doesn’t put Him first? Yes, we can. This is exactly what 2 Chronicles tells us King Amaziah did. On the outside, he was doing all the right things, but his heart wasn’t in it. His heart was on his own agenda, his own desires. Hmmm. What’s that mean, then? First, a heart turned towards God, and towards serving others, is one that is wide open to God’s blessings. Our motives for doing things are, so often, mixed. The challenge for us, then, is this: ‘&lt;em&gt;Blessed are the pure in heart, for they will see God&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Matthew 5:8 NIV) In our service, if we strip back the bits that point to us rather than Him, we’re clearing up the airwaves to see Him more clearly and let His blessings in. It’s always good to consider where our heart is when we give. How often have we thought: ‘This will make me look good. I wonder how many people saw me do that?’ The beauty of it is that we don’t need to give so God will mark off a few more brownie points for us on a ticklist. ‘&lt;em&gt;God loves a cheerful giver&lt;/em&gt;.’ (2 Corinthians 9:7 NIV) He really does. The giving of our money, time and energy can be from gratitude to His love for us. That’s a win–win for everyone involved—we don’t need to impress anyone, and our lives become bigger. So, let’s make sure our motives for giving are right. Assess your giving, assess your motives, and pray them all through. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Chr 1-4, Mark 6:30-44, Ps 119:81-88, Prov 21:17-19 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67733&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-16 15:07:30]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[4378]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-08-19 05:30:38]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-16 15:07:30]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[mixed, the, this, blessed, essed, are, pure, heart, for, they]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Amaziah did what was pleasing]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[63]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4326]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Wise Up!]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[wise-up]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Wise people are rewarded...' Proverbs 14:24 GNT&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150818.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A (very) brief summary of Proverbs 14: wisdom is the best. Without it, you’re like someone who tears their house down (verse 1), will ‘believe anything’ (verse 15), and have no qualms about making rash decisions that don’t honour God (verse 16). Sounds like it might be useful, then. As well as the big–scale school/university/work decisions we make, we are faced with hundreds of different everyday courses of action to take ourselves. Whether it’s that link you shouldn’t click, that impulse buy you didn’t need, that drinking game your flatmates are playing, it’s wisdom that gives us an insight into what will help us to build our lives best. Essentially, being wise will help us to keep putting God (and others) first, creating a solid foundation in life. Is it something we’re left alone to teach ourselves, then? Do we have to make a few terrible decisions first before eventually narrowing down what we should really be up to? Thankfully, this doesn’t have to be the case. For Solomon, a pretty wise bloke, wisdom was about admitting that handling life’s situations is best done with God at the reigns (yes, that’s wordplay), not us (1 Kings 3:9). When we humble ourselves and admit that we don’t always know what’s best, God will strengthen our conscience to start knowing which way to go. Now get that journal (didn’t grab one the day before yesterday? Go grab one now... Good work.) Now, open it up and make two lists: one of what you want to learn and improve in yourself this month, and one of people or places you want to help practically and generously this month. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Chr 5-7, Mark 6:45-56, Ps 119:89-96, Prov 21:20-23&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67734&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-17 15:35:09]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[4378]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-08-19 05:30:37]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-17 15:35:09]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[wise, will, help, keep, putting, god, and, others, first, creating]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Wise people are rewarded...' ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[37]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4327]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[It's Dangerous to Go Alone (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[its-dangerous-to-go-alone-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Share in the troubles we have like a good soldier of Christ Jesus.' 2 Timothy 2:3 NCV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150819.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are certain tactics the enemy will try use to get under our skin. Perhaps you’re feeling pressure from friends and family, or your own heart and head fill you with doubts, anxieties and temptations. It’s a serious matter, but sticking close to God gives us real strength when it comes to resisting Satan. The next few days are committed to helping us triumph when the carrot of giving up is dangling in front of us. Sometimes the world’s moving goalposts when it comes to morality are a constant temptation. Jesus spent a lot of time teaching us not to be anxious about getting by, but to influence the world as ‘&lt;em&gt;salt&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;light&lt;/em&gt;’ (Matthew 5:13–14). As hard as it is, ‘&lt;em&gt;Religion that is pure and undefiled before God, the Father, is this: to visit orphans and widows in their affliction, and to keep oneself unstained from the world&lt;/em&gt;.’ (James 1:27 ESV) Corruption leads to distancing from God. Wince. Good news: none of us can survive on our own. In this letter to Timothy—a young Christian preparing to face the difficulties of leading a church and staying faithful to God’s call—Paul reminds him that, just as good soldiers will share the burdens and struggles of their mates, we should do the same. It is an encouragement to know that we can call on other Christians to step up and support us, to have our backs, and to feel our pain with us. It’s our duty too to do the same for others. So, encourage someone who needs it today. Share in their troubles, like a good soldier of Christ Jesus. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Chr 8-11, Mark 7:1-13, Ps 119:97-104, Prov 21:24-27 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67735&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-18 15:07:58]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[4378]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-08-19 05:30:36]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-18 15:07:58]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[doubts, anxieties, and, temptations, comes, resisting, satan, the, carrot, giving]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Share in the troubles we have]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[36]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4328]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[It's Dangerous to Go Alone (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[its-dangerous-to-go-alone-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['...Make no provision for the flesh...' Romans 13:14 NAS&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150820.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Paul’s letter to the Church in Rome, he brings up a hugely important factor in the battle against Satan. Something that can, but really shouldn’t, be an elephant in the room—letting ourselves indulge in things (often secretly) that don’t honour God. Each day, we’re faced with a choice to ‘&lt;em&gt;cast off the works of darkness&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Romans 13:12 ESV) We’ll be blunt here: if you’ve got a niggle that something might be a hindrance to you, it probably is. We can all think of things that we don’t want to (or don’t know how to) let go of. That website? That ego–boosting slice of gossip? Those thoughts? Behind the temptation to keep hold of those things and use them, there’s a much better life that God has called us to as a ‘&lt;em&gt;new creation&lt;/em&gt;’ (2 Corinthians 5:17 NIV) in Him. To back that up with some serious God–protection, it’s vital to build our relationship with God, regardless of how well or badly we feel we’re doing—He invites us to &lt;em&gt;‘pray in the Spirit at all times and on every occasion.&lt;/em&gt;’ (Ephesians 6:18 NLT) This makes it harder for just–this–one–time things to slip under the radar. God doesn’t need us to be perfect (which is good, since we aren’t), but cutting back the things that hinder you will change your life. Is it time for you to find an accountability partner? Choose someone who you can be honest with. Commit to regularly keep each other in check about the thing–(or things)–to–stop–doing that came to mind today. If you can, pray for each other too. Let’s get each others’ backs. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Chr 12-15, Mark 7:14-23, Ps 119:105-112, Prov 21:28-31 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67736&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-19 15:09:46]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-19 15:09:46]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[0]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[choice, cast, off, the, works, darkness, romans, esv, don, want]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...Make no provision for the ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[11]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4314]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Who Cares?]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[who-cares]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Blessed is he who considers the poor...' Psalm 41:1 NKJ&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three richest people on the planet have more collective wealth than the combined gross national product of the world’s 48 poorest countries. You’re probably not in that league when it comes to earnings, but that’s no excuse for not giving. General Booth, the founder of the Salvation Army, said: ‘How can you convince a man of the love of God if his feet are perishing with the cold?’ Meeting people at their point of need is something Jesus did. For Him, healing and helping people went hand–in–hand with telling them about God. Giving our money, time and energy is a great thing to be doing for God. First, it’s a huge pointer to Him because, when people see our generosity, then it directs them to praise God (2 Corinthians 9:13). Secondly, giving changes our lives, too. When we open up our hearts and piggybanks to God’s way of looking at life, including His perspective on giving, we see massive blessing. In fact (and thirdly), Isaiah tells us that, sometimes, the reason our prayers aren’t answered is because we’ve been selfish when we saw others in need. ‘&lt;em&gt;Remove the... yoke of injustice and let the oppressed go free. Share your food with the hungry and open your homes to the homeless poor. Give clothes to those who have nothing to wear… Then My favour will shine on you…and your wounds will be quickly healed. I will always be with you to save you; My presence will protect you on every side. When you pray, I will answer you.&lt;/em&gt;’ (Isaiah 58:6–9 GNT) What’s something practical you can do for a needy person today?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 4:24-5:26, Mark 4:1-12, Ps 119:9-16, Prov 20:19-21 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67722&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-05 15:05:59]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-11 03:23:05]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[4378]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[2015-08-19 05:30:52]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-05 15:05:59]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[1]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[who, considers, the, poor, psalm, nkjhttp, kjhttp, www, thewordfortoday, com]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Blessed is he who considers t]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[104]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4315]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Living. Like Christ.]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[living-like-christ]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Christ... left you an example, so that you would follow in His steps.' 1 Peter 2:21 GNT&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God designed us to be a window to Him (see Genesis 1:26 for details). When we take a deep look at God’s character and His actions, we get a good indicator of what people should see when we’re showcasing Him well. Mostly, however, they get a pretty murky view. Thankfully, we don’t have to clean ourselves all in our own strength! We can ask God to show us how to be a window. What we’re talking about here is a process called ‘sanctification’, where God turns you round in a more–and–more Christlike direction. Want to know the most amazing bit? That started behind the scenes before we ever knew Him. Wow. Then, it fires up all the more when we commit to join Him in His work. We begin to look more like Him—the way we were made to be. So… can you now say: ‘Thanks for the theology lesson &lt;em&gt;word4U&lt;/em&gt;, I’ll guess I’ll sit around and be sanctified all day now, no effort needed’? Hmmm… you guessed it: no. We’re asked to follow Jesus—an action. Colossians 1:15 says we’re made in the likeness of God, and Jesus is the only ready–made Likeness of the Father. In Him, we’re given a living blueprint for taking hold of our cleaned–up lives. That’s why we’re called to live like Jesus and why He’s our example. Think of one area of your life that needs to look more like that Godly–blueprint. Pray about it, and come back to it whenever it crosses your mind. God will work in you when you ask Him to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 6:1-7:19, Mark 4:13-25, Ps 119:17-24, Prov 20:22-24 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67723&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-06 15:07:01]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-11 03:22:44]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-06 15:07:01]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[2]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[living, blueprint, for, taking, hold, our, cleaned, lives, that, needs]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Christ... left you an example]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[0]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4316]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[God's at the Gate (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[gods-at-the-gate-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...now is the day of salvation.' 2 Corinthians 6:2 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next few days we’re going to be thinking about when God works, where God works, and how God works—and where we fit into all of those things. Today’s verse answers the question: ‘When is God working?’ with an emphatic, triumphant, urgent ‘Now! What are you waiting for?’ Now, it’s really good to ‘&lt;em&gt;wait on the Lord&lt;/em&gt;’, and take time to pause and ask God where He wants us to be. Excellent stuff. Do that. But it’s also good to be wary of putting things off—waiting for a sign from Heaven or waiting for the ‘perfect time’ to chat to someone about Jesus can be procrastination. God can work through us, whether there’s a ‘green light’ showing or not about that ‘perfect time’. (In fact, funny thing about ‘perfect times’ for things: they don’t tend to ever show up). Paul reminds the Corinthian church that salvation is happening now—that now is the time to accept it, to start living in it, and to share it. In the next couple of days we’ll be taking a look at the encounter of two disciples with a man ‘&lt;em&gt;who was lame from birth&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Acts 3:2 NIV) They shared the ‘salvation’ they’d found in God. Not only the eternal salvation available through belief in Jesus and His death and resurrection, but the right–now ‘salvation’ from a disability that had kept the man from experiencing ‘&lt;em&gt;life in all its fullness&lt;/em&gt;.’ (John 10:10 NCV) Been putting something (maybe especially a Jesus–related thing) off? Decide to do it, or at least start it, today. Ask God about it first, then give it a start, and see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 7:20-9:44, Mark 4:26-41, Ps 119:25-32, Prov 20:25-27 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67724&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-07 15:11:31]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-11 03:22:21]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-07 15:11:31]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[3]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[god, the, gate, word, day, now, salvation, corinthians, hians, nivhttp]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...now is the day of salvatio]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[130]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4317]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[God's at the Gate (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[gods-at-the-gate-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...A man who was lame from birth was being carried to the temple gate...to beg.' Acts 3:2 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Acts chapter 3 there’s some really good news—God’s work isn’t limited to a certain time or place. It tells the story of Peter and John’s encounter with a man who couldn’t walk, at a city gate. It all started out as a normal day for this bloke. It’s likely the disciples would have passed this man many times before. Perhaps he was simply part of the background of the streets where they walked. And yet—on this particular afternoon, something different happened. This opportunity for the work of God suddenly arrived, right in a gateway the disciples passed through almost every day. Lesson time: first, don’t draw a line as to where you think God can work (check out 1 Chronicles 29:11). Prayer meetings? Bible study? Those spiritual parts of life are great but, if you feel as though you’re limping through your day–in–day–out life, know that God’s healing hand stretches to the gate (or wherever you find yourself), too. Just like the man who was healed, when we call out, God will provide. Secondly, God’s provision will get you back on your feet, no matter how slowly. Like the man, we often look for short term help, but God wants to do more than just provide a crutch for the issues that hold us down. Be bold today. Cry out to Him. Ask for healing. And ask for the opportunity to bring healing into the lives of others, just as Peter and John did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Eccl 11:7-12:1, Ps 39:4-13, 2 Tim 4:6-8 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67725&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-08 15:05:37]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-11 03:22:01]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-08 15:05:37]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[4]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[god, the, gate, beg, acts, cts, nivhttp, vhttp, www, thewordfortoday]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...A man who was lame from bi]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[111]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4318]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[God's at the Gate (3)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[gods-at-the-gate-3]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Taking him by the right hand, he helped him up...' Acts 3:7 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Peter and John got the picture. God is working through you and me (His disciples). That’s the role they took on as they extended their hands to people on the street. Disclaimer: God’s way of working might not match ours. The two disciples were on their way to a pretty important prayer meeting: ‘…&lt;em&gt;Peter and John were going up to the temple at the time of prayer—at three in the afternoon&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Acts 3:1 NIV) That prayer meeting took a back seat, though, when God showed how He wanted to work that day. Wherever we’re heading, God will point us to those hurting, needy, aren’t–saying–much individuals who weren’t on today’s list of notifications. Peter dropped what he was doing and let God redirect him towards helping a man who couldn’t walk: ‘&lt;em&gt;Taking him by the right hand, he helped him up.&lt;/em&gt;’ (Acts 3:7 NIV) Those disciples were blessed, too, not just the man at the gate. The moment when their hands met—that’s the moment the Church, the body of Christ, became the arm of God at work. Jesus calls us to be His hands and feet in today’s world. And here’s a beautiful thing—He tells us that ‘&lt;em&gt;whatever you do for the least of these... you did for Me&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Matthew 25:40 NIV) It’s as if, to Peter and John, the man lying at the gate is Jesus. And Peter and John, ex-tending their hands to him, are being Jesus to the man. THAT is God at work, transforming both those in need, and the ones who seek to help. Ready for a prophetic action? Write ‘Jesus’ on your hand. Use that hand to help as many people up as you can today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 10:1-12:22, Mark 5:1-10, Ps 119:33-40, Prov 20:28-30 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67726&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-09 15:17:47]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-11 03:21:41]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-09 15:17:47]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[5]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[god, the, gate, hands, met, that, moment, church, body, christ]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Taking him by the right hand,]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[103]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4319]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[An Apple A Day]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[an-apple-a-day]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...I require...the first-fruits and the choicest of your contributions....' Ezekiel 20:40 AMP&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God gave the prophet Ezekiel a picture of what it will look like when God’s relationship with His people is fixed: He’ll call them to His holy mountain, gather His people to Him—and they will offer Him the best of what they have (‘first fruits’ of the harvest). At this time in Bible history, God’s people were the Jewish people. They took this picture to heart—their law required that they offer the first fruits of harvest to God, to worship Him and remind themselves that everything came from Him. As it rolled out, they weren’t always that great at putting Him first. All they needed to do was make Him their priority (not their own selfish ambition), and they could enjoy being close to Him, but they cut corners left and right. Most of us can think of situations where we’ve done the same, forgetting that ‘my gifts are not my gifts; they belong to God.’ God’s love doesn’t depend on how well we live this out. So, because His love is so freely given, let’s try to do this well. A good way to do this? Kick it off by giving back to God the first bit of His most basic gift—the day you get to be alive in. So set your alarm 10 minutes earlier to start tomorrow with a prayer of commitment. (Hate mornings? Do it anyway… you’ve got to get up sometime.) Start your morning with words like the Psalmist: ‘&lt;em&gt;You are my God. My times are in Your hands&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Psalm 31:14–15 AMP) That’s one way to focus the rest of your day on Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 12:23-15:29, Mark 5:11-20, Ps 119:41-48, Prov 21:1-3 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67727&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-10 15:32:26]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-11 03:21:23]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-10 15:32:26]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[6]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[the, choicest, your, contributions, ezekiel, zekiel, amphttp, www, thewordfortoday, com]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...I require...the first-frui]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[126]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4301]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Grace-Full]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[grace-full]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'He...saw...evidence of the grace of God.' Acts 11:23 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Grace’. You don’t often hear it used outside of church but, boy, do you hear it a lot there. What does it even mean? As a noun, the dictionary describes grace as ‘courteous good will’. Sounds quite Christian. But in the Bible, ‘grace’ is about more than just good manners. So, what does the Bible say? Peter wrote we should be growing in ‘grace and knowledge of our Lord and Saviour.’ (2 Peter 3:18 NIV) Grace is simply God giving us what we don’t deserve. Growing in grace refers to our transformation from what we used to be into what He is making us to because of His goodness that He has undeservingly lavished on us. When we say that a person is ‘full of grace’ we don’t mean full like a tankard of coffee (though, come to think of it, tankard of coffee… mmm). The grace given to us doesn’t just stay inside. We can make the choice to let it overflow into the world around us. Jesus has already given us more than enough in His forgiveness and acceptance of us (throwback to yesterday, anyone?) That fuels our everyday lives—it’s why 2 Peter encourages us to know more about it. The more we know of it, the more we change the way we see things and respond to the world around us—places and people where there could be more of God’s presence and work. To remind yourself of what it means to be full of grace: get a mug and a stick it under the tap. Fill the mug, and keep on filling until it’s pouring over the sides into the sink. Here’s a visual of ‘full of grace’—lavishly sharing out and out and out to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Tim 1-3, Matt 28:1-10, Ps 42:1-5, Prov 19:12-14 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67247&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-23 15:09:16]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:09:03]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-23 15:09:16]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[7]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[grace, god, acts, nivhttp, www, thewordfortoday, com, media, twftaudio, courteous]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['He...saw...evidence of the gr]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[141]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4302]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Excuses]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[excuses]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Don't excuse yourself by saying, &quot;Look, we didn't know.&quot;' Proverbs 24:12 NLT &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘I’m washing my hair,’ ‘I’m doing my homework,’ ‘I’m vacuuming my cat.’ All excuses we’ve used before to get out of a variety of things. (Maybe not the cat one; we tried it once and nobody believed us). But what about when we’re trying to get out of taking responsibility for something? Ouch. That stuff can sting quite badly. When we’ve hurt a friend, left someone out or made a really bad choice. It can be so hard to hold up our hands and say, ‘You know what? My bad.’ But sometimes, it’s the only way to move on. Proverbs 12:22 ESV says: ‘Lying lips are an abomination to the Lord, but those who act faithfully are His delight.’ God actually delights in seeing us do the right thing. That doesn’t mean that doing the right thing will be an easy ride, but it does mean that when we’ve messed up and we are willing to take responsibility we are bringing honour to God. On the flipside, when we use today’s verse as our script for sticky situations, no matter how many people believe you, God sees our motivation for excuses. When we’re willing to swallow our pride and own up, we are pointing our lives in a God–ward direction—everyone’s a winner. Ephesians 4:26 NIV says: ‘Do not let the sun go down while you are still angry.’ Use that as a challenge today; seek to put things right with your family and friends before you go to bed tonight. It might be tough, and it might be a long time before a relationship is repaired, but take the first step towards it today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Tim 4-6, Matt 28:11-20, Ps 42:6-11, Prov 19:15-17 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67248&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-24 15:08:11]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:08:51]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-24 15:08:11]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[8]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[excuses, used, before, get, out, variety, things, maybe, ybe, not]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Don't excuse yourself by sayi]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[184]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4303]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Almighty Wisdom]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[almighty-wisdom]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Though it cost you all you have, get understanding.' Proverbs 4:7 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahh, Proverbs. Many pearls of wisdom. But, here’s the thing—it’s only full of wisdom when you read it, use it and do something about it. God’s Word was never meant to be a bunch of letters on a page shoved in a bookcase somewhere. It was always intended to be truth, wisdom and promise. And that means that we need to bring those things into the world by living them out. Wisdom can seem like a theoretical thing, but it’s totally not. It’s a basis of real, solid understanding—an understanding that equips us to live out God’s plans and commands. You wouldn’t expect a vacuum cleaner to keep your house clean when it’s left in the cupboard under the stairs; it’s the same with your Bible (not sure why we’ve mentioned vacuums two days in a row, clearly some of us have a guilty conscience…and a very dusty floor). If you want to get the most out of your Bible and start living out your faith, you’ve got to get it out daily. In Proverbs 1:5 NIV it says: ‘Let the wise listen and add to their learning, and let the discerning get guidance.’ The original word used here for learning is ‘leqach’, which is connected with the idea of taking something. Basically, what Proverbs is getting at is that we have to take wisdom from God. He’s the Almighty source of wisdom, He embodies wisdom itself, so anytime we’re struggling with something, He’s the One to go to. Remember memory verses? It’s old school, but it’s a good way of allowing Scripture to permeate your life and impact the way you see things. Learn a (useful for you) verse from Proverbs by heart this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Num 9:15-23, Exodus 24:15, Matt 17:1-8 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67249&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-25 15:05:10]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:08:37]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-25 15:05:10]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[9]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[almighty, wisdom, but, totally, not, left, the, cupboard, under, stairs]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Though it cost you all you ha]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[116]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4304]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Servant Heart]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[servant-heart]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Whoever wants to become great among you must be your servant.' Mark 10:43 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see so much of people serving in church (in welcome teams, in coffee rosters, handing out hymn books on the way in and so on) that we can sometimes lose touch with the word ‘servant’. We become desensitised to the whole idea and just end up assuming that it’s all about how often we stack the chairs. But being a servant in God’s eyes is less about the actual acts we do (though they are important), and more about the attitude we bring. You see, if we stack the chairs at church but get home and whinge about it, we’ve completely missed the point. Cue a great verse in Paul’s letter to the people of Philippi: ‘Do everything without complaining or arguing.’ (Philippians 2:14 GWT) Everything? Yep. Look at it this way, can you imagine Jesus saying ‘I really don’t feel like doing that today, God.’ He was willing to be a servant, willing to do as the Father asked Him, even if that meant a rough deal. It’s tough, but it’s who God calls us to be. Galatians 5:13 NIV says: ‘You, my brothers and sisters, were called to be free. But do not use your freedom to indulge the flesh; rather, serve one another humbly in love.’ God made you free so that you could serve. Use that freedom. Grab someone who looks like they might be need a hand, even the old man next door who can’t push his mower around, and ask what you can do to lend a hand. Even the smallest of odd–jobs is an opportunity to exercise your God–given freedom and be a servant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Zeph 1-3, Mark 1:1-8, Ps 46, Prov 19:18-20 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67250&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-26 15:05:01]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:08:23]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-26 15:05:01]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[10]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[servant, mark, ark, nivhttp, www, thewordfortoday, com, media, twftaudio, lcome]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Whoever wants to become great]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[131]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4305]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Bogus Slogans]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[bogus-slogans]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Be very careful, then, how you live.' Ephesians 5:15 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘You only live once.’ It’s easy to be cynical about this and other nice t–shirt slogans like: ‘Live for today’, ‘When life gives you lemons, make lemonade’, ‘carpe diem’ and all that other stuff. But, hold up, maybe there’s something in this whole ‘seize the day’ business that we shouldn’t so casually dismiss it. Ecclesiastes 9:9 NIV says: ‘Enjoy life with your wife.’ Now THAT we can see on a t–shirt (mainly because it rhymes). But it goes on to say: ‘For this is your lot in life and in your toilsome labour under the sun.’ Wow. Not so t–shirt friendly after all? There’s some meaty stuff behind the message. In Luke 9:62 NIV, a man says, ‘I will follow You, Lord, but first let me go back and say goodbye to my family.’ Jesus replies, ‘No one who puts his hand to the plough and looks back is fit for service in the Kingdom of God.’ There’s a ‘seize the day’ message if ever there was one. Maybe you’ve noticed: any Instagram–filtered–poster–pic type slogans that we can grab from the Bible tend to be paired with some real kickers. They’re not just nice platitudes or motivational quips. Yes, God is all for the ‘seize the day’ mentality, but look again at the reason. Because we can’t put God’s Kingdom off until later. We have to be prepared to step up today. To make today (and the direction of our lives) more about God than ourselves, to serve in whatever immediate way we can. Don’t put it off. Simple. Choose one little thing you can do today that will grow God’s Kingdom. Go for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezra 1-2, Mark 1:9-20, Ps 78:1-8, Prov 19:21-23 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67251&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-27 15:17:35]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:08:11]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-27 15:17:35]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[11]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[bogus, slogans, like, live, more, about, god, than, ourselves, serve]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Be very careful, then, how yo]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[140]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content>
<content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4306]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Super Power]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[super-power]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'He will empower you with inner strength.' Ephesians 3:16 NLT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever watched a superhero film and been convinced you must have superpowers you haven’t discovered yet? No? Oh c’mon, you know you have. As much as we can close our eyes and convince ourselves we can teleport from our desk to New York, sometimes we can feel pretty weak. In fact, the latter’s the more common, right? We’ve all had moments of sheer helplessness, where it’s almost impossible to get out of bed because we’re physi-cally/emotionally exhausted. As hard as it is, you can trust Him. If you’re willing to step out, His power goes with you. Isaiah 40:29 NIV says: ‘He gives strength to the weary and increases the power of the weak.’ That’s pretty incredible encouragement, right? We may not have teleportation powers (though don’t count the possibility out… check Acts 8:39–40, God did it once), but that verse from Isaiah tells us that, even in our weakest moments, we have power that God will build on. It means that we don’t have to live in exhaustion and weakness. God has the amazing power to take everything that wears us down, and free us from it. He’s ready and willing to help you, if you’ll bring it all before Him. That also goes for when you’re not allowing yourself to feel weak. When you’re convincing yourself that you can do it alone, you’re denying God the right to carry you and strengthen you. Allow Him in, He knows what He’s doing. And every time you see a picture of a superhero, remember the Super-Power (God) that goes before you and the strength that God provides.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezra 3-5, Mark 1:21-34, Ps 78:9-16, Prov 19:24-26&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67252&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-28 15:08:18]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:07:44]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-28 15:08:18]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[12]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[super, hero, film, and, been, convinced, you, must, have, superpowers]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['He will empower you with inne]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[125]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4307]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Give Up(wards)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[give-upwards]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Set your minds on things above, not on earthly things.' Colossians 3:2 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150730.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matthew 6:24 NIV says: ‘You cannot serve both God and money.’ Right. Not a problem. Buying a few new t–shirts, when we already have a full ward-robe, isn’t ‘serving money’, is it? Possibly not. There’s nothing wrong in buying stuff. But we would ask you this… Did you ask God what He wanted you to do with that cash before splashing it? Now, this is NOT a guilt trip. Promise. It’s a reality check. Some inspiration to move forwards with. And it’s inspiration that we all need. We’ve all got to get our priorities straight. Everything we’ve got is a gift from God anyway. Our very lives, and everything in them, are given by Him, so we have a definite duty to invite Him to shine through them. That means offering everything back to Him, as soon as it lands in our lap (or, even, once we’ve worked our snowflake–patterned Christmas–in–July socks off for it). Whether it’s the $100 birthday money from granny, or the $2 you just found on the floor, God loves it when you give it back to Him. He won’t necessarily tell you to give $102 to charity/church/the homeless guy in town. He may just ask you to give a portion to one of them. But, if you take all your money to Him, you accept the risk that He may tell you to give away what’s left over, after you’ve paid your bills. In fact, scratch that, you don’t just ‘accept’ that risk. You’ll learn to delight in the God–given hazard of generosity. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezra 6-8, Mark 1:35-45, Ps 78:17-31, Prov 19:27-29 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67253&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-29 15:12:28]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-29 15:12:28]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[13]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[give, him, have, definite, duty, invite, shine, through, them, that]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Set your minds on things abov]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[118]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4308]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[What've You Got?]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[whatve-you-got]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'What do you have in your house?' 2 Kings 4:2 NIV&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be brilliant when you get a direct answer to prayer through another person. But, have you ever considered the fact that you could actually be the answer to someone else’s prayers? Seriously, think about what you have to offer. God equips each one of us with gifts to bless other people. Find yourself on your knees in prayer fairly often? Great! Sometimes, when we get up and walk back into ‘the world’, we’re a walking answer to prayer (see Isaiah 52:7 for further details). Maybe you’re pretty good at just listening, or perhaps you’re great at cheering people up. In Luke 6:38 KJV Jesus said: ‘Give, and it shall be given unto you.’ Now, that doesn’t mean that you’ll always get a good deal. There will be people who let you down and take more than they give. But, God promises that when we commit to serving one another, He will honour us. John 12:26 NIV says: ‘My Father will honour the one who serves Me.’ And as long as we’re seeking God’s honour (rather than the self–gratification of being praised for being an amazing friend), we’re on the right track. Sit down with a Christian friend and chat about what you think they bring into people’s lives (even if it’s just that they can make you laugh till you cry… wait, that shouldn’t be ‘just’—that’s an awesome gift). Then ask them to tell you what you bring into people’s lives. You might be surprised by how much of a blessing you truly are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezra 9-10, Mark 2:1-12, Ps 78:32-39, Prov 20:1-3 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67254&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-30 15:09:42]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:07:28]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-30 15:09:42]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[14]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[what, you, have, offer, god, equips, each, one, with, gifts]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['What do you have in your hous]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[127]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4309]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Spiritual Diet]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[spiritual-diet]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'As newborn babes, desire the pure milk of the Word...' 1 Peter 2:2 NKJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many times have you crashed with a friend and, instead of eating dinner, you’ve gorged on chocolate and crisps? At the time it feels good, but after a few hours, you start to wonder if ‘fibre’ or ‘vitamins’ might be a good shout. The headaches start. The stomach lurches. You start to feel both too full and strangely empty at the same time. Peter’s getting at something similar in these verses. Our soul is crying out for nourishment. The temptation to go looking for that soul–nourishment in places other than God’s Word can be really strong. We don’t always notice ourselves doing it. Malice, deceit, hypocrisy, envy, evil speaking (1 Peter 2:1); they’re quick fixes, and can give the short–lived illusion that they’re just what we need to feel full. (In that moment when we give in to nastiness, we can feel satisfied in a guilty kind of way... until we spiritually sober up and catch what we’re doing.) But, they don’t provide us with the proper fruit and veg spiritual nourishment we really long for. God gives a full list of His culinary recommendations in Galatians 5:22–23. Yep, the fruit of the Spirit: love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, gentleness, faithfulness and self–control. Truth is, it’s not always easy to choose to eat healthily. But the nifty thing is: we can pray for the right kind of healthy hunger. So go for it! Ask: ‘Lord, give me a hunger for Your nourishment through Your Word in Scripture.’ Then decide: which fruit of the Spirit is going to be part of your diet today?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Jn 1:1-3:10, Mark 2:13-22, Ps 78:40-55, Prov 20:4-6 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67717&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-31 15:07:02]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:07:14]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-31 15:07:02]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[15]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[spiritual, sober, and, catch, what, doing, but, they, don, provide]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['As newborn babes, desire the ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[146]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4310]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Can't Touch This (Significance) (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[cant-touch-this-significance-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...You are Mine.' Isaiah 43:1 NKJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘For I am yours… and you are mine.’ Yeah, ok, it might seem like a bit of a greetings–card cliché. But what about when we sing it in worship? We might know in our heads that we belong to Jesus. But really knowing that we belong to Jesus, in our hearts, can be a different matter. What does it mean? What difference does it make to how our lives look? The real sense of value that comes from knowing you’re a child of God doesn’t come from all the nice things He gives you. In fact, any material ‘thing’ can disappear at any time. God’s declaration that you are His, that you are significant because of that, isn’t a promise that He’s going to give you a free pass when it comes to troubles. His is a more lasting significance and a promise to be with you in those troubles: ‘&lt;em&gt;I have called you by your name; you are Mine. When you pass through the waters, I will be with you; and through the rivers, they shall not overwhelm you. When you walk through fire, you shall not be burned…For I am the Lord your God…you are precious in My eyes&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Isaiah 43:1–4 ESV) You are precious. Not what you’ve got, or what you have done—you. When your sense of significance is an inside job, rather than based on external things, nothing can touch it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Ezek 37:1-14, Matt 27:50-53, 1 Thess 4:13-18 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67718&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-01 15:11:31]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:06:59]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-01 15:11:31]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[16]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[can, word, day, you, and, are, mine, yeah, might, seem]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...You are Mine.' Isaiah 43:1]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[138]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4311]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Can't Touch This (Significance) (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[cant-touch-this-significance-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Thank You for making me...' Psalm 139:14 NLT&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When you realise someone likes you as you are, it’s pretty great. Even when someone sheepishly says, ‘I maybe sorta kinda like you,’ it’s a massive confidence boost, right? It doesn’t even have to be romantic. It can be as straightforward as that person, the one you respect more than anyone, complimenting what you’ve done. It sticks with us when we know we’re appreciated. And that’s just when fellow humans value us! What about God? Yes, the God of creation, the same God who named the stars (Psalm 147:4) thinks more highly of you than He does the stars. Jesus says: ‘...&lt;em&gt;the very hairs on your head are all numbered&lt;/em&gt;.’ (Matthew 10:30 NKJ) Your adoring fans might know your eye colour, what flavour you like your latté, or your favourite film. But the amount of hair on your head? Nah. God knows every detail about you, and loved you even before you knew Him (Ephesians 1:4). What does all this mean? God appreciates you. A lot. He values you more than you can imagine. The things that make you ‘you’ are given huge weight because of that. It’s good to remember that the best compliment, or the most alluring romance, can’t touch the significance you’ve already been given. And it’s good to remember that ‘re–member’ literally means to put back together again. Like Humpty Dumpty. So when you recollect and remember that God has made you, you’re doing something really wonderful. Particularly if you’re feeling fractured or broken today, find somewhere to be quiet and remember, and let Him put you back together again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Jn 3:11-5:21, Mark 2:23-3:6, Ps 78:56-64, Prov 20:7-10 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67719&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-02 15:09:26]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:06:34]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-02 15:09:26]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[17]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[can, word, day, thank, you, realise, someone, likes, are, pretty]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Thank You for making me...' P]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[159]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4312]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Can't Touch This (Significance) (3)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[cant-touch-this-significance-3]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...The Lord raises those who are bowed down...' Psalm 146:8 NKJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That significance in God that we’ve been focusing on these last two days—yes, it can be shaken, especially when we do things that make us think we’re suddenly unclean again. But only in our heads. Even when we know we’ve messed up, God looks past what we’ve done and into our future. Open your Bible (app?) to John 4, where Jesus met the woman at the well. While the rest of the town slandered her because of her shady past, Jesus offered her a new life. God knows it’s sometimes hard to see beyond what we’ve done, so He meets us right where we are. At the well, or the workplace, or school or your worried mind, He’s there. He told the woman this: &lt;em&gt;‘Whoever drinks of this water will thirst again, but whoever drinks of the water that I shall give him will never thirst&lt;/em&gt;.’ (John 4:13–14) Your significance? You might feel like it has taken a knock, but your self–worth is fulfilled in Jesus—you don’t need to keep ‘thirsting’ after other people’s approval of you. In fact, God loves to show us that even in our lowest moments, He is there. Psalm 146:8 NKJ says: ‘&lt;em&gt;The Lord raises those who are bowed down&lt;/em&gt;.’ When you’re humble to accept that His way (and He Himself) is the best way forward, He’ll pick you up and show you your significance, wherever you’ve fallen down. So, whenever cruel words come at you, especially come from your own mind, remember what God really says about you. (Reread yesterday’s message, if your memory’s as bad as ours is...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 1-2, Mark 3:7-19, Ps 78:65-72, Prov 20:11-14 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67720&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-03 15:05:03]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:06:06]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-03 15:05:03]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[18]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[can, word, day, the, wordfortoday, com, media, twftaudio, that, been]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...The Lord raises those who ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[118]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4313]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Busted]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[busted]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...God will bring every work into judgment, including every secret thing, whether good or evil.' Ecclesiastes 12:14 NKJ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God’s omniscience (that’d be His all–knowingness) gets a lot of bad press from time to time. Ever heard someone advise: ‘Don’t do that. God’s watching’? As if He’s nothing more than a security guard with seven billion screens trying to catch us out every other second. But if we understand that God is love—which He is—we can really understand His all–knowingness. So often when we sin, we’re hesitant to go back to God. But the reality is that He knows everything already—He knows the worst and the best about us; He sees our innermost thoughts. We can bury our motivations and thinking so deeply, they’re hidden even from ourselves. But we can’t hide them from God. Ultimately that’s good news. We don’t have to live in fear of Him coming back to discover our mess and, in shocked horror, send us to bed without dinner. He already sees the mess, and He’s ready to deal with it lovingly. We just have to take it to Him. And while we need to go back to Him to sort out that sin, we can approach Him with confidence, knowing that Jesus has already done everything necessary to restore us to God in the first place. So—right now and in a properly Christ–like way—go clean up a mess that you didn’t make. And, if whoever did make it is around, show them real grace about it. No grumbling or fuss–making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 1 Chr 3:1-4:23, Mark 3:20-35, Ps 119:1-8, Prov 20:15-18 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67721&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-08-04 15:11:27]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:05:50]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-08-04 15:11:27]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[19]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[busted, word, day, god, will, bring, every, work, into, judgment]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...God will bring every work ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[101]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4285]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Created to Create]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[created-to-create]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['He...reveals His thoughts to man.' Amos 4:13 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150709.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;God is a creative God. He created something as delicately precise as atoms, neurons and quarks. He created something as grand and supersized as the IC1101 galaxy, which is estimated as 100 thousand light years across. God created Shakespeare and Picasso and your next door neighbour. The Piano Key butterfly gets a name from a stunning keyboard tattooed to its wings—again the work of Creator God. The shark, the wombat, jelly trifles, soap bubbles—they were all modelled at the hand of God. You get the idea: God is creative. Well, the Bible teaches we are made in the image of God—so if God is creative… yep, good guess, so are we. Ok, maybe you tend to colour outside the lines, sing like a strangled bullfrog or run like a demented crab—but in other unique ways you will reflect God’s creativity. Styling hair could be your thing. Or unravelling an equation. Or curling a free–kick. Or dissecting an aneurysm. Or turning over a sentence. Creativity doesn’t just happen in the art room. To some, God reveals beauty in mathematical sequences and scientific formulae; to others, He shows up in drama or paintings. However we’ve been wired; we’ve all received ‘creativity’. Not sure about that? You don’t have to class yourself as a ‘creative type’ to be able to bring ideas up that will bless people—we all have ways to reflect God’s creativity. When you tap into God’s creativity, He helps you see things not as they are, but as they can be. Today, do three creative things, in your own God–given way. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Eph 1:1-4:16, Matt 25:31-46, Ps 79, Prov 17:24-26 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67232&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-08 15:05:55]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-08 15:05:55]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[20]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[created, something, delicately, precise, atoms, neurons, and, quarks, estimated, thousand]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['He...reveals His thoughts to ]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[277]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4286]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Primed For Transformation]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[primed-for-transformation]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Be transformed by...renewing...your mind.' Romans 12:2 NKJ&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150710.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Romans 12 tells us to let the Holy Spirit transform us by ‘renewing...your mind.’ We can sometimes cringe at the notion of doing something that ‘isn’t me’. We tend to carve out a comfortable little possie for ourselves and that’s how the world comes to see us. And we buy into the world’s view! So when God comes along and tells the person who could never speak in class to preach to a large congregation, it’s hard to think anyone will take that seriously. Sometimes, though, we’re asked to challenge those expectations. God made us with purpose, value, dignity and worth, but along the way He’s still going to need to step in and grow us. As that emerges, of course we’re going to change. It’s practically a necessity if He’s fulfilling His purposes in us. When we don’t have the power or energy to change our own self–image, God does. In fact, whenever He calls us to do things we don’t see ourselves being capable of, He transforms us so that we can do whatever is needed. Like Op-timus Prime, we can be renewed and restored, and will come back kicking, with new Energon–like energy and power (perhaps minus the painted–on flames, though?) It’s not always easy to change others’ first impressions of us. We can don glasses but people won’t think we’re smarter. And, it can be even harder to change our own impression of ourselves. With God, though, real change happens. And those changes will eventually shine through. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Eph 4:17-6:24, Matt 26:1-13, Ps 109:1-15, Prov 17:27-28 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67233&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-09 15:07:06]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-09 15:07:06]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[21]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[primed, for, mation, word, day, ing, capable, painted, flames, though]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Be transformed by...renewing.]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[194]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4287]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Kin, Not Clones (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[kin-not-clones-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['May they be brought to complete unity.' John 17:23 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150711.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Truth time. We may not like to admit it, but sometimes we can subconsciously believe that we’re ‘better’ than someone else because we got this grade or that job. Our Church denomination is better or our social class is higher. John 17:23 tells us that God wants His children to be unified, and unity doesn’t allow for judgment. We can ignore lecturers and tolerate seemingly–silly ideas, with a forced smile, but our opinion of that other person has gone down. When this happens, immediately we’ve separated ourselves in spirit because of a difference of opinion. But we’re supposed to be different. God wants His children to be unified—but not by all being clones of each other. That said, ‘complete unity’ seems a tall order, doesn’t it? It is. Let’s be honest, it isn’t so easy to be unified with that guy who’s always one–upping you. We’ve all heard a bunch of talks or sermons about accepting people’s differences. We (probably) all agree with that rationally, and even in practice. What we’re likely to neglect is making accommodation in our mind for those who have a different way of thinking to us (ever got frustrated with someone who doesn’t do things your way?) That’s harder. But unity demands we learn to make room for others and respect their convictions. ‘Each one should be fully convinced in his own mind.’ (Romans 14:5 NIV) When you hear someone air an idea that opposes one of yours today, consider whether you’re actually listening, or if you’re just planning a lecture (even a silent–mental–lecture) entitled: ‘This is why you’re wrong.’ Really listen to what they say, and turn it into a fair conversation. You might learn something. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Sam 1:1-3:21, Matt 26:14-25, Ps 109:16-31, Prov 18:1-3 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67234&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-10 15:07:35]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-10 15:07:35]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[22]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[kin, accommodation, our, mind, for, those, who, have, different, way]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['May they be brought to comple]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[204]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4288]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Kin, Not Clones (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[kin-not-clones-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Have fervent love for one another.' 1 Peter 4:8 NKJ&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150712.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;‘Do nothing out of selfish ambition…value others above yourselves.’ (Philippians 2:3 NIV) You’ve heard it a hundred times: the golden rule, love your neighbour, etc. So why do people still talk about valuing others above yourself when everyone’s heard it a million times? Well, your Mum told you that sprouts were good for you a million times but did you eat them? Yeah. See what we mean? Christians talk about loving each other all the time because it’s important. It’s one thing to know you should be unified, it’s another to put aside pettiness and actually work for it. What we do affects other people whether we think about it or not, and quite often, when we inadvertently hurt someone, we feel awful. Or we can try to justify it: We were ‘only following the rules’. But when somebody else’s action affects us, we don’t tend to offer the same courtesy we offer ourselves. We attribute blame and assume that we know that their intention was to hurt us. For some reason, we don’t expect from others the same human weaknesses that we have. Jesus told us that love trumps everything. Paul said, ‘Everything is permissible—but not everything is beneficial.’ (1 Corinthians 10:23 NIV) He was talking about doing things that are ok but that other people might find offensive. And he basically says: think twice... then think again. Holding onto the view ‘but I did nothing wrong’ for the sake of offended pride is not on. Holding onto the spirit of Scripture that Jesus taught (again, love) is on. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: Gen 14:18-20, Ps 110, Heb 5:5-11 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67235&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-11 15:19:34]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-11 15:19:34]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[23]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[kin, about, doing, things, that, are, but, other, people, might]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Have fervent love for one ano]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[243]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4289]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Doing vs. Being]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[doing-vs-being]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['You cannot be fruitful unless you remain in Me.' John 15:4 NLT&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150713.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jesus tells us straight up that our successes lie in Him. End of story. Unless we’re doing things in His name and with His backing, it’s not going to work out. We have a problem when we try to emulate Jesus, without Jesus. A lot goes into the running of a Church and, when you get to a certain point in your Church life, you might think about helping out. That’s brilliant. It’s a great thing to want to use your talent with technology to set up the sound equipment, or to use your awesome coffee–making–and–smiling–at–the–same–time skills in joining the refreshment team. Sometimes, though, we can get caught up in wanting to help. Suddenly, we’re on twelve different rotas and we never actually get to sit and listen to a sermon. We’re doing all these things for God, but if we’re not building our relationship with Him, then we lose track of why we’re doing those things in the first place. James 2:26 famously says that ‘faith without works is dead’. But works without faith aren’t alive, either. They become a façade, sometimes even an at-tempt to buy favour with God! It doesn’t matter if you look like a Super Christian outwardly, if you’re not right with God inwardly. When we stop doing things in Him, we can’t succeed, and our efforts become meaningless. Spend an hour today not doing anything but waiting on God. No matter how much work you have to do, clear your schedule just for one hour. Sit with your Bible and a pen, and maybe some Spirit–focussed music. But just *be* in that hour, don’t worry about *doing* anything. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Sam 3:22-7:17, Matt 26:26-35, Ps 118:1-9, Prov 18:4-6 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67236&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-12 15:10:39]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-12 15:10:39]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[24]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[doing, things, his, name, and, with, backing, not, going, work]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['You cannot be fruitful unless]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[0]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4290]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Wait for it...]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[wait-for-it]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['The Lord has need of him.' Luke 19:34 NKJ&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150714.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you’re a Christian it’s less–than–great not knowing how God wants to use you. When people all around are talking about their callings and all’s quiet on the Heaven–front for you, it can be disheartening. But remember that story about the colt Jesus rode into Jerusalem? That colt had never been ridden and was tied to a tree, overlooked and underestimated by the people around him. But Jesus had ‘need of him’ and knew the right time to call for him. Now, you’re not a baby horse (or a baby goat. Neigh, we kid you not), but the same applies in your life. You’ve heard that God has a plan for you and you may be wondering what that is (or not; if you already know, then that’s prettyyyy cool). However we have to remember that plans run on a schedule and, unlike ours, God’s plans tend to stay on schedule. He’s going to call you when He knows the time is right. That can be difficult to accept, but let’s face it, God’s plan is better than anything we could come up with. Jesus was never influenced by other people’s opinions. It didn’t matter that the colt was overlooked or the prostitute was looked down upon or that everyone hated the taxman, Jesus still loved them and had a purpose for them. He knows your value better than others do, and better than you do. So, try this reminder: when you’re making tea tonight, stop cooking halfway through and see if you’d want to eat it. Bet you’d rather wait until it’s cooked and ready. Some things you just have to wait for. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Sam 7:18-11:27, Matt 26:36-46, Ps 118:10-18, Prov 18:7-9 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67237&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-13 15:32:32]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-13 15:32:32]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[25]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[wait, until, cooked, and, ready, some, things, you, just, have]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['The Lord has need of him.' Lu]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[0]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4291]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Muscle Memory Prayer (1)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[muscle-memory-prayer-1]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA['Whatever you ask for in prayer, believe...and it will be yours.' Mark 11:24 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{mp3remote}http://www.thewordfortoday.com.au/media/twftaudio/20150715.mp3{/mp3remote}&lt;br /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s pray. Hands together. Sound like a familiar instinct? If you were taught to pray as a kid, it’s probably muscle memory. You likely also felt that rush of rebellion as you sneakily took a peek around the assembly hall to see if anyone ‘wasn’t praying right.’ But you’ve probably realised that God doesn’t care if your hands are together, at your sides, or raised in the air. Prayer isn’t about hand placement. There’s a cool thought from William Ward: ‘We stamp and address an envelope and send it on its way with complete confidence that it will reach its destination. Yet we wonder and even doubt if our prayers will be heard by an ever–present, ever–loving God.’ When Peter told a man who couldn’t walk to get up and go, it didn’t happen because he thought, half–heartedly, ‘Meh, might as well give it a go.’ It happened because he knew that God has real power, and would answer his prayer. God rewarded Peter’s sincere faith. We can get caught up in the words of a prayer or the length of it. It can be hard to remember that prayer is just a way of telling God that we’re ready and believing. Peter simply said, ‘In the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, rise up and walk’ (Acts 3:6 ESV), and it happened. God knows already what we want to say. So pray in a way you’re comfortable with, and keep an eye out for answers. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Sam 12:1-14:20, Matt 26:47-56, Ps 118:19-29, Prov 18:10-12 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;i&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/i&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia.  2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src='http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;track=67238&amp;www=blog' height='0' width='0' alt=''&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-14 15:12:09]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[0]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-14 15:12:09]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[1]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[26]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[muscle, memory, you, sneakily, took, peek, around, the, assembly, hall]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Whatever you ask for in praye]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[201]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4292]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Muscle Memory Prayer (2)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[muscle-memory-prayer-2]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'When you pray, go into your room, close the door.' Matthew 6:6 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all been in that situation: in church (or youth group or life group...) and somebody’s been praying when suddenly you’re saying ‘Amen’ with no idea what the prayer was about. Your mind wandered. Again. Oops. Today we’re not usually very good at putting all of our attention on one thing. We listen to music while we work, we watch sitcoms while we clean. We’re not always great with staying focused on God when there’s a billion other things going on around us. Sometimes, we fall asleep before we reach Amen. If you relate, don’t worry, you’re not a bad Christian, and you’re definitely not the only one who does that sort of thing. Turns out God knows us pretty well, He foresaw all of that, and gave us some handy tips via the Bible. Through them, we can re–learn how to be delighted with prayer, and in the real, living relationship we have with God. Matthew 6 tells us to be real in our prayers, no posturing or showing off or the like. ‘...go into your room, close the door.’ (Matthew 6:6 NIV) By closing the door you’re putting yourself in the mindset of being closed off from distractions to focus all of your attention on God. It may feel like there are so many other things you should be doing that you can’t afford to close the door, but what better way to deal with those worries than to bring them to God? Try physically closing the door when you pray to shut out distractions, and, for the next week, try writing your prayers down in a notebook and putting them away to be remembered later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Sam 14:21-17:13, Matt 26:57-75, Ps 123, Prov 18:13-16 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67239&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-15 15:07:59]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-07-23 03:52:21]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-15 15:07:59]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[27]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[muscle, memory, prayer, was, about, your, room, close, the, door]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['When you pray, go into your r]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[160]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4293]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Muscle Memory Prayer (3)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[muscle-memory-prayer-3]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...ask whatever you wish, and it will be done for you.' John 15:7 NLT&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 15:7 doesn’t give us licence to treat God like a magic genie. We don’t just tell Him what we want and watch it appear in a puff of smoke. (Even if we did expect that as kids—praying for whatever we wanted, off the top of our heads. Chocolate. A pony. A barrel of spider monkeys wearing tophats.) But there’s a first part to that verse. And it rolls out like this: ‘Abide vitally united to Me…’ (John 15:7 AMP) Our life comes from God. We’re vitally con-nected to Him. And He’s connected to us—it goes on to say: ‘...and [if] My words remain in you, ask whatever you wish, and it will be done for you.’ Get your teeth into your Bible and you’ll naturally be praying that bit more in line with the things that God wants to do anyway. When you’re obedient to Him, your desires will start to look more like His will. James 4:3 NIV says: ‘...when you ask, you do not receive, because you ask with wrong motives…’ So let’s check our motives; be willing to let God change your desires, too. This might have to be re–learned from old habits of praying selfishly (no more barrels of spider monkeys, sigh.) Once you’re living and moving in–tune with God and His will, ‘...ask whatever you wish, and it will be done for you.’ Been writing down your prayers like we suggested yesterday? Good. Now, go back through them, and for each one that requests something, think about why you’re asking it: what are your desires, are they in line with God’s will?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Sam 17:14-19:43, Matt 27:1-10, Ps 133, Prov 18:17-20 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67240&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-16 15:09:27]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-07-23 03:51:58]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-16 15:09:27]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[28]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[muscle, memory, prayer, like, suggested, yesterday, good, now, back, through]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...ask whatever you wish, and]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[135]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4294]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Muscle Memory Prayer (4)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[muscle-memory-prayer-4]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...Seek His face always...' 1 Chronicles 16:11 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br id=&quot;system-readmore&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, in the days before the paparazzi trailed celebs and royals everywhere, it was quite common for the average person to have no idea what a famous person looked like. No magazines, no photographs, no paintings. In the ancient world, even people working in the palace all their lives might never get close enough to know what the king actually looked like. Seeking God’s face always means desiring to have continual access to God’s presence. To be with Him. To feel His reassuring closeness. All the time. But how can we do that continually when life can be so busy? Sometimes finding time in the middle of things is hard. It’s great to take time outside of our busy activity to pray. Sometimes we need that close presence in the ‘always’ ongoing bit of our lives. Psalm 16:11 AMP says that in God’s presence ‘is fullness of joy’. Here’s a fact: when you’re *in* your day, all wrapped up in the minute–by–minute stuff, God is still with you. You are still able to know that. Making God the focus of your day, your life, each second is easier said than done, but in each decision you make and in each word you speak, make that conscious effort to look up to God. It’s worth it. So: for today, here’s a task. On the hour, every hour, say hi to God, and bring one thing from the past hour to Him. Ask Him to be in the next 60 minutes, too. Just quickly make the effort to check in with Him. Set reminders on your phone, if necessary.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Sam 20:1-22:30, Matt 27:11-26, Ps 140, Prov 18:21-22&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67241&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-17 15:05:42]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-07-23 03:51:38]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-17 15:05:42]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[29]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[muscle, memory, prayer, word, day, seek, his, face, always, chronicles]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...Seek His face always...' 1]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[150]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4295]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Muscle Memory Prayer (5)]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[muscle-memory-prayer-5]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'...He fell with His face to the ground and prayed...' Matthew 26:39 NIV&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Matthew 26 we see Jesus in a very human light. He knows what’s about to happen—Judas will betray Him—so He takes His disciples to a garden called Gethsemane. He chose to walk a bit further than they did, to pray alone. You might ask why Jesus separated Himself to pray. There is no straight–cut answer but it’s possible that, by being alone, He had greater room to express His emotions. He tells the closest three disciples: ‘My soul is exceedingly sorrowful…’ (Matthew 26:38 NIV) Sometimes, it’s good to be alone before God and pour your heart out to Him without holding back (maybe more than we already do). Three times Jesus prays, ‘Let this cup be taken from Me,’ (Matthew 26:39 NIV) but He follows it up with: ‘Your will be done.’ (Matthew 26:42 NIV) Three times. When you’re battling your human emotions, it’s a good call to keep going back to God and recommitting yourself to Him. This is a crucial moment in Jesus’ life, and we gain insight into how He poured this out to God. Right. That’s a fairly privileged position. If Jesus (God Himself) let loose and literally cried out to His heavenly Father, despite who He is, what does that teach us? Don’t be afraid to open up the very, very weakest parts of yourself to God. Don’t forget that Jesus knows already; He told His disciples: ‘The spirit is willing, but the flesh is weak.’ (Matthew 26:41 NIV) We can take encouragement in that, because God knows how much we need Him; we don’t need to be perfect to approach Him in prayer. Whatever you’ve been praying about recently, whatever is really on your heart, pray for it three times, at three different points today. SoulFood: Gen 5:22–24, Heb 11:5, 2 Kings 2:1–12&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67242&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-18 15:06:56]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-07-23 03:51:18]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-18 15:06:56]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[30]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[muscle, memory, prayer, whatever, really, your, heart, pray, for, three]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['...He fell with His face to t]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[157]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><content mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4296]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Loaves Before Ducks]]></title>
<alias><![CDATA[loaves-before-ducks]]></alias>
<title_alias><![CDATA[]]></title_alias>
<introtext><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;'Cast your bread upon the waters...' Ecclesiastes 11:1 ESV &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You didn’t read that wrong, that’s an actual verse in the Bible… What’s it going on about? Should we be feeding more ducks or something? Here’s a basic outline of what’s going on. The same as now, bread back in long, long ago times was used for food; the more bread or grain farmers sent out in trade, the more places it reached, the more they would get back. It’s really simple. Jesus liked to use ‘everyday’ examples to get across the point. Stick with us here: our ‘grain’ can be taken to mean our gifts and talents. Like a labourer trying to get a good return, we can share what we have with others (no matter who they are) to bless them. Why? Well, when we use our gifts in lots of diverse ways and reach out to as many people as we can with them, there’s a principle at work: ‘...after many days you may receive a return’ (that’s the other half of verse 11). Chip away at the things you do, day by day. Watch as God grows you and the situation you’re in. You reap what you sow. (An agricultural way of saying that you get back what you give out.) God wants to use you in the ways He has gifted you, but you need to put yourself out there for that to happen. What has God been calling you in to? If you can feel God nudging you in a particular direction, note it down. Then pray about it to discern if it’s His will for your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;SoulFood: 2 Sam 22:31-24:25, Matt 27:27-32, Ps 146, Prov 18:23-24 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;word4U2day &lt;em&gt;(an adaptation of The Word for Today authored by Bob &amp;amp; Debby Gass)&lt;/em&gt; is published under licence by UCB Australia. 2015 UCB International Ltd&lt;/small&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://word.ucbmedia.com/includes/track/track.php?b=4&amp;amp;track=67255&amp;amp;www=blog&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;]]></introtext>
<fulltext><![CDATA[]]></fulltext>
<state><![CDATA[1]]></state>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
<mask><![CDATA[0]]></mask>
<catid><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></catid>
<created><![CDATA[2015-07-19 15:14:58]]></created>
<created_by><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></created_by>
<created_by_alias><![CDATA[]]></created_by_alias>
<modified><![CDATA[2015-07-23 03:50:59]]></modified>
<modified_by><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></modified_by>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<publish_up><![CDATA[2015-07-19 15:14:58]]></publish_up>
<publish_down><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></publish_down>
<images><![CDATA[]]></images>
<urls><![CDATA[]]></urls>
<attribs><![CDATA[show_title=
link_titles=
show_intro=
show_section=
link_section=
show_category=
link_category=
show_vote=
show_author=
show_create_date=
show_modify_date=
show_pdf_icon=
show_print_icon=
show_email_icon=
language=
keyref=
readmore=]]></attribs>
<version><![CDATA[2]]></version>
<parentid><![CDATA[0]]></parentid>
<ordering><![CDATA[31]]></ordering>
<metakey><![CDATA[loaves, before, ducks, something, here, our, grain, can, taken, mean]]></metakey>
<metadesc><![CDATA['Cast your bread upon the wate]]></metadesc>
<metadata><![CDATA[robots=
author=]]></metadata>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<hits><![CDATA[111]]></hits>
<frontpage><![CDATA[0]]></frontpage>
</content><section mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[8]]></id>
<title><![CDATA[Broadcast]]></title>
<name><![CDATA[]]></name>
<alias><![CDATA[broadcast]]></alias>
<image><![CDATA[]]></image>
<scope><![CDATA[content]]></scope>
<image_position><![CDATA[left]]></image_position>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
<published><![CDATA[1]]></published>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<ordering><![CDATA[7]]></ordering>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<params><![CDATA[]]></params>
</section><category mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[33]]></id>
<parent_id><![CDATA[0]]></parent_id>
<title><![CDATA[word4U2day]]></title>
<name><![CDATA[]]></name>
<alias><![CDATA[word4u2day]]></alias>
<image><![CDATA[]]></image>
<image_position><![CDATA[left]]></image_position>
<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
<published><![CDATA[1]]></published>
<checked_out><![CDATA[0]]></checked_out>
<checked_out_time><![CDATA[0000-00-00 00:00:00]]></checked_out_time>
<ordering><![CDATA[10]]></ordering>
<access><![CDATA[0]]></access>
<params><![CDATA[]]></params>
<sectionid><![CDATA[broadcast]]></sectionid>
</category><user mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[4372]]></id>
<name><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></name>
<username><![CDATA[Aletheia]]></username>
<email><![CDATA[aletheia@ucbmedia.com]]></email>
<password><![CDATA[332c6062e0e3b289d5909c9a5450b859:UKLPpC8WaK6JYoAtd5w6pwdJsKOpXYPu]]></password>
<usertype><![CDATA[Administrator]]></usertype>
<block><![CDATA[0]]></block>
<sendEmail><![CDATA[0]]></sendEmail>
<gid><![CDATA[24]]></gid>
<registerDate><![CDATA[2013-01-14 04:26:20]]></registerDate>
<lastvisitDate><![CDATA[2014-06-02 05:00:10]]></lastvisitDate>
<activation><![CDATA[]]></activation>
<params><![CDATA[admin_language=en-GB
language=en-GB
editor=
helpsite=
timezone=10

]]></params>
</user><user mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[2360]]></id>
<name><![CDATA[Anne Hamilton]]></name>
<username><![CDATA[ahamilton]]></username>
<email><![CDATA[ahamilton@ucb.com.au]]></email>
<password><![CDATA[77349b84e521fec14e778b58376d1b7e:Rs5uKU8QMFXKsUzAiasA6Xy7kpPrThsb]]></password>
<usertype><![CDATA[Administrator]]></usertype>
<block><![CDATA[0]]></block>
<sendEmail><![CDATA[0]]></sendEmail>
<gid><![CDATA[24]]></gid>
<registerDate><![CDATA[2009-12-04 00:01:26]]></registerDate>
<lastvisitDate><![CDATA[2015-08-11 04:01:58]]></lastvisitDate>
<activation><![CDATA[]]></activation>
<params><![CDATA[admin_language=
language=
editor=jce
helpsite=
timezone=10

]]></params>
</user><user mapkeystotext="true"><id><![CDATA[1123]]></id>
<name><![CDATA[Grant Kennedy]]></name>
<username><![CDATA[gkennedy]]></username>
<email><![CDATA[gkennedy@ucb.com.au]]></email>
<password><![CDATA[2c1254eec94d77359316370e0ab0d994:ns4oKlgpodxSB6vTneF3cmpOcoC5cjZ3]]></password>
<usertype><![CDATA[Super Administrator]]></usertype>
<block><![CDATA[0]]></block>
<sendEmail><![CDATA[1]]></sendEmail>
<gid><![CDATA[25]]></gid>
<registerDate><![CDATA[2009-04-16 01:37:00]]></registerDate>
<lastvisitDate><![CDATA[2015-08-05 03:05:05]]></lastvisitDate>
<activation><![CDATA[]]></activation>
<params><![CDATA[admin_language=
language=
editor=
helpsite=
timezone=10

]]></params>
</user></j2xml>