<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" lang="en-GB"><head><title>???</title><meta content="Hamilton" name="author"/><meta content="2015-09-28T21:15:00Z" name="dcterms.created"/><meta content="2015-09-28T21:15:00Z" name="dcterms.modified"/><meta content="United Christian Broadcasters Australia Ltd" name="dcterms.publisher"/><meta content="XMLmind Word To XML Professional Edition 1.0.0-beta04" name="generator"/></head><body>
<p>October 31</p>
<p>‘…take up the whole armour of God…’ Ephesians 6:13 NKJ</p>
<p>Drawing the Line</p>
<p>Simon the Sorcerer was doing good business. The people ‘…followed him because he had amazed them for a long time with his magic.’ (Acts 8:11 NIV) But, no doubt to everyone’s astonishment, he chose to accept the Gospel message and got baptised. Sadly though, before long, traces of his old ways emerged: he offered Peter and John money to buy the gift of the Holy Spirit! How did the apostles handle this? Simple! They confronted this guy with the truth in Jesus’ name, saying: ‘Repent of this wickedness and pray to the Lord.’ (Acts 8:22 NIV) You see, Peter knew something that we should all know: when a new Christian starts turning back to their old ways you must quickly deal with it or they’ll end up hurting themselves and other people too. Being fuzzy and soft in those moments helps no–one. <br></br>For all of us, whether disciples for 10 minutes or 10 years, the forces of evil around us are real; we can’t just ignore them and hope they’ll play nice or maybe just go away. To fight and win you must know what you are up against. There’ll be times when you have to be decisive and draw a line saying, ‘That’s it, the other side of this line is out of bounds for me now that I follow Jesus.’ Do you need to draw or re–draw some lines around your life today?</p>
<p>SoulFood (Halloween): Deut 18:9–18, Dan 2, Is 47:5–15, Acts 16:16–34 </p></body></html>